<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Alcohol Alcohol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Alcohol Alcohol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">alcalc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">alcalc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Alcohol and Alcoholism (Oxford, Oxfordshire)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0735-0414</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-3502</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443987</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3633362</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/alcalc/agt009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">agt009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence and Patterns of Hazardous and Harmful Alcohol Consumption Assessed Using the AUDIT among Bhutanese Refugees in Nepal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luitel</surname><given-names>Nagendra P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jordans</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>Adrianna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Bayard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCambridge</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Transcultural Psychosocial Organization (TPO) Nepal</institution>, <addr-line>Baluwatar, Kathmandu</addr-line>, <country>Nepal</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Research &#x00026; Development</addr-line>, <institution>HealthNet TPO</institution>, <addr-line>Lizzy Ansinghstraat 163, Amsterdam 1073 RG,</addr-line><country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Center for Global Mental Health</addr-line>, <institution>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Keppel St, London WC1E 7HT</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Faculty of Public Health &#x00026; Policy</addr-line>, <institution>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>15-17 Tavistock Place, London WC1H 9SH</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Tel.: +977-1-4431717/977-9841333725; E-mail: <email>luitelnp@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Medical Council on Alcohol.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="agt009.pdf"/><abstract><p><bold>Aims</bold>: This study sought to ascertain the prevalence of hazardous and harmful alcohol consumption among Bhutanese refugees in Nepal and to identify predictors of elevated risk in order to better understand intervention need. <bold>Methods</bold>: Hazardous and harmful alcohol consumption was assessed using the Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test (AUDIT) administered in a face-to-face interview in a census of two camps comprising &#x0223c;8000 refugees. <bold>Results</bold>: Approximately 1/5 men and 1/14 women drank alcohol and prevalence of hazardous drinking among current drinkers was high and comparable to that seen in Western countries with longstanding alcohol cultures. Harmful drinking was particularly associated with the use of other substances including tobacco. <bold>Conclusions</bold>: Assessment of the alcohol-related needs of Bhutanese refugees has permitted the design of interventions. This study adds to the small international literature on substance use in forced migration populations, about which there is growing concern.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May/June 2013</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Concerns have been expressed about hazardous and harmful alcohol use amongst populations who have been forcibly displaced from their homes by armed conflict, human rights abuses and persecution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C23">Johnson, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C7">de Jong, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C47">UNHCR and WHO, 2008</xref>). These forcibly displaced persons include around 26.4 million internally displaced persons (IDPs) who have fled their homes but remain within their own country, 10.4 million refugees who have crossed into another country, and 876,000 asylum seekers who have applied for refugee status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C16">IDMC, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C46">UNHCR, 2012</xref>). Forced displacement is usually protracted, with most people affected living in these situations for &#x0003e;5 years, and often for decades. Policies and programmes thus need to embrace both short-term humanitarian relief and longer-term developmental concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C28">Loescher and Milner, 2009</xref>).</p><p>Forcibly displaced people can be exposed to high levels of violent and traumatic events related to armed conflict and displacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C17">Ingleby, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C32">Porter and Haslam, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C42">Steel <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). It commonly also leads to worse living conditions; impoverishment and the loss of family; friends; assets; livelihoods and self-esteem and cultural and social support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C31">Miller and Rasco, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C32">Porter and Haslam, 2005</xref>). Alcohol use may act as a coping strategy in response to such exposure to traumatic events and social stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C36">Rhodes and Jason, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C23">Johnson, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C26">Kozaric-Kovacic <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C29">Marshall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C14">Galea <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C37">Roberts <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Perhaps unsurprisingly, there are strong associations of traumatic experiences and daily stressors with mental health problems such as post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and depression and anxiety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C8">de Jong <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C31">Miller and Rasco, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C32">Porter and Haslam, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C42">Steel <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). These are also associated with hazardous and harmful alcohol use, which has been viewed by some as a form of self-medicating the physiological, behavioural, affective and cognitive symptoms of these problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C43">Stewart, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C24">Kessler <italic>et al</italic>., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C5">Chilcoat and Breslau, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C4">Breslau <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C38">Sacco <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C25">Kizza <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). For example, qualitative studies have explored how refugee men and women from Kenya, Laos and Cambodia drank alcohol as means of trying to cope with symptoms of stress and forgetting past events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C6">D'Avanzo and Frye, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C1">Adelekan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C27">Lee <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Despite these risk factors for hazardous alcohol use among forcibly displaced persons, the evidence base is weak on the prevalence and patterns of alcohol use. Systematic reviews have noted limitations including the very small number of studies, particularly in low and middle-income countries which is where the vast majority of forcibly displaced populations live, weak sampling designs, limited statistical analysis and limited use of validated instruments to assess hazardous alcohol use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C49">Weaver and Roberts, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C10">Ezard, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The few studies of hazardous alcohol use among forcibly displaced persons have consistently shown higher levels of hazardous alcohol use among men compared with women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C19">Jenkins <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C26">Kozaric-Kovacic <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C29">Marshall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C41">Steel <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C33">Puertas <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C20">Jeon <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C27">Lee <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C37">Roberts <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C12">Ezard <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Evidence on the influence of age is more mixed, with younger age associated with hazardous alcohol use in two studies of South East Asian refugees in the USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C29">Marshall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C27">Lee <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>), while a study of IDPs in northern Uganda observed higher levels among older age groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C37">Roberts <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). A number of studies have shown associations between hazardous drinking and exposure to violent and traumatic events, both from the conflict and after displacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C26">Kozaric-Kovacic <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C29">Marshall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C37">Roberts <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Since 1990, more than 100,000 Bhutanese Refugees have fled to Nepal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C48">van Ommeren <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). These refugees, called Lhotsampas, are ethnically Nepali, the majority group in southern Bhutan. Bhutan claims that this group of people left willingly and that they were never citizens of Bhutan. The refugees claim that they were forced to leave Bhutan because of their ethnicity. In 1992, UNHCR established the first camps and since then, they have been living in seven refugee camps in eastern Nepal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C18">IOM Damak, 2008</xref>). Camp settlement was managed in such a way that people from same village were kept in the same camp. Many want to return to their homes in Bhutan. Despite this desire, and notwithstanding numerous high-level meetings between the governments of Bhutan and Nepal to resolve the refugee crisis over the past 20 years, Bhutan has not permitted any refugee to return home. Moreover, Nepali government policy has not allowed the integration of refugees into the local community. With neither repatriation nor local integration realistically possible for the majority of refugees, resettlement to a third country emerged as an alternative. In 2007, the Bhutanese refugees began a second phase of migration as the USA along with several other Western nations signed third-country resettlement agreements. Initially, a significant number of the refugees were against resettlement to a third country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C18">IOM Damak, 2008</xref>), however since then, &#x0223c;65,000 of the Bhutanese have found new homes in other countries. This leaves &#x0223c;45,000 Bhutanese refugees living in the seven refugee camps in eastern Nepal. Qualitative studies undertaken by non-governmental organizations have revealed concerns about alcohol problems. The extent of these problems was unknown, however, hence the rationale for the current study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>METHODS</title><p>This study was conducted in two refugee camps, Goldhap and Timai, located in the eastern part of Jhapa district, during May&#x02013;June 2010. These two camps were selected in order to develop and pilot an alcohol prevention program, which could be replicated in other camps. We used a census method based on the updated list of the refugee population provided by the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR). The study thus targeted the entire population of 8501 aged 15 years and older in the two camps. Of these 8021 (94%) participated in the study and rates of non-participation were similar in both camps (Goldhap 183/3843, 5% and Timai 297/4658, 6%).</p><p>Face-to-face interviews were undertaken with the respondents in their own residence. Each interview was conducted individually by a gender-matched research assistant, one of 22 with at least intermediate level education hired from the same refugee community. Three days training were provided on study objectives, basics of quantitative research, informed consent and interviewing skills including role-playing. All participants were informed about the nature of the study, and consent was obtained verbally as is common in humanitarian populations, including amongst Bhutanese refugees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C48">van Ommeren <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). The study protocol was also approved by the camp management committee (CMC) and UNHCR Nepal office. There were 47 refusals to participate and 78 potential participants were unable to speak. Pre-testing of the instrument was conducted in a separate refugee camp.</p><p>The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) was used to assess hazardous and harmful drinking. It was originally developed by the World Health Organization (WHO) as a screening instrument in primary health care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C39">Saunders <italic>et al</italic>., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C3">Babor <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>), with a well-validated threshold score of 8 for hazardous or harmful consumption and a score of 20 or greater suggested as indicating possible alcohol dependence. The AUDIT has been found to be suitable for use, with good psychometric properties, in identifying hazardous or harmful consumption across a variety of health care settings and among patients of different cultural backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C2">Adewuya, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C35">Reinert and Allen, 2007</xref>). More recently, the AUDIT has been used in settings other than health care and scores obtained from the AUDIT used to make inferences about the severity of problems in the absence of thresholds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C30">McCambridge and Thomas, 2009</xref>).</p><p>One difficulty that can arise in use of the AUDIT is in estimating consumption of non-standardized drinks. Since there are similarities in various aspects of alcohol consumption between Nepal and India, we have used the same conversion factor of reported consumption of local beverages to standardized drinks (equivalent to 10 g of alcohol) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C50">Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Using the above standard (10 g of alcohol as one peg), two mana (local quantity term) or 1200 ml Chhang/Jad (locally made beverage from rice/corn/millet) or three glasses of local Rakshi (locally distilled alcohol) or two bottles of beer (750 ml each) or a small bottle of vodka are the equivalent to six pegs or standard drinks.</p><p>The Statistical Software for Social Science package (SPSS 19.0) was used for data entry and analysis. Samples from the Goldhap and Timai camps were combined to improve statistical power, with camp included as a variable in the analysis. Three outcome measures were used: hazardous or harmful alcohol consumption (AUDIT score &#x0003e;7), possible alcohol dependence (AUDIT score &#x0003e;19) and an AUDIT score as a continuous outcome. First, we performed an unadjusted regression analysis using each covariate of interest (gender, age category, caste/ethnicity, educational status, religion, marital status, resettlement status, working status, history of alcohol use in the family, smoking and tobacco use, substance use and camp) to test for an association with each outcome. Logistic regression was used for the binary outcomes of hazardous alcohol consumption and alcohol dependence; linear regression was used for the AUDIT score as a continuous outcome. Only those covariates that showed a significant association with the outcome in the unadjusted analysis were included in the adjusted model and no other model selection criteria were applied.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AGT009TB1">1</xref> shows the socio-demographic characteristics of the study population. The sample was almost evenly split between males and females and the mean age was 35.3 years. Respondents were most commonly married, of the Brahmin/Chhetri or Janajati caste and Hindu. A significant proportion of the sample were illiterate and not currently in paid work (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AGT009TB1">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="AGT009TB1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Socio-demographic characteristic of study population<sup>a</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goldhap camp (<italic>n</italic> = 3660)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Timai camp (<italic>n</italic> = 4361)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (<italic>n</italic> = 8021)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age groups</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;15&#x02013;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;20&#x02013;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;25&#x02013;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;35&#x02013;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;45&#x02013;54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e;55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4 (16.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2 (16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3 (16.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Education</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Illiterate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Non-formal education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Primary level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Lower secondary level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Secondary level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Intermediate and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not stated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Caste/ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Brahmin/Chhetri</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Janajati</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Dalit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Widow/widower</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Separated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not stated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Religion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Hindu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Buddhist</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Christian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Kirat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Resettlement status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No-declaration of interest for resettlement (DOI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;DOI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;DOI and in the process of resettlement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Prefer not to say</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Working status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Currently working for earning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Total does not add up to 100 due to exclusion of respondents who refused to answer or answered &#x02018;do not know&#x02019;.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The prevalence of hazardous drinking (AUDIT score &#x0003e;7) and alcohol dependence (AUDIT score &#x0003e;19) in the study population were 2.8% (<italic>n</italic> = 222) [males 5.1% (<italic>n</italic> = 198) and females 0.6% (<italic>n</italic> = 24)] and 0.6% (<italic>n</italic> = 51) [males 1.2% (<italic>n</italic> = 46) and females 0.1% (<italic>n</italic> = 5)], respectively. The prevalence of current alcohol consumption (defined as any response other than &#x02018;never&#x02019; to AUDIT question 1), as well as of hazardous or harmful drinking (AUDIT score &#x0003e;7) and possible alcohol dependence (AUDIT score &#x0003e;19), among those who reported drinking is given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AGT009TB2">2</xref>. The prevalence of each of these was higher among males compared with females but there was no clear pattern by age group.
<table-wrap id="AGT009TB2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Prevalence by gender and age</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Age category</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Current drinking<hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hazardous/harmful drinking<sup>a</sup><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Possible dependence<sup>b</sup><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women, <italic>n</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (11.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (22.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x02013;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207 (22.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (7.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#x02013;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (10.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (19.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (9.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x02013;54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (27.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (10.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (23.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (23.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (29.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (6.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">876 (22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">279 (6.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (22.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (8.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>(AUDIT score &#x0003e;7) among current drinkers.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>(AUDIT score &#x0003e;19) among current drinkers.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The odds of hazardous or harmful alcohol consumption associated with each of our covariates of interest are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AGT009TB3">3</xref>. In the unadjusted models, gender, education, religion, working status, history of alcohol use, tobacco use, substance use and camp were all statistically significantly associated with hazardous alcohol consumption. The adjusted model controlled for these covariates and found that males, those who have a history of alcohol use in the family, those who use tobacco, those who use other substances and those living in Timai camp all exhibit higher odds of hazardous alcohol consumption, whilst those with &#x02018;intermediate or above&#x02019; education exhibit lower odds. Tobacco is used by placing in the mouth, as well as by smoking. Only 25 people used other substances last month, of which the great majority (<italic>n</italic> = 23) used marijuana. Two participants reported injecting drugs, and although for the majority other substance use was infrequent, for approximately one-third (9/25) this was daily.
<table-wrap id="AGT009TB3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Odds of hazardous or harmful drinking (AUDIT score &#x0003e;7), among current drinkers (<italic>n</italic> = 1155)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Covariate</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted<hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98&#x02013;4.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71&#x02013;4.64</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;15&#x02013;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;20&#x02013;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56&#x02013;2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;25&#x02013;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45&#x02013;1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;35&#x02013;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40&#x02013;1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;45&#x02013;54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50&#x02013;2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;55+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59&#x02013;2.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Caste/ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Brahmin/Chhetri</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Janajati</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54&#x02013;1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56&#x02013;1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Educational status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Illiterate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No-formal/primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#x02013;1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69&#x02013;1.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Lower secondary/secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81&#x02013;1.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#x02013;2.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Intermediate or above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#x02013;0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16&#x02013;0.75</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Religion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Hindu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Buddhist</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60&#x02013;1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48&#x02013;1.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Christian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16&#x02013;3.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#x02013;2.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Kirat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40&#x02013;1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#x02013;1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45&#x02013;2.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#x02013;1.98</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93&#x02013;1.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Widow/widower</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#x02013;1.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Separated/divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#x02013;4.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Resettlement status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Non-DOI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;DOI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78&#x02013;1.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;DOI and in the process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#x02013;1.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Working status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Currently working for earning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14&#x02013;2.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#x02013;1.67</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">History of alcohol use in the family</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04&#x02013;2.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07&#x02013;2.25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Smoking and tobacco use</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67&#x02013;3.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35&#x02013;3.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substance use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64&#x02013;31.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.77***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90&#x02013;29.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Goldhap</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Timai</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06&#x02013;2.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07&#x02013;2.25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 and ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; DOI = declaration of interest for resettlement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>For possible alcohol dependence, males (OR = 3.03, 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.19&#x02013;7.72), those who reported being Christian (compared with being Hindu, OR = 2.19 [1.31&#x02013;7.77]), currently working for pay (OR = 2.03 [1.07&#x02013;3.85]), using tobacco (OR = 3.06 [1.20&#x02013;7.78]) and using other substances (OR = 11.55 [4.48&#x02013;29.76]) were all at higher odds of alcohol dependence in the unadjusted model. Of these only Christian religion (OR = 2.78 [1.09&#x02013;7.07]) and substance use (OR = 7.84 [2.89&#x02013;21.24]) remained statistically significantly associated with alcohol dependence in the adjusted model.</p><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AGT009TB4">4</xref> presents data using the AUDIT score as a continuous outcome. In the unadjusted analysis, being male, Christian, working for pay, having a history of alcohol use in the family, smoking, substance use and living in Timai camp were all associated with higher AUDIT scores while &#x02018;intermediate education or above&#x02019; and Kirat religion were associated with lower scores. All of these covariates except for Christian religion, work status and camp remained significant in the adjusted model.
<table-wrap id="AGT009TB4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Associations between AUDIT score and socio-demographic characteristics among current drinkers (<italic>n</italic> = 1155)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Covariate</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted<hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23&#x02013;2.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87&#x02013;2.67</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;15&#x02013;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;20&#x02013;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.52 to 0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;25&#x02013;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.76 to 0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;35&#x02013;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.60 to 0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;45&#x02013;54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.67 to 0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e;55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.14 to 1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Caste/ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Brahmin/Chhetri</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Janajati</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.64 to 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.96 to 0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Educational status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Illiterate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No-formal/primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.28 to 1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.84 to 0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Lower secondary/secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.38 to 1.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.27 to 0.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Intermediate or above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.44*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.73 to &#x02212;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.81**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.12 to &#x02212;0.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Religion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Hindu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Buddhist</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.72 to 0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.03 to 0.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Christian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#x02013;3.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.34 to 2.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Kirat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.06*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.10 to &#x02212;0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.18 to &#x02212;0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.09 to 1.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.33 to 1.40</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.41 to 1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Widow/widower</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.80 to 0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Separated/divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.36 to 3.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Resettlement status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Non-DOI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;DOI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.34 to 1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;DOI and in the process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00&#x02013;0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Working status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Currently working for earning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#x02013;1.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.38 to 1.12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">History of alcohol use in the family</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#x02013;1.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35&#x02013;1.88</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Smoking and tobacco use</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05&#x02013;2.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48&#x02013;2.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Substance use</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.41***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89&#x02013;10.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.69***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20&#x02013;10.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Camp</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Goldhap</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Timai</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03&#x02013;1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.10 to 1.44</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 and ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; DOI = declaration of interest for resettlement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This is the first study of hazardous and harmful alcohol use among Bhutanese refugees. It also adds to the currently very limited evidence base on alcohol use and displacement, particularly in low-income countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C49">Weaver and Roberts, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C10">Ezard, 2012</xref>), and the limited research globally on alcohol use in low-income settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C34">Rajendram <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Rates of hazardous and harmful drinking seen here are lower than in some other forced migration populations and higher than others. The prevalence of alcohol dependence among the Bhutanese refugees is lower than general population in the city of Dharan in Nepal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C21">Jhingan <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>), and comparable with that of the general population in Kathmandu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C40">Shrestha <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). Among those who drink alcohol, the prevalence of hazardous drinking was high and comparable with that seen in general populations in Western countries. The prevalence of possible dependence among current drinkers is also similar to that seen in other populations. Findings of greater risk for hazardous and harmful drinking among men are in line with findings from other studies of forcibly displaced populations and with general population studies. The absence of clear patterning of alcohol-related risk by age is interesting and distinct from that seen in general populations. It is also interesting to note that status within the resettlement process, seen by many refugees as an additional stressor, was not associated with increased alcohol risk or problems in any of the analyses. These findings, to some extent, undermine the extent to which alcohol use may be seen as a coping strategy across this population as a whole.</p><p>The study also provides novel evidence on risk factors associated with hazardous alcohol that have not been reported in other studies of forcibly displaced persons. The study identifies the influence of a history of alcohol use in the family on hazardous drinking. It is also the first to examine the association of hazardous alcohol use with tobacco and other substance use among forcibly displaced population, and the findings suggest a similar pattern of their co-occurrence to studies from general populations globally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C13">Farrell <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C9">Drobes, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C22">John <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). Hazardous and harmful drinking were strongly associated with the use of other substances, and there is quite clearly a minority using multiple inter-related substances. As a result of this study, a range of activities has been initiated to reduce harms related to alcohol in the camps. These services include psycho-education, group work, individual counselling, detoxification and rehabilitation designed and targeted at those with increased risk of harmful drinking. This is especially useful given the stigma attached to help-seeking relating to alcohol use and mental health problems in general.</p><p>This study has strengths including the use of the AUDIT and the conduct of multivariate analyses to address possible confounding in identification of risk factors. We decided not to use a multi-level model, nesting the data with camp, so as to simplify the analyses. This means that camp-level influences such as differential alcohol availability are not addressed by this study. It is also the case that some findings are influenced by relatively small numbers in some cells, for example in relation to possible dependence and other substance use. Although the AUDIT is brief and efficient in capturing a number of outcomes of interest, therein lies a limitation of this study as more detailed measures of the outcomes of interest may yield more valuable data. The study context is also important to consider. Many of the respondents were in the process of being resettled, and may have been reluctant to share information on their drinking behaviour if they thought it might create a problem in being resettled. This possibility may have been exacerbated by stigma associated with alcohol use and camp administration prohibition of alcohol production and consumption inside the camp, punishable with fines. These threats to the validity of the self-reported data and other study limitations should be borne in mind.</p><p>Recognition of the importance of addressing alcohol use among forcibly displaced persons appears to be increasing. UNHCR and WHO have produced guidelines and accompanying research on the use rapid assessment of alcohol and other substance use in such settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C47">UNHCR and WHO, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C11">Ezard <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). There is also some guidance on addressing hazardous alcohol in the leading guidelines on mental and psychosocial health in humanitarian crises settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C15">IASC, 2007</xref>). However, both programmes and research on hazardous alcohol among forcibly displaced populations are still at a rather nascent stage despite the fact that the majority live in protracted settings where longer-term developmental activities could take place to address chronic conditions associated with hazardous alcohol use. There remains limited understanding of how and why patterns of alcohol use may change as a result of forced displacement. There is also no high quality data on the effectiveness of alcohol-related interventions for forcibly displaced persons, reflecting broader gaps in the evidence on the effectiveness of mental and psychosocial health interventions among conflict-affected populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C44">Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AGT009C45">Tol and van Ommeren, 2012</xref>). Substantially greater research is required to alcohol use among forcibly displaced persons to better understand its patterns and drivers in order to help address the issues more effectively.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Authors&#x02019; Contributions</title><p>N.P.L.: developed needs assessment design, was responsible for implementation of the needs assessment, contributed to analyses, contributed to drafting and revising of manuscript. M.J.: initiated needs assessment, developed study design, contributed to drafting manuscript, contributed to analyses, contributed to drafting and revising of manuscript. A.M.: conducted the secondary data analyses and contributed to the drafting and revising of the manuscript. B.R.: contributed to discussions about data analyses and drafting and revising of the manuscript. J.M.: brought together the study team, designed secondary data analyses and led integration of draft text and revisions of the paper.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Funding</title><p>This study has been made possible with the financial support from <funding-source>United Nations High Commission for Refugee</funding-source> (UNHCR), Nepal. J.M. is supported by <funding-source>a Wellcome Trust Research Career Development award in Basic Biomedical Science</funding-source> (<award-id>WT086516MA</award-id>).</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Ms Eirin H. Broholm from UNHCR field office Damak for her support.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="AGT009C1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adelekan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Rapid Assessment of Substance use and HIV Vulnerability in Kakuma Refugee Camp and Surrounding Community, Kakuma, Kenya</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adewuya</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) as a screening tool for alcohol-related problems among Nigerian university students</article-title><source>Alcohol Alcohol</source><year>2005</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16115823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins-Biddle</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>AUDIT&#x02014;Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test: Guidelines for Use in Primary Care</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breslau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder and the incidence of nicotine, alcohol, and other drug disorders in persons who have experienced trauma</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>2003</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12622662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilcoat</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder and drug disorders: testing causal pathways</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>1998</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9783562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Avanzo</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress and self-medication in Cambodian refugee women</article-title><source>Addict Nurs Netw</source><year>1992</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C7"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Trauma, War, and Violence: Public Mental Health in Socio-cultural Context</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Komproe</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Ommeren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common mental disorders in postconflict settings</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2003</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>2128</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drobes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Concurrent Alcohol and Tobacco Dependence: Mechanisms and Treatment</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>NIAAA</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use among populations displaced by conflict: a literature review</article-title><source>Disasters</source><year>2012</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22066703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppenheimer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Six rapid assessments of alcohol and other substance use in populations displaced by conflict</article-title><source>Confl Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21310092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiptharakun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risky alcohol use among reproductive-age men, not women, in Mae La refugee camp, Thailand, 2009</article-title><source>Confl Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22963719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bebbington</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nicotine, alcohol and drug dependence and psychiatric comorbidity. Results of a national household survey</article-title><source>Br J Psychiatry</source><year>2001</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11689401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neighborhood income and income distribution and the use of cigarettes, alcohol, and marijuana</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>S195</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C15"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IASC</collab><source>Guidelines on Mental Health and Psychosocial Support in Emergency Settings</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Inter-Agency Standing Committee</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C16"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IDMC</collab><source>Internal Displacement Global Overview 2011</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Internal Displacement Monitoring Centre</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C17"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingleby</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Forced Migration and Mental Health</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C18"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IOM Damak</collab><source>Cultural Profile: The Bhutanese Refugees in Nepal: A Tool for Settlement Workers and Sponsors</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Kathmandu</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IOM Damak</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>CNH</given-names></name><name><surname>McPhee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer risks and prevention practices among Vietnamese refugees</article-title><source>West J Med</source><year>1990</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2389574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Traumatic experiences and mental health of North Korean refugees in South Korea</article-title><source>Psychiatr Invest</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jhingan</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shyangwa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of alcohol dependence in a town in Nepal as assessed by the CAGE questionnaire</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2003</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12603233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumpf</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Probabilities of alcohol high-risk drinking, abuse or dependence estimated on grounds of tobacco smoking and nicotine dependence</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2003</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12780369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and drug use among displaced persons: An overview</article-title><source>Subs Use Misuse</source><year>1996</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1853</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crum</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lifetime co-occurrence of DSM-III-R alcohol abuse and dependence with other psychiatric disorders in the National Comorbidity Survey</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>1997</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9107147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kizza</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjelmeland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinyanda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and suicide in postconflict northern Uganda: a qualitative psychological autopsy study</article-title><source>Crisis</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22343055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozaric-Kovacic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljubin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grappe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity of posttraumatic stress disorder and alcohol dependence in displaced persons</article-title><source>Croat Med J</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10853047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Battle</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Antin</surname><given-names>TMJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use among two generations of Southeast Asians in the United States</article-title><source>J Ethn Subs Abuse</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loescher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the challenge</article-title><source>Forced Migr Rev</source><year>2009</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental health of Cambodian refugees 2 decades after resettlement in the United States</article-title><source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source><year>2005</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16077051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCambridge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short forms of the AUDIT in a Web-based study of young drinkers</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Rev</source><year>2009</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19320671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C31"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasco</surname><given-names>Ls</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ecological framework for addressing the mental health needs of refugee communities</article-title><source>The Mental Health of Refugees: Ecological Approaches to Healing and Adaptation</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predisplacement and postdisplacement factors associated with mental health of refugees and internally displaced persons: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2005</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16077055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puertas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>del Valle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of common mental disorders in urban slumbs with displaced persons in Columbia</article-title><source>Pan Am J Public Health</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajendram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewison</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Preedy</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worldwide alcohol-related research and the disease burden</article-title><source>Alcohol Alcohol</source><year>2006</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The alcohol use disorders identification test: an update of research findings</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17250609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jason</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A social stress model of substance abuse</article-title><source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source><year>1990</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2212175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix Ocaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol disorder amongst forcibly displaced persons in northern Uganda</article-title><source>Addict Behav</source><year>2011</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>870</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21481540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucholz</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitznagel</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use among older adults in the national epidemiologic survey on alcohol and related conditions: a latent class analysis</article-title><source>J Stud Alcohol Drugs</source><year>2009</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19895759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aasland</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Amundsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption and related problems among primary health care patients: WHO Collaborative Project on Early Detection of Persons with Harmful Alcohol Consumption: I</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>1993</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8220062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C40"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karmacharya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Study of Prevalence of Alcohol use and Suicide in Kathmandu Metropolitan City</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Kathmandu</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO South-East Asia Regional Office</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaunekar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prevalence and correlates of hazardous drinking in industrial workers: A study from Goa, India</article-title><source>Alcohol Alcohol</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Silove</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental disorders, disability and health service use amongst Vietnamese refugees and the host Australian population</article-title><source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source><year>2005</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15740466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Silove</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of torture and other potentially traumatic events with mental health outcomes among populations exposed to mass conflict and displacement: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2009</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19654388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol abuse in individuals exposed to trauma: a critical review</article-title><source>Psychol Bull</source><year>1996</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8711018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tol</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbui</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galappatti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental health and psychosocial support in humanitarian settings: linking practice and research</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2011</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22008428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tol</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ommeren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence-based mental health and psychosocial support in humanitarian settings: gaps and opportunities</article-title><source>Evid Based Ment Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22450116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C46"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>UNHCR</collab><source>UNHCR Global Trends 2011</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C47"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>UNHCR and WHO</collab><source>Rapid Assessment of Alcohol and Other Substance use in Conflict-affected and Displaced Populations</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees/World Health Organisation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Ommeren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>JTVM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Psychiatric disorders among tortured Bhutanese refugees in Nepal</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>2001</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11343527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="AGT009C49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drinking and displacement: a systematic review of the influence of forced displacement on harmful alcohol use</article-title><source>Subst Use Misuse</source><year>2010</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>2340</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20469970</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>