<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">mBio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">MBio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">mbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">mbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mBio</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>mBio</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2150-7511</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22872780</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3419515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mBio00156-12</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00156-12</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antisense Transcription Is Pervasive but Rarely Conserved in Enteric Bacteria</article-title><alt-title>Antisense RNAs in Enteric Bacteria</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>Rahul</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>Daniel B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ochman</surname><given-names>Howard</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Microbial Diversity Institute, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to Rahul Raghavan, <email>r.raghavan@yale.edu</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Editor</bold> Jizhong Zhou, University of Oklahoma</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e00156-12</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012 Raghavan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Raghavan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Noncoding RNAs, including antisense RNAs (asRNAs) that originate from the complementary strand of protein-coding genes, are involved in the regulation of gene expression in all domains of life. Recent application of deep-sequencing technologies has revealed that the transcription of asRNAs occurs genome-wide in bacteria. Although the role of the vast majority of asRNAs remains unknown, it is often assumed that their presence implies important regulatory functions, similar to those of other noncoding RNAs. Alternatively, many antisense transcripts may be produced by chance transcription events from promoter-like sequences that result from the degenerate nature of bacterial transcription factor binding sites. To investigate the biological relevance of antisense transcripts, we compared genome-wide patterns of asRNA expression in closely related enteric bacteria, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium, by performing strand-specific transcriptome sequencing. Although antisense transcripts are abundant in both species, less than 3% of asRNAs are expressed at high levels in both species, and only about 14% appear to be conserved among species. And unlike the promoters of protein-coding genes, asRNA promoters show no evidence of sequence conservation between, or even within, species. Our findings suggest that many or even most bacterial asRNAs are nonadaptive by-products of the cell&#x02019;s transcription machinery.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>IMPORTANCE</title><p>Application of high-throughput methods has revealed the expression throughout bacterial genomes of transcripts encoded on the strand complementary to protein-coding genes. Because transcription is costly, it is usually assumed that these transcripts, termed antisense RNAs (asRNAs), serve some function; however, the role of most asRNAs is unclear, raising questions about their relevance in cellular processes. Because natural selection conserves functional elements, comparisons between related species provide a method for assessing functionality genome-wide. Applying such an approach, we assayed all transcripts in two closely related bacteria, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium, and demonstrate that, although the levels of genome-wide antisense transcription are similarly high in both bacteria, only a small fraction of asRNAs are shared across species. Moreover, the promoters associated with asRNAs show no evidence of sequence conservation between, or even within, species. These findings indicate that despite the genome-wide transcription of asRNAs, many of these transcripts are likely nonfunctional.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>July/August 2012</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="h0.0"><title>Introduction</title><p>Antisense RNAs (asRNAs) are transcripts encoded on the strand complementary to protein-coding genes. Many of the first bacterial asRNAs were shown to influence horizontally acquired elements by regulating bacteriophage gene expression, controlling plasmid and transposon copy number, and serving as antitoxins that promote plasmid retention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). The recent application of deep-sequencing technologies has revealed that chromosomal antisense transcription is widespread in bacterial genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). For example, in diverse bacterial lineages, such as <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Synechocystis</italic>, and <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>, between 20% and 50% of protein-coding genes have been found to encode asRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p><p>Despite the pervasive transcription of antisense sequences, the role of most antisense transcripts is unknown. Of the thousands of proposed asRNAs in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>, the functions of only a few have been characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Similarly, in <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium, the function of only a single asRNA has been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Despite the paucity of functionally characterized asRNAs, it is often assumed that because it is costly to produce RNA, most asRNAs are likely to perform some function. Alternatively, a major fraction of asRNAs could represent nonadaptive transcriptional noise due to the low information content present in bacterial promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>).</p><p>The degree of conservation among homologous sequences provides an effective method for discriminating functional from nonfunctional sequences; but to date, no studies have investigated the genome-wide patterns of asRNA conservation in bacterial species or applied a comparative approach to evaluate the functional relevance of asRNAs. To this end, we sequenced in parallel the transcriptomes of <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium and identified highly expressed transcripts arising from the opposite strand of protein-coding genes in each genome. Although antisense transcription is abundant in both species, only a small fraction of asRNAs are conserved across species, and the promoter elements associated with these transcripts show no evidence of purifying selection. The lack of evolutionary conservation between these two closely related enteric bacteria, combined with comparisons of strains within species, supports the view that many or even most of the asRNAs detected by deep-sequencing techniques are nonfunctional transcripts originating from spurious promoter-like sequences that arise nonadaptively throughout the genome.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="h1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="h1.1"><title>Pervasive antisense transcription in <italic>E</italic>.&#x000a0;<italic>coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>.</title><p>We obtained approximately 30 million 35-nucleotide (nt) strand-specific sequencing reads each from exponential-phase <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium grown in LB medium, with approximately 90% of the reads mapping to the respective genomes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). The read coverages for the two genomes are nearly identical, with &#x02248;2% of the reads mapping to the antisense strands of protein-coding genes. After applying empirically derived cutoffs to recognize expressed sequences from both genomes (see Materials and Methods), we detected sense and antisense transcripts from &#x02248;75% and &#x02248;28% of protein-coding genes, including transcripts from 14 of 17 previously annotated asRNAs in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material).</p><table-wrap id="tab1" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;1 </label><caption><p>Sequencing reads mapped to <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> genomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Value for genome<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Salmonella<xref rid="ngtab1.1"><sup>a</sup></xref></italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total no. of reads</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,206,434</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,275,111</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total mapped reads (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein-coding genes (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Antisense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic regions (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No plasmid</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab1.1"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p>&#x000a0;Of 5,313 putative ORFs in the <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium 14028S genome, only 4,477 with orthologs in <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium LT2 and/or in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> MG1655 were considered.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="h1.2"><title>Detection of transcription start sites and quantification of expression levels.</title><p>The strand-specific coverage at each genomic position was visualized and manually inspected using the Artemis software tool (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). As observed in previous deep-sequencing studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), sequencing reads accumulated with a pronounced peak at the 5&#x02032; end of each gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). Although this bias precludes characterizing the read coverage across the whole transcript, it allows the relatively precise identification of transcription start sites (TSSs) based on the 5&#x02032; end of mapped reads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). For a sample of 50 highly expressed protein-coding genes, 80% of the TSSs identified with RNA-seq data were within 2&#x000a0;bp of experimentally determined positions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref> in the supplemental material).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;1 </label><caption><p>Location of an asRNA within the <italic>holE</italic> coding region of <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>. Transcripts identified by RNA-seq mapped onto the <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> genome: reads corresponding to <italic>holE</italic> mRNA transcripts are in red, and reads corresponding to the antisense transcript are in green. Locations of TSSs and the direction of transcription are shown. Numbering is according to the <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> MG1655 genome (NC_000913.2).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0041213080001"/></fig><p>To verify the relationship between mapping coverage and gene expression, we used a quantitative PCR (qPCR) assay with a set of 4 mRNAs and 18 asRNAs whose maximum read depths spanned several orders of magnitude. We found that maximum read depth was an accurate measure of expression level as estimated by qPCR for both mRNAs (<italic>r</italic> = 0.920; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and asRNAs (<italic>r</italic> = 0.814; <italic>P</italic> &#x0226a; 0.001; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material).</p></sec><sec id="h1.3"><title>Highly expressed asRNAs from <italic>E</italic>.&#x000a0;<italic>coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>.</title><p>To compare the most highly expressed asRNAs in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>, we identified antisense TSSs within annotated protein-coding genes with a maximum read depth of at least 200. We excluded antisense TSSs within prophage genes and those that were located at the extreme 5&#x02032; end of a protein-coding gene and likely represented the TSSs for a divergently transcribed gene on the opposite strand. Based on these criteria, we identified 90 asRNAs in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and 91 in <italic>Salmonella</italic>. These corresponded to a total of 173 distinct genes, 120 of which have orthologs in both species (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS3">Tables&#x000a0;S3</xref> and S4 in the supplemental material).</p></sec><sec id="h1.4"><title>asRNAs are enriched for &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> promoters.</title><p>Consistent with previous findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), the antisense TSSs that we identified by deep sequencing were frequently associated with canonical promoter elements on the antisense strand, further validating the use of RNA-seq to identify TSSs and indicating that most of the identified asRNAs are expressed under the control of the &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> transcription factor. In both <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>, &#x0003e;70% of the antisense TSSs had an identifiable &#x02212;10 promoter element (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). This represents a highly significant enrichment (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), since only &#x02248;15% of randomly chosen antisense positions have a &#x02212;10 sequence that met these criteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). In contrast, similar analyses for &#x003c3;<sup>28</sup>, &#x003c3;<sup>32</sup>, or &#x003c3;<sup>54</sup> promoters did not yield significant enrichments upstream of antisense TSSs in either species.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;2 </label><caption><p>Enrichment of promoter elements associated with antisense RNAs. Distributions show null expectations for the percentage of randomly selected antisense sites associated with a &#x02212;10 promoter element in the <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (black/right) and <italic>Salmonella</italic> (gray/left) genomes. For each genome, arrows indicate the percentage of identified antisense TSSs associated with &#x02212;10 promoter elements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0041213080002"/></fig></sec><sec id="h1.5"><title>Most asRNAs are not shared between species.</title><p>Among the 120 orthologous gene pairs with a highly expressed asRNA in either <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> or <italic>Salmonella</italic>, only 8 (6.7%) showed high antisense expression in both species, and only 3 (2.5%) shared an identical antisense TSS position. Applying relaxed criteria that included any asRNA with a maximum read depth of at least 20 and an antisense TSS within 10&#x000a0;bp, we found that only 17 (14.2%) of the 120 gene pairs shared antisense expression at homologous positions in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tab2" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;2 </label><caption><p>Genes with asRNAs conserved on their noncoding strands in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Product</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">asRNA expression<italic><sup><xref rid="ngtab2.1">a</xref></sup></italic><hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Distance between TSS positions (bp)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Salmonella</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>acrR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-binding transcriptional repressor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">495</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">819</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>asd</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspartate-semialdehyde dehydrogenase, NAD(P) binding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>erfK</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sc>l,d</sc>-Transpeptidase linking Lpp to murein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">680</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>gloB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxyacylglutathione hydrolase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ispB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octaprenyl diphosphate synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">637</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mdtL</italic> (<italic>yidY</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multidrug efflux system protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>metB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cystathionine gamma-synthase, PLP dependent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">502</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mltC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane-bound lytic murein transglycosylase C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">657</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>napA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate reductase, periplasmic, large subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">419</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nudF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADP-ribose pyrophosphatase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pflB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyruvate formate lyase I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>treR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-binding transcriptional repressor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ybhA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyridoxal phosphate (PLP) phosphatase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ycdX</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted zinc-binding hydrolase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>yhbE</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted inner membrane permease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>yjjX</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inosine/xanthosine triphosphatase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">419</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ytfP</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved protein, UPF0131 family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">432</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab2.1"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p>&#x000a0;Maximum depth of mapped reads near asRNA TSS.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>For asRNAs that were expressed in one species but not detected in the orthologous gene in the other species, the species lacking the asRNA was less likely to have an antisense &#x02212;10 promoter element. In such cases, only 26.9% of the homologous positions in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and 31.5% in <italic>Salmonella</italic> had an identifiable &#x02212;10 promoter element. Although these values are greatly reduced relative to the frequencies of &#x0003e;70% observed for expressed asRNAs, they still significantly exceed the expectation based on randomly chosen antisense positions (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). As expected, promoter elements were much less likely to be shared between <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> if antisense expression was detected in only one of the species (37%) than if it was detected in both (90%) (<italic>P</italic> = 0.002, Fisher&#x02019;s exact test).</p></sec><sec id="h1.6"><title>Lack of purifying selection on antisense promoters.</title><p>Patterns of DNA sequence divergence provide an effective tool for identifying sequences of functional importance. Such sequences typically experience purifying selection, meaning that most new mutations are deleterious and are therefore eliminated from the population. As a result, functional sequences show lower rates of sequence evolution than their nonfunctional counterparts. Promoters are necessary for the precise control of gene expression, and their sequences are typically under purifying selection and enriched in the regulatory regions of bacterial genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Accordingly, we found that the promoter regions for mRNAs exhibited reduced nucleotide divergence between <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> relative to third codon position sites within protein-coding sequences. In particular, mRNA promoters exhibited pronounced reductions in divergence around the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 elements, important functional regions that are involved in &#x003c3; factor binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;3 </label><caption><p>Comparisons of divergence/polymorphism in asRNA and mRNA promoter sequences. Plotted are averages from a 9-bp sliding window of the interspecific sequence divergence between either <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> (A) or <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>E.&#x000a0;fergusonii</italic> (B) or for the proportion of segregating sites within <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (C). Black arrows on <italic>y</italic>&#x000a0;axes indicate average divergence (or polymorphism) for the entire coding sequences of ORFs containing asRNAs. Note that levels of sequence divergence (or polymorphism) in the asRNA promoter regions are statistically indistinguishable from the corresponding levels in the surrounding ORF (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.5 for all three data sets; paired <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;tests). The 10&#x000a0;bp flanking the &#x02212;10 and &#x02212;35 regions have been highlighted. Each error bar represents &#x000b1;1 standard error of the proportion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0041213080003"/></fig><p>In contrast to the functional constraint acting on promoter regions of mRNAs, there was no evidence of purifying selection on antisense promoter regions in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>. This is consistent with the observed differences between these species in antisense expression patterns and in the presence/absence of antisense promoter elements. The levels of sequence divergence in antisense promoter regions were indistinguishable from background levels in the surrounding gene, and unlike the situation for mRNA promoters, there was no indication of specific reductions in the rate of sequence evolution around the &#x02212;10 and &#x02212;35 positions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3A</xref>).</p><p>Repeating this analysis with <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and its congener <italic>Escherichia&#x000a0;fergusonii</italic> yielded similar results, indicating that even on a more recent evolutionary time scale, there is no evidence of selection on antisense promoter regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3B</xref>). Furthermore, we found a similar pattern at the intraspecific level by analyzing 41 completely sequenced <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> genomes, revealing a reduced frequency of polymorphic sites in promoter regions (particularly around the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 positions) for mRNAs but not for asRNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3C</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="h2"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We detected widespread antisense transcription and strikingly similar numbers of asRNAs in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> but found that most individual asRNAs are not shared between these two closely related enteric bacteria. The lack of conservation in asRNAs between these species might be taken to indicate that asRNAs function largely in a species-specific manner; however, we found no evidence of conservation or functional constraint acting within the genus <italic>Escherichia</italic> or even among different strains of <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Therefore, we suggest the alternative interpretation that a large fraction of antisense expression in bacterial genomes is nonfunctional.</p><p>Promoter-like sequences are expected to arise spontaneously by point mutations over short evolutionary time scales in bacterial genomes because of the low information content in &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> transcription factor binding sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). The underrepresentation of transcription factor binding motifs in bacterial genomes indicates that selection acts to purge spurious promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). However, Hahn et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) found that the average intensity of selection against such elements is weak, falling well within the range of &#x0201c;nearly neutral&#x0201d; mutations, where the effects of genetic drift begin to overwhelm the strength of selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Consequently, many spurious promoter-like sequences are expected to persist within populations and even reach fixation based purely on nonadaptive mechanisms of mutation and drift.</p><p>In the context of these observations, the lack of conservation in highly expressed bacterial asRNAs between <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> and within <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> suggests that many of these transcripts are the products of transcriptional misfiring resulting from the degenerate nature of the binding site motifs for the housekeeping &#x003c3; factor. This conclusion parallels a recent examination of the <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> transcriptome, which also found many asRNAs to be products of spurious transcriptional events from evolutionarily less conserved promoter sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p><p>The recent analysis of transcription in <italic>B.&#x000a0;subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) found that asRNAs were highly variable across environmental conditions and originated preferentially with alternative promoters. In contrast to the situation in <italic>B.&#x000a0;subtilis</italic>, we found asRNA expression in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> to be predominantly controlled by the housekeeping &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> factor, consistent with expectations given our sampling at log-phase growing conditions. It is possible that our analysis captured only a fraction of potential antisense expression, which could account for the limited overlap observed between the sets of asRNAs reported in different studies of <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS5">Table&#x000a0;S5</xref> in the supplemental material). The sensitivity of spurious transcription events to minor environmental differences may also explain why antisense TSS positions are weakly but significantly enriched in promoter-like sequences, even in species for which we found no expression of the corresponding asRNA.</p><p>Even if most asRNAs do not have a clear role in cellular processes, there are undoubtedly some individual asRNAs that serve some biological function. Previous studies have described functional asRNAs in both <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), and a recent analysis of the transcriptomes of a number of Gram-positive bacteria suggests a role for asRNAs in genome-wide mRNA processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Our findings, however, make it clear that the identification of antisense expression does not, in and of itself, confirm an adaptive role. The future identification of functional asRNAs should ideally link expression data to a combination of genetic, biochemical, and evolutionary data to reject the null hypothesis that expression is a consequence of transcription from spurious promoters.</p><p>The existence of pervasive, antisense transcription may be of general consequence to the cell: antisense transcription itself may be metabolically costly or interfere with the expression of the cognate protein-coding gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>), and asRNA transcripts could potentially serve as raw material for the evolution of new regulatory elements. Noncoding RNAs and regulatory sequences have been found to be involved in short-term evolutionary diversification and adaptation to local environments in both bacteria and eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), suggesting that strain-specific evolution of noncoding transcripts has the potential to supply new functions. Pervasive antisense expression may also affect genome contents in that bacterial mutations are biased towards <named-content content-type="gene">A+T</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) and selection pressure acting to purge AT-rich promoter-like sequences would have a counterbalancing effect on the genomic base composition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="h3"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="h3.1"><title>Bacterial strains, RNA preparation, library construction, and sequencing.</title><p><italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> K-12 MG1655 (GenBank accession no. NC_000913.2) and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp. <italic>enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium strain 14028S (GenBank accession no. CP001363.1) were grown in LB medium to log phase (optical density at 600 nm [OD<sub>600</sub>] of ~0.5). Cells were harvested by centrifugation at 4&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, and total RNA was extracted from bacterial pellets using Tri reagent (ABI) and cleaned using Qiagen RNeasy columns. Genomic DNA was removed by DNase treatment, and 16S and 23S rRNAs were eliminated using the MICROBExpress kit (ABI). Directional (i.e., strand-specific) RNA-seq libraries were prepared to maintain strand information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) and were assayed on a Bioanalyzer 2100 system (Agilent) for quality. Each library was loaded onto a single lane of a flow cell and sequenced using the Illumina GA II platform (35 cycles) at the Yale Center for Genome Analysis. Raw sequencing reads have been deposited in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (accession no. SRA047329.1), and Artemis-ready files are available on request.</p></sec><sec id="h3.2"><title>Mapping of sequencing reads and quantitative PCR.</title><p>Sequencing reads were mapped using the software program MAQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>) onto the published <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (NC_000913.2) and <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium (CP001363.1) genomes, allowing up to two mismatches per read. The number of reads mapped to each nucleotide position on each strand was obtained by parsing the MAQ pileup file using a custom Perl script, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The expression levels of genes were estimated by identifying the maximum number of reads that mapped to the sense and antisense strands of annotated open reading frames (ORFs). Background expression levels were calculated for 53 genes (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS6">Table&#x000a0;S6</xref> in the supplemental material) that were not expressed in a previous microarray-based study in exponential-phase <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> in LB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Microarray data were downloaded from the Oklahoma University <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> Gene Expression Database (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://genexpdb.ou.edu/main/">http://genexpdb.ou.edu/main/</uri>). Read depths for these genes ranged from 0 to 19. Based on these, we used a cutoff of 20 reads to designate an asRNA as expressed.</p><p>For qPCR validation of expression levels, <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> was grown in LB medium, and RNA was extracted as described above. After DNase treatment, cDNA was prepared from 1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of RNA using an iScript kit (Bio-Rad). Four loci (<italic>cdd</italic>, <italic>ldcC</italic>, <italic>napF</italic>, and <italic>ompA</italic>) were selected for qPCR, which was performed using SYBR green on a LightCycler instrument (Roche). To assess the similarity between expression estimates from Illumina sequencing and qPCR, we calculated the Pearson correlation coefficient between log-transformed maximum read depth and the qPCR cycle threshold (<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic>), applying a one-tailed test of significance (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material).</p><p>For qPCR validation of asRNAs, three independent <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> samples were grown in LB and RNA was extracted, as described above. After DNase treatment, cDNA was prepared from 500&#x000a0;ng of RNA and asRNA-specific primers using a SuperScript II reverse transcriptase kit (Invitrogen). Reaction mixtures were incubated at 50&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min, followed by enzyme inactivation at 70&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min. qPCR was performed on a Mastercycler instrument (Eppendorf), and the intraclass correlation among the replicate <italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> values obtained for each sample was determined using the irr package in the software environment R v2.8.0 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">Fig.&#x000a0;S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="h3.3"><title>Identification of antisense TSSs.</title><p>After RNA-seq reads were mapped to the respective genome, the antisense strands of all protein coding genes were scanned using a custom Perl script to identify regions with a read depth of at least 200. These genes were then manually inspected in Artemis to determine the positions of upshifts in coverage to identify putative TSSs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). Antisense TSSs that were located at the 5&#x02032; ends of three protein-coding genes (<italic>ybaN</italic> and STM14_1994 in <italic>Salmonella</italic>, and <italic>yneJ</italic> in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>) were excluded from further analysis because they potentially represent the TSSs of the divergently transcribed adjacent genes.</p></sec><sec id="h3.4"><title>Identification of &#x02212;10 promoter elements.</title><p>DNA binding of the &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> transcription factor is mediated by a promoter region that consists of two short motifs positioned approximately 10 and 35&#x000a0;bp upstream of the TSS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). The &#x02212;10 element is particularly indispensable and has a core sequence with the 6-bp consensus <named-content content-type="gene">TATAAT</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). This motif is highly degenerate, however, since promoter elements often have imperfect matches to the consensus and can be located anywhere in a window ranging from approximately 4 to 18&#x000a0;bp upstream of the TSS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). Therefore, to identify potential &#x02212;10 elements associated with antisense TSSs, we searched this 15-bp window for any hexamers that matched at least 4 of the 6&#x000a0;bp in the consensus sequence including the two most highly conserved positions, A2 and T6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). This approach could potentially miss some legitimate &#x02212;10 elements because many documented promoters are too divergent to satisfy these criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>).</p><p>To produce a null expectation for the observed frequency of &#x02212;10 elements, we generated 1,000,000 sets of randomly sampled antisense positions in each genome and determined the fraction of sites in each set that contained a &#x02212;10 element satisfying the criteria described above.</p></sec><sec id="h3.5"><title>Analysis of nucleotide sequence divergence and polymorphism.</title><p>Patterns of nucleotide divergence and polymorphism were analyzed to infer whether promoter regions regulating asRNA expression are subject to functional constraint. To calculate levels of nucleotide sequence divergence, protein-coding gene sequences containing identified antisense TSSs were extracted from the genome sequence of either <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (NC_000913.2) or <italic>Salmonella</italic> (CP001363.1) and aligned with orthologous sequences from the other species. Codon-based nucleotide alignments were generated by aligning translated amino acid sequences using the software program MUSCLE v3.7 and then converting them back to nucleotide sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). Divergence values were calculated using third codon positions only, which are largely synonymous and thus less susceptible to selection acting on the sense-strand-encoded amino acid sequence. Alignment gaps were excluded from divergence estimates.</p><p>Average divergence levels between <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> were calculated based on the distance to the antisense TSS. To test the hypothesis that purifying selection acts to constrain sequence evolution in antisense promoter regions, the divergence data were partitioned into two categories: (i) an antisense promoter region consisting of the TSS along with 50 upstream and 10 downstream nucleotides on the antisense strand and (ii) the rest of the surrounding protein-coding gene. A paired <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;test was implemented in R v2.8.0 to compare levels of nucleotide divergence between these two partitions. In addition, divergence data within the antisense promoter region were visualized using a sliding-window analysis with a window size of 9&#x000a0;bp and a step size of 1&#x000a0;bp.</p><p>The above comparison between <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> was repeated using <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and its more closely related congener <italic>Escherichia fergusonii</italic> (NC_011740.1). In addition, a similar analysis was performed using the number of segregating sites in multiple alignments generated from complete genome sequences of 41 strains of <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS7">Table&#x000a0;S7</xref> in the supplemental material). Note that this set of genomes included some isolates that are taxonomically placed in the genus <italic>Shigella</italic> based on their pathogenic properties but are phylogenetically nested within <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). Only genes that were present in at least 10 of the strains were included in this polymorphism analysis.</p><p>To provide a basis of comparison for the patterns of nucleotide divergence and polymorphism observed in antisense promoter regions, we identified TSSs for a set of highly expressed protein-coding mRNAs (maximum read depth of at least 200) in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> (67 and 55 loci, respectively). For this set of control loci, we extracted gene sequences along with associated 5&#x02032; regions extending 200&#x000a0;bp upstream of the identified TSS from the same sets of genomes described above. Nucleotide alignments were performed in MUSCLE, and sequence divergence and polymorphism values were calculated as described above, except that there was no filtering based on codon position for upstream noncoding sequences. Genes with unalignable upstream regions were excluded from the analysis.</p><p>For both interspecific and intraspecific comparisons, putative orthologs were identified as pairs of genes that returned top hits in reciprocal searches between a pair of genomes with NCBI tBLASTn v2.2.24 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). All analyses were conducted with custom Perl scripts utilizing BioPerl modules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="h4"><title>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL</title><supplementary-material id="figS1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;S1</label><caption><p>Validation by qPCR of asRNA expression levels estimated by RNA-seq. Threshold cycle value for 18 asRNAs is strongly correlated with maximum read coverage. RNA-seq and qPCR values are provided. Download <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.00156-12/-/DCSupplemental/mbo004121308sf01.eps">Figure&#x000a0;S1, EPS file, 1.1 MB</ext-link>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308sf01.eps" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="postscript"><caption><p>Figure&#x000a0;S1, EPS file, 1.1 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="figS2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;S2</label><caption><p>Estimates of asRNA expression from multiple <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> samples are highly reproducible. Correlation between qPCR threshold cycle (<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic>) values measured for 18 asRNAs from three independent <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> samples is shown. Download <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.00156-12/-/DCSupplemental/mbo004121308sf02.eps">Figure&#x000a0;S2, EPS file, 0.7 MB</ext-link>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308sf02.eps" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="postscript"><caption><p>Figure&#x000a0;S2, EPS file, 0.7 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS1"><label>Table&#x000a0;S1</label><caption><p>Expression of previously annotated asRNAs in <italic>E. coli</italic>. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st1.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S1, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS2"><label>Table&#x000a0;S2</label><caption><p>Accuracy of TSSs mapped in <italic>E. coli</italic> by RNA-seq. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st2.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S2, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS3"><label>Table&#x000a0;S3</label><caption><p><italic>E. coli</italic> genes containing asRNAs on their noncoding strands. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st3.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S3, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS4"><label>Table&#x000a0;S4</label><caption><p><italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium genes containing asRNAs on their noncoding strands. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st4.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S4, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS5"><label>Table&#x000a0;S5</label><caption><p>Overlap of previously detected asRNAs in <italic>E. coli</italic>. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st5.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S5, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS6"><label>Table&#x000a0;S6</label><caption><p><italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> genes used to determine background expression level. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st6.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S6, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS7"><label>Table&#x000a0;S7</label><caption><p>Genomes examined for polymorphism analysis. </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo004121308st7.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S7, DOCX file, 0.1 MB.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation </bold>Raghavan R, Sloan DB, Ochman H. 2012. Antisense transcription is pervasive but rarely conserved in enteric bacteria. mBio 3(4):e00156-12. doi:10.1128/mBio.00156-12.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We thank Cindy Barlan for technical help and Kim Hammond for assistance with figures.</p><p>This work was supported in part by <funding-source id="GS1">NIH</funding-source> grant <award-id rid="GS1">GM74738</award-id> to H.O. D.B.S. was supported by an <funding-source id="GS2">NIH</funding-source> Ruth Kirschstein postdoctoral fellowship (<award-id rid="GS2">1F32GM099334-01</award-id>).</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomizawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Selzer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Som</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>Inhibition of ColE1 RNA primer formation by a plasmid-specified small RNA</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>1421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6165011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stougaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Molin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>RNAs involved in copy-number control and incompatibility of plasmid R1</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>6008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6012</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6171808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleckner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>Translational control of IS10 transposition</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>691</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6311438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Mechanism of postsegregational killing by the hok gene product of the parB system of plasmid R1 and its homology with the relF gene product of the <italic>E. coli</italic> relB operon</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>2023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3019679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krinke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wulff</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>OOP RNA, produced from multicopy plasmids, inhibits lambda cII gene expression through an RNase III-dependent mechanism</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1013</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2962901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selinger</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>RNA expression analysis using a 30 base pair resolution <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> genome array</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1268</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Bacterial antisense RNAs: how many are there, and what are they doing?</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Genet</source>. <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20707673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>cis-antisense RNA, another level of gene regulation in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev</source>. <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21646430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dornenburg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Devita</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Palumbo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Widespread antisense transcription in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>1</volume>(<issue-id>1</issue-id>):<fpage>e00024-10</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/mBio.00024-10">http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/mBio.00024-10</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The primary transcriptome of the major human pathogen <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>464</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>255</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitschke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>An experimentally anchored map of transcriptional start sites in the model cyanobacterium Synechocystis sp. PCC6803</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>2124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2129</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opdyke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>GadY, a small-RNA regulator of acid response genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol</source>. <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>6698</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6705</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>An antisense RNA controls synthesis of an SOS-induced toxin evolved from an antitoxin</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol</source>. <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>738</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>754</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17462020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fozo</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemm</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Small toxic proteins and the antisense RNAs that repress them</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev</source>. <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19052321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>An antisense RNA that governs the expression kinetics of a multifunctional virulence gene</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol</source>. <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1033</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20398218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendoza-Vargas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification of transcription start sites, promoters and transcription factor binding sites in E. coli</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e7526</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0007526">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0007526</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19838305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Artemis: sequence visualization and annotation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>944</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>945</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A strand-specific RNA-Seq analysis of the transcriptome of the typhoid bacillus <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1000569</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1000569">http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1000569</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19609351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Biases in Illumina transcriptome sequencing caused by random hexamer priming</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>e131</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp868">http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp868</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20395217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide detection of novel regulatory RNAs in <italic>E. coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1497</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21665928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification of transcription start sites yields a novel thermosensing RNA and new cyclic AMP receptor protein-regulated genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol</source>. <volume>193</volume>:<fpage>2871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2874</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keseler</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>EcoCyc: a comprehensive database of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> biology</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>D583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D590</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21097882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Francino</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Morett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Collado-Vides</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Selection for unequal densities of sigma70 promoter-like signals in different regions of large bacterial genomes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e185</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.0020185">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.0020185</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17096598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Froula</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Francino</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Selection against spurious promoter motifs correlates with translational efficiency across bacteria</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e745</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000745">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000745</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17710145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvinsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Evidence that purifying selection acts on promoter sequences</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>1121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1126</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Rapid evolution of cis-regulatory sequences via local point mutations</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1764</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1770</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The effects of selection against spurious transcription factor binding sites</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol</source>. <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>906</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12716998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>The nearly neutral theory of molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<source>The origins of genome architecture</source>. <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates Inc</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sunderland, MA</publisher-loc></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Condition-dependent transcriptome reveals high-level regulatory architecture in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>335</volume>:<fpage>1103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1106</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide antisense transcription drives mRNA processing in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>20172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20177</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22123973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shearwin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Callen</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional interference&#x02014;a crash course</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horler</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderpool</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Homologs of the small RNA SgrS are broadly distributed in enteric bacteria but have diverged in size and sequence</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>5465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5476</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19531735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Velicer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Adaptive evolution of an sRNA that controls <italic>Myxococcus</italic> development</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>328</volume>:<fpage>993</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20489016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>BZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maerkl</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Does positive selection drive transcription factor binding site turnover? A test with <italic>Drosophila</italic> cis-regulatory modules</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1002053</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002053">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002053</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Diversification at transcription factor binding sites within a species and the implications for environmental adaptation</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol</source>. <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3344</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21693437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hershberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Evidence that mutation is universally biased towards AT in bacteria</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1001115</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001115">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001115</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Evidence of selection upon genomic GC-content in bacteria</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1001107</fpage>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1001107">http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1001107</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Highly integrated single-base resolution maps of the epigenome in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>536</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18423832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Mapping short DNA sequencing reads and calling variants using mapping quality scores</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1858</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18714091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khankal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cirino</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional effects of CRP* expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Eng</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19703305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Multiple sigma subunits and the partitioning of bacterial transcription space</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol</source>. <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pribnow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1975</year>
<article-title>Nucleotide sequence of an RNA polymerase binding site at an early T7 promoter</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>784</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>788</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1093168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Collado-Vides</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Sigma70 promoters in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: specific transcription in dense regions of overlapping promoter-like signals</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol</source>. <volume>333</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14529615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Margalit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Compilation of <italic>E. coli</italic> mRNA promoter sequences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1516</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8479900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1797</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pupo</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Multiple independent origins of <italic>Shigella</italic> clones of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and convergent evolution of many of their characteristics</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>10567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10572</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>421</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The Bioperl toolkit: Perl modules for the life sciences</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1618</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>