<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3082884</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq1278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkq1278</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transition dynamics and selection of the distinct S-DNA and strand unpeeling modes of double helix overstretching</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Hongxia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Hu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xinghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>John F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Mechanobiology Institute, National University of Singapore, Singapore 117411, <sup>2</sup>Department of Physics, National University of Singapore, Singapore 117542, <sup>3</sup>BioSyM, Singapore-MIT Alliance for Research and Technology, National University of Singapore, Singapore 117543, <sup>4</sup>Department of Molecular Biosciences, <sup>5</sup>Department of Physics and Astronomy, Northwestern University, Evanston, IL 60208, USA and <sup>6</sup>Centre for Bioimaging Sciences, National University of Singapore, 14 Science Drive 4, Singapore 117543</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+65 6516 2620</phone>; Fax: <fax>+65 6777 6126</fax>; Email: <email>phyyj@nus.edu.sg</email></corresp><fn><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p></fn></author-notes><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>39</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3473</fpage><lpage>3481</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Recent studies have revealed two distinct pathways for the DNA overstretching transition near 65 pN: &#x02018;unpeeling&#x02019; of one strand from the other, and a transition from B-DNA to an elongated double-stranded &#x02018;S-DNA&#x02019; form. However, basic questions concerning the dynamics of these transitions, relative stability of the two competing overstretched states, and effects of nicks and free DNA ends on overstretching, remain open. In this study we report that: (i) stepwise extension changes caused by sequence-defined barriers occur during the strand-unpeeling transition, whereas rapid, sequence-independent extension fluctuations occur during the B to S transition; (ii) the secondary transition that often occurs following the overstretching transition is strand-unpeeling, during which the extension increases by 0.01&#x02013;0.02&#x02009;nm per base pair of S-DNA converted to single-stranded DNA at forces between 75 and 110 pN; (iii) even in the presence of nicks or free ends, S-DNA can be stable under physiological solution conditions; (iv) distribution of small GC-rich islands in a large DNA plays a key role in determining the transition pathways; and (v) in the absence of nicks or free ends, torsion-unconstrained DNA undergoes the overstretching transition via creation of S-DNA. Our study provides a new, high-resolution understanding of the competition between unpeeling and formation of S-DNA.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The DNA overstretching transition occurs at forces around 65 pN, after which the double helix becomes about 1.7 times the B-DNA contour length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). The transition is sharp (a few pN wide) and cooperative near room temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). A series of experiments have been used to support an interpretation that this transition is exclusively force-induced strand separation, resulting in single-stranded DNAs (ssDNA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5 B6 B7 B8">3&#x02013;8</xref>). In these experiments, the dependence of the transition force on factors that affect base pair stabilities was reported to be in agreement with the strand-separation hypothesis. In addition, ssDNA binding proteins and glyoxal were found able to directly interact with overstretched DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), suggesting that the overstretched state involves exposed base pairs. Notably, this &#x02018;force-induced DNA melting&#x02019; interpretation of overstretching was initially proposed to involve two, parallel ssDNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5">3&#x02013;5</xref>). However, subsequent theoretical analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) and experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) have suggested that force-driven strand separation occurs <italic>via</italic> &#x02018;unpeeling&#x02019; of one strand from the other starting from a DNA nick or end, leaving one ssDNA to support the pulling force.</p><p>A separate series of experiments suggested that instead of always leading to force-induced melting, overstretching can result in formation of a novel double-stranded (ds) form of DNA called &#x02018;S-DNA&#x02019;. These experiments showed that: (i) the DNA tether was not broken after the transition in experiments where force was applied to the two opposing strands, as would be expected if strand separation were to occur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>); (ii) a second transition at a higher force was often observed that did lead to final strand separation after the 65-pN overstretching transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13 B14">11&#x02013;14</xref>); (iii) S-DNA is only partially unwound, with a well-defined helix repeat near 35&#x02009;bp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>); and (iv) the force-extension curve of S-DNA was inconsistent with that of either one or two ssDNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Despite these inconsistencies between experiments observing S-DNA and an interpretation of those experiments in terms of force-induced melting, advocates of force-induced melting have asserted that the overstretching transition is always strand separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>).</p><p>The conflicts between the two views were largely resolved by a recent study that revealed the existence of two distinct overstretching transitions: a slow hysteretic &#x02018;unpeeling&#x02019; of one strand off the other, and a fast, non-hysteretic transition to an elongated ds form, i.e. formation of S-DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Either can be selected or can co-exist via small changes in salt concentration, temperature, and DNA sequence composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Overall, higher salt concentration, lower temperature, and higher GC base pair percentage can bias the transition toward forming S-DNA, in general agreement with prior theoretical predictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). This result suggests that special attention must be paid to temperature control when optical tweezers are used in such experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), since a temperature increase by only a few degrees Celsius can completely switch the transition from forming S-DNA to causing unpeeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Similarly, caution should be applied when ssDNA binding ligands or proteins are used, since they likely can bias the transition toward the strand-unpeeling transition.</p><p>Despite the elucidation of the existence of two distinct types of overstretching transition, many other important questions remain unanswered: (i) The strand-unpeeling/re-annealing process requires the unpeeling fork between the ssDNA and B-DNA regions to move forward/backward (see sketch in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>), while the B to S transition does not. This suggests a distinction between the unpeeling and B to S transition dynamics which has not been systematically investigated. (ii) A secondary transition often occurs following the overstretching transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Whether it is a strand-unpeeling transition directly from B-DNA or from S-DNA is unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). (iii) The properties of S-DNA have not been carefully studied. In particular, it has been questioned whether S-DNA is merely a transient intermediate state before the DNA is finally unpeeled. (iv) It remains unknown whether nicks or free ends are necessary for DNA overstretching at &#x0223c;65 pN.</p><p>Since extended double helices and strands displaced from a nick are both transition states in DNA recombination, replication and repair processes, understanding the tendency of different sequence and different conditions to control the relative stability of these overstretching modes is of basic biological importance. The above outstanding questions have become gaps persisting in our understanding of the overstretching transition and the resulting overstretched DNA structures. In this article, these questions are answered by overstretching various DNA constructs under different conditions using magnetic tweezers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>DNA constructs</title><p>The four DNA constructs used in our experiments are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A: (i) 48&#x02009;502&#x02009;bp &#x003bb;-DNA (New England Biolabs), (ii) a 576&#x02009;bp DNA of 53% GC content, (iii) a 586&#x02009;bp DNA of 60% GC content and (iv) an 876&#x02009;bp DNA that contains a central 571&#x02009;bp sequence identical to that in the 576&#x02009;bp DNA. Two GC-rich DNA &#x02018;handles&#x02019;, biotin labeled 153&#x02009;bp DNA (GC&#x02009;=&#x02009;61%) and digoxigenin labeled 152&#x02009;bp DNA (GC&#x02009;=&#x02009;65%), were ligated to each end of this 571&#x02009;bp DNA. For all the short DNA constructs, biotin and digoxygenin were labeled to the two ends of the same DNA strand. Therefore, the force is applied by 3&#x02032;&#x02013;5&#x02032; stretching. For the longer &#x003bb;-DNA, the force is applied to the two opposite strands (3&#x02032;&#x02013;3&#x02032;). More details of construct fabrication are in &#x02018;DNA constructs&#x02019; in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) DNA constructs. (<bold>B</bold>) Sketches of the magnetic tweezers used in the experiments. The vertical magnetic tweezers (top) were used to stretch short DNA, while the transverse magnetic tweezers (bottom) were used for stretching long &#x003bb;-DNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1278f1"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Magnetic tweezers measurements</title><p>A vertical magnetic tweezers setup was used to stretch the short DNA constructs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). The digoxygenin end of the DNA was fixed to an anti-digoxygenin (Roche) coated cover glass surface, and the biotin end of the DNA was fixed to a streptavidin coated 2.8-&#x000b5;m paramagnetic bead (Dynal M-280, Invitrogen). The bead position in the focal plane was determined by the self-correlation method at a resolution of &#x0223c;2&#x02009;nm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). The bead position perpendicular to the focal plane was determined at resolution &#x0223c;2&#x02009;nm by analyzing the diffraction pattern of the defocused bead image at different defocusing planes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). More details are in &#x02018;Vertical magnetic tweezers&#x02019; in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>.</p><p>Forces were applied to the opposite strands (3&#x02032;&#x02013;3&#x02032;) of the &#x003bb;-DNA by a transverse magnetic tweezers setup (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). One biotin end of the DNA was fixed to a streptavidin-coated edge of a #0# cover glass, and the other was attached to an 8.2-micron-diameter streptavidin-coated paramagnetic bead (Bangs Laboratories Inc.) to achieve high force. The DNA was inside a narrow flow channel so that the buffer could be conveniently replaced. A permanent magnet outside the channel applies controlled forces from 0.04 up to 180 pN to the paramagnetic bead in the focal plane, and the extension of DNA was determined to be the distance from the bead to the edge of the cover glass in the force direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). The persistence length of DNA was measured in the force range 1&#x02013;10 pN by fitting force-extension data to the expected response for a worm-like chain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). The DNA was determined to be a single DNA if the measured persistence length was 44&#x02013;53&#x02009;nm. Temperatures below room temperature were achieved using an ice-water container on the top of the flow channel and were measured using the TM-902C Prober Digital Thermometer (Lutron). More details of the setup can be found in our previous article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Kinetics simulation of unpeeling dynamics</title><p>The kinetics simulation was performed assuming strand-unpeeling from B-DNA using Gillespie&#x02019;s stochastic kinetics simulation algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). In our model, tensile force was applied to one strand of a dsDNA. Meanwhile, the DNA has two free ends, so two ways of unpeeling that start from two ends are considered according to fork dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). The conformational free energy of B-DNA was determined by the extensible worm-like-chain model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), and the conformational free energy of ssDNA was determined by the model in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). The B-DNA base pairing and stacking energy was determined by Santa Lucia&#x02019;s model that includes sequence, salt and temperature dependence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). The details of the simulation can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Information S1</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Two distinctive modes of overstretching: irreversible unpeeling versus reversible formation of S-DNA</title><p>We first investigated how short DNAs respond during the unpeeling transition and the B to S transition. Beginning with a moderate-salt buffer favoring unpeeling, 10&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 150&#x02009;mM NaCl and 24&#x000b0;C, we slowly increased the force through the overstretching transition for a 576&#x02009;bp DNA that contained 53% GC base pairs. We paused for a few seconds or more at each force level; we then decreased force through the same set of force levels. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A shows the whole time course of one such experiment. After the transition the tether became an ssDNA, indicated by the non-reversibility as force was reduced through the same set of forces. Given that 3&#x02032;- and 5&#x02032;-ends of the same strand are tethered, this experiment shows that in the moderate-salt buffer, the non-tethered strand unpeeled from the tethered strand at a force near to 65 pN.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Overstretching transition of short DNA in 10&#x02009;mM Tris buffer (pH 7.5, 24&#x000b0;C) at different salt concentrations. (<bold>A</bold>) DNA (576&#x02009;bp) (GC 53%) in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl; in these moderate-salt conditions, force-induced melting occurs leading to strong hysteresis. (<bold>B</bold>) The same 576&#x02009;bp DNA as (A) in 1 M NaCl; these conditions suppress melting, and a reversible overstretching transition is observed. (<bold>C</bold>) DNA (586&#x02009;bp) (GC 60%) in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl; the sequence composition suppresses force-induced melting at physiological salt concentration, and a reversible transition is observed. Each force is denoted by a unique color in each panel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1278f2"/></fig></p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B shows that overstretching of the same DNA in 1 M NaCl (other conditions were unchanged) became completely reversible. This transition could not be explained by strand unpeeling or formation of two, parallel ssDNAs, since then an ssDNA tether should be expected after the transition. The overstretched molecule was not a mixture of ssDNA and B-DNA either, as this would have resulted in hysteresis during the reverse transition. Further, it could not be a mixture of two, parallel ssDNAs and B-DNA, because the resulted extension would be much shorter than that observed in experiments. The reversible transition could also be obtained by increasing the GC percentage. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C, a 586&#x02009;bp DNA containing 60% GC base pairs in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl and 24&#x000b0;C displayed the same behavior as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B. These experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A&#x02013;C) unambiguously indicated two distinct overstretched DNA structures: ssDNA via the strand-unpeeling transition when DNA base pairs are less stable and S-DNA via the B to S transition when DNA base pairs are more stable. These results were in agreement with our recently reported findings obtained from stretching a 48 502&#x02009;bp &#x003bb;-DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Distinctive transition dynamics of unpeeling and S-DNA formation</title><p>Earlier experiments for long DNA have shown that the strand-unpeeling transition is slow and hysteretic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). The cause of the slow kinetics in the unpeeling transition was hypothesized to be the energy barriers present in the transition due to sequence heterogeneity. This hypothesis was examined in detail by recording extension at constant forces in the range where overstretching occurred (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). This revealed interesting stepwise dynamics under various constant forces during the transition plateau, similar to that seen in DNA/RNA unzipping experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Detailed dynamics of 576&#x02009;bp DNA during the overstretching transition in 10&#x02009;mM Tris buffer (pH 7.5, 24&#x000b0;C) at different salt concentrations. (<bold>A</bold>) Stepwise dynamics observed in an experiment in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl (see the full-time course in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>). (<bold>B</bold>) Similar stepwise dynamics observed for the same DNA sequence in a kinetic simulation of unpeeling of B-DNA in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl (see details in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>). (<bold>C</bold>) Rapid fluctuation dynamics observed for experiment in 1 M NaCl (see the full-time course in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figure S5</ext-link>). (<bold>D</bold>) Stepwise dynamics observed during kinetics simulation of unpeeling of the same DNA sequence in 1 M NaCl. The transition occurred at higher forces due to more stable base pairs in 1 M salt concentration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1278f3"/></fig></p><p>In order to understand the stepwise dynamics, we carried out kinetic simulations for strand-unpeeling starting from the free ends of the DNA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figures S1&#x02013;S3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Information S1</ext-link>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B shows that, for parameters corresponding to the experimental conditions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A, similar stepwise dynamics were observed in the simulation. The agreement between experiment and simulation suggested that the stepwise dynamics was resulted from overcoming sequence-dependent energy barriers in the unpeeling process from DNA ends. In contrast, the time courses recorded in 1&#x02009;M&#x02009;NaCl completely lacked such stepwise dynamics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C). However, the corresponding strand-unpeeling kinetic simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D) carried out with parameters corresponding to experimental conditions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C still predicted stepwise dynamics, but at higher forces due to more stable DNA base pairs at higher salt concentration. We emphasize that formation of S-DNA was not included in our simulation. The disagreement between <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D indicates that the transition in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C was not strand-unpeeling of B-DNA.</p></sec><sec><title>The secondary transition is unpeeling from S-DNA</title><p>A secondary transition often occurs following the 65 pN overstretching transition which results in unpeeling from nicks or free ends of DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Depending on the pulling rate and sequence, the transition plateau can be much larger than 65 pN (slower pulling biases toward smaller secondary transition force). Such a secondary transition has often been observed for DNA containing significant GC percentage, while AT-rich DNA goes through a single unpeeling-like transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Although it is clear that this secondary transition is a strand-unpeeling transition, it has been debated whether it is unpeeling from S-DNA or directly from small remaining B-DNA islands that prevent the two DNA strands from being dissociated. In other words, there has been a debate over whether the observation of the secondary transition can be used as evidence to support the existence of S-DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>).</p><p>In order to answer this question, we investigated the extension increase per base pair of S-DNA converted to unpeeled DNA at forces in the range of 75&#x02013;110 pN at 24&#x000b0;C. To do this, we increased the force from 61 to &#x0003e;75&#x02009;pN in &#x0003c;0.3&#x02009;s, during which the DNA was overstretched (as an example, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A shows part of a time course obtained from cycling between 61 and 110&#x02009;pN). Following this, the DNA was held at the higher force for a few seconds or more, during which the secondary transition occurred as indicated by the gradual elongation at the higher force. This secondary transition was an unpeeling transition, and the amount of base pairs unpeeled determined the number of melted base pairs to be re-annealed when the force was dropped back down to 61 pN. Therefore, cycling between the two forces allowed us to obtain the correlation between the extension at the higher force right before dropping the force, and the extension right after dropping the force which marked the re-annealing starting position. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B shows that a linear relationship exists between the two extensions for the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>The secondary transition and the mechanical reponse of S-DNA. (<bold>A</bold>) Cycling between 61 pN (orange) and 110 pN (red) for a &#x003bb;-DNA molecule in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl, 24&#x000b0;C. A lower force of 35pN (black) was used to facilitate the re-annealing. (<bold>B</bold>) A linear relationship exists between the extensions just before and just after reducing force from 110 to 61 pN. The red line shows the linear fitting of the data (circles) with a slope of 0.085. For the same DNA, cycling between 61 pN and various other forces larger than 75 pN yielded linear relations with different slopes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6</ext-link>). (<bold>C</bold>) The extension increase associated with unpeeling one base pair of the overstretched DNA was calculated from the fitting slopes (circles). The solid triangles show the extension difference between ssDNA and S-DNA plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D. The red line shows the theoretical extension difference between ssDNA and B-DNA. (<bold>D</bold>) Force-extension curve of &#x003bb;-DNA measured in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl at 17&#x000b0;C (solid triangle). The blue curve shows the fitting by the extensible WLC model with persistence length of 46&#x02009;nm, stretching modulus of 1230 pN, and contour length per base pair 0.332&#x02009;nm/bp. The red curve shows the fitting by the extensible WLC model with a persistence length of 11.6&#x02009;nm, stretching modulus of 3030 pN, and contour length per base pair of 0.58&#x02009;nm/bp. The black curve shows the fitting by the ssDNA force-extension curve using formula in ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). The purple curve shows the force-extension curve of two, non-interacting parallel ssDNAs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1278f4"/></fig></p><p>A linear relationship was also observed for cycling between 61 pN and other forces &#x0003e;75 pN (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6</ext-link>). From the fitting slopes, the extension increase by converting one base pair of the overstretched DNA at the higher force to an ssDNA nucleotide was determined to be 0.01&#x02013;0.02&#x02009;nm/bp in the force range of 75&#x02013;110 pN (empty circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C. Also see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Information S2</ext-link> for the method of conversion). This value was one order of magnitude smaller than the predictions assuming that it is unpeeling from a B-DNA (red curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C. Also see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Information S2</ext-link>), suggesting that this secondary transition must be unpeeling from S-DNA rather than from B-DNA.</p><p>The extension increase by converting one base pair of S-DNA to an ssDNA nucleotide could also be obtained by comparison of the force-extension curve of the S-DNA and the ssDNA. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D shows the force extension curve of a DNA recorded from 1 to 110 pN recorded at 17&#x000b0;C. In the force range of 75&#x02013;110 pN, the DNA was nearly pure S-DNA, indicated by the negligible re-annealing signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). The difference of the force-extension between the ssDNA and the measured S-DNA was plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C (orange triangles) (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Information S2</ext-link> for the ssDNA force-extension model), which was comparable to the values obtained by direct unpeeling from S-DNA (empty circles). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D, the extensible WLC model was used to fit the data measured before (blue) and after (red) the transition. In addition, the theoretical force-extension of ssDNA was plotted to compare with that of S-DNA) (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Information S2</ext-link> for the ssDNA force-extension model).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>S-DNA stability. (<bold>A</bold>) Force cycling between 52 pN (blue) and 83 pN (red) for a &#x003bb;-DNA in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl at 17&#x000b0;C. The DNA was held at 83 pN for up to 5&#x02009;min to study its stability. (<bold>B</bold>) Force cycling between 53 pN (Blue) and various forces from 75 to 110 pN (red) for another &#x003bb;-DNA in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl at 17&#x000b0;C. At each force &#x0003e;75 pN, the DNA was held for 20 s. The top panel in (<bold>B</bold>) shows the values of forces &#x0003e;75 pN.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1278f5"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Stability of S-DNA</title><p>Another point of debate concerns the question of whether S-DNA can be a stable state or just a short-lived transient intermediate structure before the DNA is finally unpeeled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). To address this question, we overstretched a &#x003bb;-DNA in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl, 10&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5 at 17&#x000b0;C and held it at a constant force of 83 pN. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A, we did not observe an apparent secondary unpeeling transition over a time scale up to five minutes (it was difficult to record for a longer time scale due to biotin-streptavidin linkage breakage at such high force). Accordingly, when force was dropped to &#x0003c;60 pN, the DNA extension immediately returned to the B-DNA extension without significant re-annealing. This result suggested that the S-DNA is a stable structure that can exist over at least a time scale of minutes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B shows that, in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl and 17&#x000b0;C, S-DNA was stable over a wide force range seen by cycling between 53 pN and various forces in the range of 75&#x02013;110 pN. At each force &#x0003e;75 pN, we held the DNA for 20 s to check whether there was the secondary transition, and then the force was dropped to 53 pN to check whether there was re-annealing transition. We found the unpeeling from S-DNA was negligible until force was increased to above 110 pN.</p></sec><sec><title>Stabilization of S-DNA in an unnicked molecule with GC-rich ends</title><p>It was reported that torsion-constrained DNA that did not have free ends and nicks could not undergo the overstretching transition at &#x0223c;65 pN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). This raised a question as to whether free ends or nicks in DNA are necessary for the 65-pN overstretching transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A, we showed that the 576&#x02009;bp DNA (53% GC) underwent the strand-unpeeling transition in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl and 24&#x000b0;C; while under the same condition, we showed that the 586&#x02009;bp GC-rich DNA (60%) converted to S-DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C). This made it possible to construct a new 876&#x02009;bp DNA which was essentially the 576&#x02009;bp DNA sandwiched between two short GC-rich DNA handles (&#x0003e;60% GC) at its ends. These two DNA handles were used to make sure that strand-unpeeling could not occur from the two ends of DNA in 10&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 150&#x02009;mM NaCl and 24&#x000b0;C. We then ask whether the 576&#x02009;bp DNA in the middle, which does not have free ends but torsion unconstrained, still can undergo the 65-pN transition.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> shows that the 876&#x02009;bp DNA did undergo the 65 pN transition, via the non-hysteretic reversible B to S transition. The extension increased &#x0223c;200&#x02009;nm after the transition, to about 1.7 times the B-form contour length of the entire molecule. Therefore, the 576&#x02009;bp DNA in the middle must be overstretched to explain this extension change. In addition, due to the end blocking by the two GC-rich handles, unpeeling of the 576 DNA was not possible. This experiment shows that torsion-unconstrained DNA without free ends or nicks still could undergo the overstretching transition at 65 pN but only via the B to S transition pathway. Equally importantly, this result showed that not only the overall percentage of GC base pairs of a DNA but also the distribution of the GC-rich islands in the DNA play critical roles in determining the transition pathway, which is in agreement with the previous theoretical prediction that the sequence design can be used to tune the transition pathway during overstretching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). Finally, we noted that the 876&#x02009;bp DNA and the 586&#x02009;bp GC-rich DNA could undergo the stand-unpeeling transition when the base pair stability was reduced by decreasing salt concentration to 10&#x02009;mM NaCl (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Figure S7</ext-link>).
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>The overstretching transition of 876&#x02009;bp DNA in 150&#x02009;mM NaCl at 24&#x000b0;C. Note that this DNA consists of 571&#x02009;bp taken from the 576&#x02009;bp DNA flanked by GC-rich DNA segments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Each force is denoted by a unique color in each panel. The GC-rich segments eliminate the possibility of unpeeling, and a reversible transition to S-DNA is observed in the whole molecule under physiological conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1278f6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>By stretching short DNAs of only a few hundred base pairs using vertical magnetic tweezers, a dramatic distinction in dynamics between the unpeeling transition and the B to S transition was revealed with a spatial resolution of a few nanometers and a temporal resolution of &#x0223c;10&#x02009;ms. In the unpeeling transition, a stepwise extension change was observed, consistent with sequence-defined barriers in the strand unpeeling process. At forces in the B to S transition, sequence-independent and rapid extension fluctuations were observed, suggesting that the transition does not require crossing of significant energy barriers and occurs locally, i.e. as a structural transformation of the double helix. Such sequence-independent and rapid extension fluctuations are in agreement with an earlier report that showed &#x0223c;65 pN overstretching transition both in lambda DNA and CG-rich DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>).</p><p>Importantly, we show that a nick-free DNA that undergoes the strand unpeeling transition can be switched to overstretching to form S-DNA under the same solution conditions when its two ends are blocked and the DNA remains torsionally unconstrained. Equally importantly, our results suggest that a pair of small GC-rich islands can impose a constraint on the mode of overstretching that occurs in a nick-free DNA of arbitrary sequence between them, resulting in preferential selection of the B to S transition over the strand-unpeeling transition under conditions where the GC-rich islands do not unpeel. We conclude that force-induced melting without torsional constraint requires a DNA nick or equivalently a free end, and that the sequence composition of the molecule at the nick or end must favor strand separation.</p><p>Our results reveal that the secondary transition seen at forces well &#x0003e;65 pN is an unpeeling transition starting from S-DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). This resolves another debate regarding the nature of the secondary transition as to whether it is unpeeling from remaining B-DNA islands or from S-DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). The secondary transition under constant forces in the range of 75&#x02013;110 pN allow us to directly determine the extension increase by unpeeling one S-DNA base pair into one ssDNA nucleotide to be 0.01&#x02013;0.02&#x02009;nm/bp. We also show that this value was in agreement with the comparison between the force-extension curve of pure S-DNA and that of ssDNA.</p><p>Our results also addressed an important question regarding whether S-DNA is merely a transient structure or a stable structure within a reasonably long experimental time scale. We showed that at 17&#x000b0;C, the &#x003bb;-DNA in S-form was stable in the force range of 75&#x02013;110 pN for a few minutes which was the longest time scale we could achieve in the experiments before the DNA anchors became unstable. These results suggest that even in the presence of nicks or free ends, S-DNA can still be a stable structure in physiological conditions.</p><p>Overall, we have addressed and answered several important questions related to the nature of the 65-pN DNA overstretching transition, the secondary transition, and the mechanical properties of the overstretched DNA. Under physiological condition, our results suggest that the S-DNA is a stable structure in a wide force range up to 110 pN. We have not addressed the structure of S-DNA, but insight into possible structures of S-DNA have been obtained by full-atom molecular simulations and coarse-grained models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). These calculations suggest that an overstretched dsDNA can exist with highly inclined base pairs and a narrower helical backbone, or as an under-wound flat ribbon structure. These results were in agreement with an experiment that showed that DNA overstretching required under-winding of the DNA double helix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1278/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p><funding-source>Ministry of Education of Singapore, NUS</funding-source> (grants <award-id>R144000192112</award-id> and <award-id>R144000251112</award-id>); Mechanobiology Institute at National University of Singapore; Singapore-MIT Alliance for Research and Technology at National University of Singapore; <funding-source>National Science Foundation, NU</funding-source> (grants <award-id>DMR-0520513</award-id>, <award-id>DMR-0715099</award-id> and <award-id>PHY-0852130</award-id>); <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source>-National Cancer Institute (grant <award-id>U54-CA143869-01</award-id>); Chicago Biomedical Consortium with support from The Searle Funds at The Chicago Community Trust. Funding for open access charge: Mechanobiology Institute at National University of Singapore.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Supplementary Data</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_39_8_3473__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
                   xlink:href="supp_gkq1278_Supplementary_Information-resubmission.doc"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Dr Simona Cocco (Ecole Normale Superieure and Princeton University) for helpful discussions. H.F., H.C., X.H.Z., Y.Y.Q. and J.Y. performed the experiments and simulations. J.F.M. and J.Y. conceived the research and wrote the article.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overstretching B-DNA: the elastic response of individual double-stranded and single-stranded DNA molecules</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cluzel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Viovy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatenay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA: an extensible molecule</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouzina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloomfield</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Force-induced melting of the DNA double helix 1. Thermodynamic analysis</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2001</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouzina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloomfield</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Force-induced melting of the DNA double helix. 2. Effect of solution conditions</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2001</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>894</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouzina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloomfield</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salt dependence of the elasticity and overstretching transition of single DNA molecules</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>3160</fpage><lpage>3169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12023240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouzina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloomfield</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of pH on the overstretching transition of double-stranded DNA: evidence of force-induced DNA melting</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2001</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>874</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Mameren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Farge</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooijman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Modesti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Falkenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuite</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unraveling the structure of DNA during overstretching by using multicolor, single-molecule fluorescence imaging</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>18231</fpage><lpage>18236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19841258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shokri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouzina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA overstretching in the presence of glyoxal: structural evidence of force-induced DNA melting</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cocco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatenay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overstretching and force-driven strand separation of double-helix DNA</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. E Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys.</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>011910</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15324091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouzina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peeling back the mystery of DNA overstretching</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>18047</fpage><lpage>18048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19846782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rief</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clausen-Schaumann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaub</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-dependent mechanics of single DNA molecules</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10201403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calderon</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying DNA melting transitions using single-molecule force spectroscopy</article-title><source>J. Phys. Condens. Matter</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>34114</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20046972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clausen-Schaumann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rief</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolksdorf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaub</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanical stability of single DNA molecules</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2000</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1997</fpage><lpage>2007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10733978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danilowicz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Limouse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Conover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Coljee</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleckner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of DNA overstretched from the 5&#x02032;5&#x02032; ends differs from the structure of DNA overstretched from the 3&#x02032;3&#x02032; ends</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>13196</fpage><lpage>13201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19666582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdieu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatenay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural transitions of a twisted and stretched DNA molecule</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>1999</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaurasiya</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paramanathan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biophysical characterization of DNA binding from single molecule force measurements</article-title><source>Phys. Life Rev.</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two distinct overstretched DNA states</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>5594</fpage><lpage>5600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pronk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissler</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>There and (slowly) back again: entropy-driven hysteresis in a model of DNA overstretching</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>2452</fpage><lpage>2469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-dependent unpeeling dynamics of stretched DNA double helix</article-title><source>J. Comput. Theor. Nanosci.</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>I</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature control methods in a laser tweezers system</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1308</fpage><lpage>1316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15923237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gittes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laser-induced heating in optical traps</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2003</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1308</fpage><lpage>1316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gosse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Croquette</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetic tweezers: micromanipulation and force measurement at the molecular level</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>3314</fpage><lpage>3329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12023254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Near-field-magnetic-tweezer manipulation of single DNA molecules</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. E Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys.</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>011905</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15324086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Siggia</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stretching DNA</article-title><source>Macromolecules</source><year>1995</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>8759</fpage><lpage>8770</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exact stochastic simulation of coupled chemical reactions</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem.</source><year>1977</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>21</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cocco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marko</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Monasson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Slow nucleic acid unzipping kinetics from sequence-defined barriers</article-title><source>Eur. Phys. J. E. Soft Matter</source><year>2003</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15011069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>SantaLucia</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>A unified view of polymer, dumbbell, and oligonucleotide DNA nearest-neighbor thermodynamics</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1460</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liphardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Onoa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reversible unfolding of single RNA molecules by mechanical force</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodside</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Behnke-Parks</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Larizadeh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanomechanical measurements of the sequence-dependent folding landscapes of single nucleic acid hairpins</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>6190</fpage><lpage>6195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16606839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pronk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissler</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stretching chimeric DNA: a test for the putative S-form</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2008</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>205101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19045879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modelling extreme stretching of DNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1996</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2260</fpage><lpage>2267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8710494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haijun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong-can</surname><given-names>O-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bending and Base-Stacking Interactions in Double-Stranded DNA</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>1999</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>4560</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>