<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diacare</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">dcare</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22410813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3329852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1839</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc11-1839</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Care/Education/Nutrition/Psychosocial Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Relationship Between Glycosylated Hemoglobin Assessment and Glucose Therapy Intensification in Patients With Diabetes Hospitalized for Acute Myocardial Infarction</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stolker</surname><given-names>Joshua M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spertus</surname><given-names>John A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>Darren K.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MHSc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>Marcus</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Fengming</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Philip G.</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Inzucchi</surname><given-names>Silvio E.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>Saif S.</given-names></name><degrees>PHD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maddox</surname><given-names>Thomas M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MSC</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Masoudi</surname><given-names>Frederick A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MSPH</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kosiborod</surname><given-names>Mikhail</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Saint Louis University, St. Louis, Missouri</aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Saint Luke&#x02019;s Mid America Heart and Vascular Institute, Kansas City, Missouri</aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas</aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden</aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup>Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup>VA Eastern Colorado Health Care System, Denver, Colorado</aff><aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup>University of Colorado Denver, Denver, Colorado</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Joshua M. Stolker, <email>jstolker@yahoo.com</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2012 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="991.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>To evaluate the relationship between A1C and glucose therapy intensification (GTI) in patients with diabetes mellitus (DM) hospitalized for acute myocardial infarction (AMI).</p></sec><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>A1C was measured as part of routine care (clinical A1C) or in the core laboratory (laboratory A1C, results unavailable to clinicians). GTI predictors were identified using hierarchical Poisson regression.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>Of 1,274 patients, 886 (70%) had clinical A1C and an additional 263 had laboratory A1C measured. Overall, A1C was &#x0003c;7% in 419 (37%), 7&#x02013;9% in 415 (36%), and &#x0003e;9% in 315 patients (27%). GTI occurred in 31% of patients and was more frequent in those with clinical A1C both before (34 vs. 24%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and after multivariable adjustment (relative risk 1.34 [95% CI 1.12&#x02013;1.62] vs. no clinical A1C).</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Long-term glucose control is poor in most AMI patients with DM, but only a minority of patients undergo GTI at discharge. Inpatient A1C assessment is strongly associated with intensification of glucose-lowering therapy.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Diabetes mellitus (DM) is present among 25&#x02013;35% of patients hospitalized for acute myocardial infarction (AMI) and confers a poor prognosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Although A1C assessment is recommended for patients with DM hospitalized for an acute illness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>), whether inpatient A1C assessment impacts DM management during AMI remains unclear. We studied patients with DM in a multicenter AMI registry to evaluate the frequency of A1C assessment and its relationship with glucose therapy intensification (GTI) at discharge.</p><sec id="s1"><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><sec id="s2"><title>Patient population</title><p>The Translational Research Investigating Underlying Disparities in Acute Myocardial Infarction Patients' Health Status (TRIUMPH) study is a prospective AMI registry at 24 U.S. hospitals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). In this analysis, patients with known DM (self-reported or documented in the chart) or those on glucose-lowering drugs on admission were included.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Data definitions</title><p>Patients were considered to have clinical A1C if measured during hospitalization or obtained in the preceding 3 months. Patients consenting to TRIUMPH laboratory assessments also had A1C measured separately (laboratory A1C); these results were not available to treating clinicians. Standard A1C cut points were used (good, suboptimal, and poor control for A1C &#x0003c;7, 7&#x02013;9, and &#x0003e;9%, respectively) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). GTI was defined as increase in the dose of an oral antihyperglycemic agent, addition of a new antihyperglycemic agent, or &#x02265;20% increase in daily insulin dose on discharge versus admission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Changing one oral agent to another was not considered GTI.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Statistical approach</title><p>Hierarchical Poisson regression models (controlling for clustering by hospital) were constructed to identify independent predictors of GTI. Candidate variables included demographics, factors associated with GTI in bivariate analysis, or those considered a priori as clinically important (BMI, admission glucose, mean fasting glucose, clinical A1C, intravenous insulin infusion, and admission DM medications). To evaluate whether physicians are more likely to prescribe GTI in patients with worse glycemic control when A1C is clinically available (versus when A1C levels are not known), we performed a secondary analysis in which GTI rates were compared between patients with clinical A1C versus laboratory A1C only within each glucose control subgroup (good, suboptimal, and poor).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s5"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s6"><title>A1C assessment</title><p>Between 2005 and 2008, TRIUMPH enrolled 1,274 AMI patients with DM on admission (6% type 1, 87% type 2, and 7% unknown type). Clinical A1C assessment was performed in 886 patients (70%), and an additional 263 individuals had laboratory A1C measured. Of these 1,149 patients with known A1C levels, glycemic control was good in 419 (37%), suboptimal in 415 (36%), and poor in 315 patients (27%).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Rates and predictors of GTI</title><p>Overall, 396 of 1,274 patients (31%) had GTI at hospital discharge (33% new oral medication, 37% new insulin, 5% new oral medication and insulin, 9% oral medication up-titration, and 15% insulin increase). GTI was more frequent in patients with versus without clinical A1C assessment (34 vs. 24%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). In patients with clinical A1C, GTI rates increased with progressively worse glucose control (16, 37, and 55% with A1C levels &#x0003c;7, 7&#x02013;9, and &#x0003e;9%, respectively; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Moreover, physicians were more likely to prescribe GTI in patients with suboptimal or poor glucose control when A1C was clinically available (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>GTI stratified by subgroup of glycemic control. A1C indicates glycosylated hemoglobin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="991fig1"/></fig><p>Independent predictors of GTI included clinical factors (higher BMI, lack of insurance, no insulin before AMI, and fewer DM medications before AMI) and several glucose-related factors: presence of clinical A1C (relative risk 1.34 [95% CI 1.12&#x02013;1.62]), higher A1C (1.86 [1.40&#x02013;2.45] for A1C 7&#x02013;9% and 2.45 [1.63&#x02013;3.67] for A1C &#x0003e;9%, vs. A1C &#x0003c;7%), and higher fasting glucose during hospitalization (1.19 [1.10&#x02013;1.29] per one SD increase [52 mg/dL]). After multivariable adjustment, presence of clinical A1C was independently associated with higher GTI rates in each glucose control subgroup, versus patients with laboratory A1C only (1.30 [1.06&#x02013;1.59] for A1C &#x0003c;7%, 2.14 [1.13&#x02013;4.04] for A1C 7&#x02013;9%, and 1.78 [1.06&#x02013;2.97] for A1C &#x0003e;9%; interaction <italic>P</italic> = 0.30).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s8"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Although guidelines recommend A1C assessment for all hospitalized patients with DM (if not recently measured) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>), we found that only 70% of AMI patients with DM had A1C levels measured clinically. When assessed, nearly two-thirds of patients with DM had suboptimal or poor long-term glycemic control, but only a minority underwent intensification of their glucose-lowering therapy by hospital discharge. Of note, clinical A1C assessment was strongly and independently associated with GTI during AMI hospitalization, especially in patients with suboptimal and poor glucose control.</p><sec id="s9"><title>Clinical implications</title><p>Although this analysis shows modest improvement in A1C assessment compared with earlier data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), nearly one in three patients with DM still do not have A1C checked during AMI hospitalization. The observed association between clinical A1C availability and higher rates of both GTI and nonpharmacologic measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) in patients with suboptimal and poor glucose control suggests that presence of clinical A1C may lead to important therapeutic interventions for DM management. In addition, many physicians relegate DM evaluation to the outpatient setting, but chronic DM management is not consistently addressed after hospital discharge post-AMI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Although randomized trials have not demonstrated reductions in cardiovascular events with intensive glucose control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), better glucose control does reduce microvascular complications of DM, and optimization of A1C levels continues to be recommended by professional societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). Incorporating routine A1C assessment as part of in-hospital care for AMI patients with DM represents an opportunity to emphasize individualized, patient-centered DM management during AMI hospitalization that may improve transition to the outpatient setting, and potentially reduce long-term DM-related complications.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Limitations</title><p>Only patients with established DM and AMI were included in this study, so its implications cannot be extrapolated to patients with prediabetic states or newly diagnosed DM, and generalizability of findings to other hospitalized patients is unknown. Information about GTI during the immediate postdischarge period was not available, and some patients may have received GTI during early outpatient follow-up. Furthermore, the impact of therapeutic intensification on clinical outcomes remains unclear, as our study was not designed to address this question.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Summary</title><p>Nearly two-thirds of hospitalized AMI patients with DM have suboptimal or poor long-term glycemic control, but only a minority receives intensification of glucose-lowering therapy at discharge. Inpatient A1C assessment is strongly associated with higher rates of GTI, particularly when glycemic control is suboptimal or poor. Future studies should evaluate whether clinical outcomes are affected by intensification of glucose-lowering therapy after AMI in patients with poor glucose control.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Funding for this analysis was provided by a grant from sanofi-aventis. J.M.S. has served on the speaker&#x02019;s bureau for AstraZeneca. J.A.S. received research grant support from sanofi-aventis, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eli Lilly, and Amgen. D.K.M. served as a consultant to Tethys Biosciences, Novo Nordisk, F. Hoffman LaRoche, Genentech, sanofi-aventis, Pfizer, Boehringer Ingelheim, and Daiichi Sankyo. M.L. received research grant support from AstraZeneca, Novo Nordisk Scandinavia, and Abbott Scandinavia; served on an advisory board for Novo Nordisk Scandinavia; and served as a consultant to Eli Lilly, Medtronic, Novartis, Novo Nordisk Scandinavia, Pfizer, and sanofi-aventis. S.E.I. received research grant support from Eli Lilly; served as a consultant to Takeda, Merck, and Boehringer Ingelheim; and received speaking honoraria from Novo Nordisk. F.A.M. received grant support from Amgen and has been a member of the advisory board for Takeda Pharmaceuticals. M.K. served as a consultant for sanofi-aventis, Boehringer Ingelheim, Gilead, Kowa Pharmaceuticals, Genentech, and Medtronic Diabetes and has research grant support from Medtronic Diabetes. No other potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p><p>sanofi-aventis had no role in the design of this study, statistical analysis, or approval of the manuscript.</p><p>J.M.S. and M.K. conceived and designed the study and wrote the manuscript. J.A.S. and D.K.M. provided critical recommendations regarding study design and methodology, critically reviewed the manuscript, and provided editorial recommendations. M.L., S.E.I., S.S.R., T.M.M., and F.A.M. critically reviewed the manuscript and provided editorial recommendations. F.T. and P.G.J. performed statistical analyses. J.M.S. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p>This study was presented previously in abstract form at the 45th European Association for the Study of Diabetes Annual Meeting, Vienna, Austria, 27 September&#x02013;1 October 2009; the American Heart Association (AHA) 2009 Scientific Sessions, Orlando, Florida, 14&#x02013;18 November 2009; and the AHA Quality of Care and Outcomes Research in Cardiovascular Disease and Stroke 2010 Scientific Sessions, Washington, DC, 19&#x02013;21 May 2010.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donahoe</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Diabetes and mortality following acute coronary syndromes</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>298</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17699010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moliterno</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Influence of diabetes mellitus on clinical outcome in the thrombolytic era of acute myocardial infarction.</article-title>
<source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9207639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannel</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The impact of diabetes on survival following myocardial infarction in men vs. women. The Framingham Study</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>260</volume>:<fpage>3456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2974889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norhammar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindb&#x000e4;ck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryd&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallentin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenestrand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><collab>Register of Information and Knowledge about Swedish Heart Intensive Care Admission (RIKS-HIA)</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Improved but still high short- and long-term mortality rates after myocardial infarction in patients with diabetes mellitus: a time-trend report from the Swedish Register of Information and knowledge about Swedish heart intensive care admission</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>1577</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Standards of medical care in diabetes&#x02014;2011</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>S11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21193625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Cardiovascular Outcomes Research Consortium</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Translational research investigating underlying disparities in acute myocardial infarction patients&#x02019; health status (TRIUMPH): design and rationale of a prospective multicenter registry</article-title>. <source>Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21772003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Standards of medical care in diabetes&#x02014;2010</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>S11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20042772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Conaway</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Importance of measuring glycosylated hemoglobin in patients with myocardial infarction and known diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1090</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20381658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziemer</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Little time for diabetes management in the primary care setting</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Educ</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14999900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Byington</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Action to Control Cardiovascular Risk in Diabetes Study Group</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of intensive glucose lowering in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>358</volume>:<fpage>2545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>MacMahon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/><collab>ADVANCE Collaborative Group</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Intensive blood glucose control and vascular outcomes in patients with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>358</volume>:<fpage>2560</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Czupryniak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Guidelines for the management of type 2 diabetes: is ADA and EASD consensus more clinically relevant than the IDF recommendations?</article-title>
<source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>S22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20115928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>