<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26844507</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4748924</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000002685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">02685</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>5300</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pregnancy Outcome After I-131 Therapy for Patients With Thyroid Cancer</article-title><subtitle>A Nationwide Population-Based Cohort Study</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>Kuan-Yin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>Ruoh-Fang</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Cheng-Li</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Mei-Fang</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Wen-Sheng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>Chia-Hung</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;hlich.</surname><given-names>Eleonore</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>From the Department of Nuclear Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei (K-YK, R-FY, M-FC); Management Office for Health Data, China Medical University Hospital (C-LL); College of Medicine, China Medical University, Taichung (C-LL); Department of Radiology, National Taiwan University College of Medicine, (R-FY, M-FC); Department of Nuclear Medicine, Changhua Christian Hospital, Changhua, and Taipei Veteran General Hospital, Taipei (W-SH); Graduate Institute of Clinical Medical Science and School of Medicine, College of Medicine, China Medical University (C-HK); and Department of Nuclear Medicine and PET Center, China Medical University Hospital, Taichung, Taiwan, Republic of China (C-HK).</aff><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Chia-Hung Kao, Graduate Institute of Clinical Medical Science, College of Medicine, China Medical University, No. 2, Yuh-Der Road, Taichung 40447, Taiwan, Republic of China (e-mail: <email>d10040@mail.cmuh.org.tw</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>95</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e2685</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e2685.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The aim of this study was to evaluate the influence of I-131 therapy on pregnancy outcome in patients that received therapeutic I-131 doses for thyroid cancer in Taiwan.</p><p>This nationwide population-based cohort study was based on data from 1998 to 2010 obtained from the Taiwanese National Health Insurance Research Database. We identified 11,708 women with thyroid cancer (&#x02265;15 and &#x02264;50 years of age) by International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification codes. Patients were divided into 2 cohorts: I-131 therapy cohort and non-I-131 therapy cohort. The mean follow-up period was 6.08 years for the I-131 cohort and 6.87 years for the non-I-131 cohort. The case cohort and the control cohort comprised 775 and 716 pregnant patients, respectively.</p><p>The overall incidence of pregnancy was significantly lower in the I-131 cohort (adjusted HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.77, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.70&#x02013;0.86) and it was also observed when the patients were stratified according to age (HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.73, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.64&#x02013;0.83 in 25&#x02013;34 years; HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.63, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.49&#x02013;0.82 in 35&#x02013;44 years). Patients in the I-131 cohort had a lower successful delivery rate, particularly among patients in 25 to 34 years (OR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.60, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.45&#x02013;0.80). No significant difference was observed for adverse pregnancy conditions between 2 cohorts.</p><p>I-131 therapy is associated with decreased pregnancy and successful delivery rates. The underlying mechanism likely involves physician recommendation, patient's psychological issue, and potential impact of I-131 treatment on reproductive health. Further investigation is needed.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The definitive therapy for differentiated thyroid carcinoma is surgical thyroidectomy, coupled with I-131 therapy for treating residual, unresectable, and metastatic tumors.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> I-131 has been used for the postsurgical treatment of differentiated thyroid carcinoma for over 50 years. Young females comprise the majority of patients with well-differentiated thyroid carcinoma,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> and most differentiated thyroid carcinoma survivors have a long life expectancy.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> The idea that radiation may affect the gonads resulting in genetic damage to the offspring has raised concerns. Because many women are diagnosed with differentiated thyroid cancer during the reproductive years, determining the effect of I-131 on ovarian function and future pregnancy is crucial.</p><p>This was a nationwide cohort study of women with thyroid cancer, using data derived from the database of the Taiwanese National Health Insurance (NHI) program to investigate the association between I-131 therapy and pregnancy outcome.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Data Sources</title><p>The NHI program was established in 1995 and covers approximately 99% of the residents of Taiwan. The National Health Insurance Research Database (NHIRD) includes complete ambulatory and inpatient care details and provides researchers with scrambled identification numbers associated with the relevant claim information containing the sex, date of birth, registry of medical services, and medication prescriptions of the patient. The details of the NHIRD have been described in previous studies.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>The insured population with a major disease such as cancer can apply for a catastrophic illness certificate. The Registry for Catastrophic Illness Patient Database (RCIPD) integrates multiple NHI databases to provide comprehensive utilization and enrollment information for all patients with severe diseases who were exempted from copayments.</p><p>Codes from the International Classification of Disease, 9th Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-9-CM) were used. Patient consent is not required for accessing the NHIRD; hence, this study was exempted by the Institutional Review Board of China Medical University in Central Taiwan (CMUH-104-REC2-115).</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Study Patients</title><p>Female patients certified with thyroid cancer catastrophic illness certification (ICD-9-CM code 193) as identified in the RCIPD covering a period of 13 years (1 January 1998 to 31 December 2010) were selected for this study. Patients were divided into 2 cohorts: an I-131 cohort (patients who received I-131 therapy) and a non-I-131 cohort (patients who did not receive any I-131 therapy). The date of I-131 treatment was assigned as the index date for patients in the I-131 cohort. The index date for patients in the non-I-131 cohort was randomly assigned according to the dates in the I-131 cohort. Patients were excluded if they were under 15 years of age or older than 50 years of age. The mean cumulative I-131 dose was 120.1&#x0200a;mCi indirectly calculated from NHI payment code. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the selection procedure of patients in the study cohorts.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart showing the selection procedure of the study patients.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e2685-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Definitions of End Point, Comorbidities, and Covariables</title><p>The primary outcome was the first pregnancy after I-131 treatment. The 2 cohorts were observed until pregnancy, death, withdrawal from the NHI system, or December 31, 2011.</p><p>Furthermore, we evaluated several comorbidities which were defined as the history before the index date. They could be related to outcomes, namely, abortion (ICD-9-CM 632, 634, and 637), ectopic pregnancy (ICD-9-CM 633), and infertility (ICD-9-CM 628). The term abortion meant both spontaneous and therapeutic or elective reasons.</p><p>Moreover, for pregnancy-related analyses, we considered several covariables, successful delivery (ICD-9-CM 650), low birth weight (ICD-9-CM 765, 765.01&#x02013;765.08, 765.11&#x02013;765.18), preterm delivery (ICD-9-CM 644 and 765), gestational hypertension (ICD-9-CM 642.0-642.3 and 642.7&#x02013;642.9), preeclampsia (ICD-9-CM 642.4&#x02013;642.7), gestational diabetes (ICD-9-CM 648.0 and 648.8), placenta abruption (ICD-9-CM 641.2), placenta previa (ICD-9-CM 641.0 and 641.1), and antepartum hemorrhage (ICD-9-CM 641.1, 641.3, 641.8, and 641.9). Here, successful delivery was defined as at least 1 live birth.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The distributions of categorical sociodemographic characteristics and comorbidities were compared between the I-131 and non-I-131 cohorts, and the differences were examined using the Chi-square test. The follow-up person-years were calculated for estimating the incidence rate by using each variable. The I-131 to non-I-131 rate ratio for pregnancy with incidence rate ratio (IRR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) for each variable were calculated. Multivariable Cox proportional hazards regression analyses were used to assess the risk of pregnancy associated with I-131 use after mutually adjusting for age, occupation, comorbidities of abortion, ectopic pregnancy, and infertility. Furthermore, the univariable and multivariable logistic regression model was used to analyze the successful delivery rate between the 2 cohorts. Information about gestation or delivery conditions, such as low birth weight, preterm delivery, gestational hypertension, preeclampsia, gestational diabetes, placenta abruption, and placenta previa, were included in the model. Baseline characteristics variables such as age, occupation, comorbidities of abortion, ectopic pregnancy, and infertility were also included in the multivariable model for adjustment. The Kaplan&#x02013;Meier analysis was used for calculating cumulative incidence of pregnancy in the 2 cohorts and compared using the log-rank test. A <italic>P</italic> value of &#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were performed using the SAS statistical software (Version 9.3 for Windows; SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>During the study period, 11,708 patients with thyroid cancer were enrolled. The mean follow-up period was 6.08 years (SD&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3.82) for the I-131 cohort and 6.87 years (SD&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3.95) for the non-I-131 cohort. The demographic data and comorbidities of the I-131 and non-I-131 cohorts are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The majority of the study participants were in the age range of 15 to 39 years. Patients in the I-131 cohort were more likely to have had a prior abortion (8.87% vs 6.86%, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.001) than those in the non-I-131 cohort.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Demographic Characteristics and Baseline Comorbidity Between I-131 and non-I-131 Cohorts</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e2685-g002"/></table-wrap><p>Of the 11,708 study participants, 1491 patients became pregnant after being diagnosed with thyroid cancer. Among these 1491 patients, 775 patients belonged to the I-131 cohort (incidence rate [IR]&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;18.7 per 1000 person-year), and 716 belonged to the non-I-131 cohort (IR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;21.4 per 1000 person-year) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Median time to 1st pregnancy for patients in the I-131 cohort was 3.24 years (SD&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.63) and 2.94 years (SD&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.86) for the non-I-131 cohort. The Kaplan&#x02013;Meier analysis showed that patients in the I-131 cohort had significantly lower pregnant cumulative incidence than the non-I-131 cohort (Log-rank test, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.001) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The incidence of pregnancy was significantly lower in the I-131 cohort than in the non-I-131 cohort (incidence rate ratio [IRR]&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.86, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.79&#x02013;0.97). The adjusted hazard ratio (HR) for pregnancy was 0.77 (95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.70&#x02013;0.86) in the I-131 cohort compared with the non-I-131 cohort. As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, differences in the HR of pregnancy were observed when the patients were stratified according to age. Among in the age range of 25 to 39 years, patients who received I-131 therapy had a significantly lower incidence of pregnancy than those who did not receive I-131 therapy (HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.76, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.64&#x02013;0.90 for patients in the age range of 25&#x02013;29 years; HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.69, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.56&#x02013;0.84 for patients in the age range of 35&#x02013;34 years; HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.63, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.46&#x02013;0.85 for patients in the age range of 35&#x02013;39 years). As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, patients in the I-131 cohort were less likely to have pregnancies without comorbidities such as abortion (HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.79, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.71&#x02013;0.88), ectopic pregnancy (HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.78, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.70&#x02013;0.86), and infertility (HR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.78, 95% CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.70&#x02013;0.86) than those in the non-I-131 cohort.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>IR and HR for Pregnancy Between I-131 and Non-I-131 Cohorts Stratified by Age, Occupation, and Prior Comorbidity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e2685-g003"/></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Cumulative incidence of pregnancy for patients in the I-131 cohort and in the non-I-131 cohort.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e2685-g004"/></fig><p>As shown in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>, we applied logistic regression model analyses to estimate the risk factors of successful delivery and adverse pregnancy outcomes. The results indicated that patients who received I-131 therapy had lower successful delivery rates than those who did not receive I-131 therapy, particularly in the age range of 25 to 34 years (OR&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.60, 95%, CI&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.45&#x02013;0.80 for patients in the age range of 25&#x02013;34 years) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). When the population was analyzed for gestational disorders, no remarkable differences were observed between patients in both cohorts (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Successful Delivery for I-131 and Non-I-131 Cohorts Stratified by Age</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e2685-g005"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Delivery and Gestational Outcomes for I-131 and Non-I-131 Cohorts</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e2685-g006"/></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>I-131 and Gonadal Function</title><p>For women with differentiated thyroid cancer, the effects of I-131 therapy on gonadal function are an important consideration since most patients are of reproductive age. Female gonads may be affected during I-131 therapy from circulating radioiodine in the blood. A systemic review of 16 papers, containing data from 3023 women or adolescents with differentiated thyroid carcinoma, examining the gonadal and reproductive effects of I-131 therapy was analyzed.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Transient absence of menstrual periods occurred in 8% to 27% of women within the 1st year after radioactive therapy, particularly in older women. In addition, women who received I-131 therapy experienced menopause at a slightly younger age than those who did not receive I-131 therapy.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p><p>Ceccarelli et al<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> reported that I-131 therapy may contribute to follicular atresia and may induce early menopause. However, a controlled study of 202 patients did not reveal the aforementioned relationship between I-131 therapy and early menopause.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p><p>Sioka et al<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> studied 45 women of child-bearing age with thyroid cancer compared to 83 age-matched control females and reported a significant increase in the number of patients with menstrual cycle and/or menses irregularities after I-131 therapy. Vini et al<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> reported that transient amenorrhea or menstrual irregularities lasting for up to 10 months were experienced by 83 patients (17%), and no cases of permanent ovarian failure were recorded.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Another study indicated similar results in which 20% of the patients with thyroid cancer who received I-131 therapy experienced amenorrhea during the 1st year, and the elevated FSH levels of 28% of the patients returned to the normal levels by the end of the 1st year.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Conversely, Esfahani et al<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> observed that no significant correlation existed between gonadal&#x02013;hypophyseal hormones and I-131 therapy. Sexual dysfunction, infertility, and abortion were not reported during a 12-month follow-up period. Several studies have indicated that I-131 therapy resulted in transient menstrual cycle abnormalities lasting up to a year and a slightly early menopause, but no permanent ovarian failure.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> In our study, the overall incidence of pregnancy was significantly lower in the I-131 cohort than in the non-I-131 cohort. When patients were stratified according to age, patients in the age range of 25 to 39 years who received I-131 therapy had lower success rates for getting pregnancy. A bias possibly existed because after receiving I-131 therapy, patients were more likely to use contraception. International clinical practice guidelines for the management of differentiated thyroid cancer recommend that women who receive I-131 therapy wait at least 6 to 12 months before trying to conceive.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Thus, this recommendation may lower the pregnancy rates in the I-131 cohort.</p></sec><sec><title>I-131 and Pregnancy Outcomes</title><p>Most of previous studies in female patients showed no significant effects of I-131 therapy on fertility rate and offspring outcome. Garsi et al<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> obtained data on 2673 pregnancies in women who were treated for thyroid carcinoma, and the data revealed that the incidence of spontaneous abortion was 10% before any treatment, 20% after surgery only, and 19% after I-131 therapy. Spontaneous abortions were not significantly more frequent in women who received I-131 therapy during the year before conception, even in women who had received more than 370&#x0200a;MBq of I-131 during that year. The incidences of stillbirths, preterm births, low birth weight, congenital malformations, and death during the 1st year of life were not significantly different before or after I-131 therapy.<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Similarly, several studies concluded that there was no evidence of adverse effects of I-131 therapy on the rate of successful delivery, live birth demographics, and the risk of congenital anomalies.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> In a recent study, Wu et al<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> analyzed 18,850 women treated for well-differentiated thyroid cancer and demonstrated that a significant 29% reduction in birthrate among women age 20 to 39 who received I-131 therapy. The results of this study revealed that patients who received I-131 therapy, particularly patients in the age range of 25 to 34 year, had lower successful delivery rates than those who did not receive I-131 therapy. However, similar to previous studies, no remarkable differences regarding preterm birth, low birth weight, and some gestational disorders, such as gestational hypertension, preeclampsia, gestational diabetes, placenta abruption, and placenta previa, were observed between the 2 cohorts.</p><p>We observed that the incidence rate of pregnancy and successful delivery rate decreased in thyroid cancer patients with I-131 treatment. These findings might be attributable to not only potential effect of I-131 exposure on subsequent fertility but also an inability to tolerate a delay in childbearing either due to physician recommendation or impact of I-131 therapy on patient's reproductive choice. Considering the psychological issue, patients might be afraid of being pregnant because worry about adverse impact brought by I-131 therapy. The major strength of our study is that the large sample size in this nationwide study minimized the problem of losing cohort members at follow-up, even if patients were treated at different hospitals because of the coverage of the NHIRD including more than 98% of the population in Taiwan and its reimbursement system.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Limitations</title><p>Our study had some potential limitations. The NHIRD did not contain detailed information such as pathological type, disease severity, laboratory data (such as thyroid hormone levels), and maternal comorbidity, as well as it is very difficult to accurately calculate the complete ablation rate after thyroidectomy and I-131 treatment based on the NHIRD.</p></sec><sec><title>Tumor Type and Disease Extent</title><p>Lack of disease stage is a major limitation in this study. Although we reasonably assumed that most of our study patients had AJCC stage I and stage II differentiated thyroid cancer because the majority of our patients were &#x0003c;45 years old, there was still small percentage of patients over 45 years old. Patients who received I-131 therapy might have advanced tumor stage or higher recurrence risk which might affect the incidence of pregnancy. However, whether the patient received I-131 therapy or not might not precisely reflect the disease severity. Because controversy still exists regarding the role of I-131 therapy of American Thyroid Association (ATA) low to intermediate risk differentiated thyroid cancer patients according to the current ATA guidelines.<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> In our country, the use of postoperative I-131 therapy for patients with ATA low to intermediate risk is usually based on physician's preference and patient's compliance.</p></sec><sec><title>Maternal Comorbidity</title><p>It should be noted that the term abortion in our study included both spontaneous and therapeutic abortion, and subsequent therapy as well as comorbidity after I-131 treatment was not documented because such information was not easily available in our database. In our study, we found that previous abortion rate was more frequent in the I-131 treatment group. The possible reason was that some pregnant women terminated the pregnancy when confronted with the need to undergo I-131 therapy. But, &#x0201c;previous abortion&#x0201d; did not influence our result according to stratified analysis.</p><p>Diseases diagnosed using the ICD-9-CM codes in the NHIRD. Although the ICD-9-CM codes are among the most popular coding systems used for disease diagnosis in claims, the databases do not always precisely fit the clinical condition of interest. The evidence derived from a retrospective cohort study has a typically lower statistical quality than that of other studies because of the presence of inherent bias.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>In conclusion, our findings indicate that I-131 treatment is associated with decreased pregnancy and successful delivery rates. The underlying mechanism likely involves physician recommendation, patient's psychological issue, and potential impact of I-131 treatment on reproductive health. Further investigation is needed.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank the support from National Taiwan University Hospital, Taiwan Ministry of Health and Welfare Clinical Trial and Research Center of Excellence (MOHW105-TDU-B-212-133019), China Medical University Hospital, Academia Sinica Taiwan Biobank Stroke Biosignature Project (BM10501010037), NRPB Stroke Clinical Trial Consortium (MOST 104-2325-B-039-005), Tseng-Lien Lin Foundation, Taichung, Taiwan, Taiwan Brain Disease Foundation, Taipei, Taiwan, and Katsuzo and Kiyo Aoshima Memorial Funds, Japan; and CMU under the Aim for Top University Plan of the Ministry of Education, Taiwan; and Health, and welfare surcharge of tobacco products, China Medical University Hospital Cancer Research Center of Excellence (MOHW104-TDU-B-212-124-002, Taiwan). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. No additional external funding received for this study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>Abbreviations: CI = confidence interval, HR = hazard ratio, ICD-9-CM = International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification, NHIRD = National Health Insurance Research Database.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>K-YK, R-FY, W-SH, and C-HK contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Conception and design: K-YK, R-FY, C-HK; Administrative support: W-SH, C-HK, Collection and assembly of data, Data analysis and interpretation, Manuscript writing, Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p>This study is supported in part by National Taiwan University Hospital, Taiwan Ministry of Health and Welfare Clinical Trial and Research Center of Excellence (MOHW105-TDU-B-212-133019), China Medical University Hospital, Academia Sinica Taiwan Biobank Stroke Biosignature Project (BM10501010037), NRPB Stroke Clinical Trial Consortium (MOST 104-2325-B-039-005), Tseng-Lien Lin Foundation, Taichung, Taiwan, Taiwan Brain Disease Foundation, Taipei, Taiwan, and Katsuzo and Kiyo Aoshima Memorial Funds, Japan; and CMU under the Aim for Top University Plan of the Ministry of Education, Taiwan; and Health, and welfare surcharge of tobacco products, China Medical University Hospital Cancer Research Center of Excellence (MOHW104-TDU-B-212-124-002, Taiwan).</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. No additional external funding received for this study.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prognostic factors for thyroid carcinoma. A population-based study of 15,698 cases from the Surveillance, Epidemiology and End Results (SEER) program 1973&#x02013;1991</article-title>. <source><italic>Cancer</italic></source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9028369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Terris</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contemporary management of thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Otolaryngol</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15991091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlumberger</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Papillary and follicular thyroid carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>N Engl J Med</italic></source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>338</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9445411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Outcome of pregnancy after radioactive iodine treatment for well differentiated thyroid carcinomas</article-title>. <source><italic>J Endocrinol Invest</italic></source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9854681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balan</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Outcome of pregnancy following treatment of well-differentiated thyroid cancer with 131iodine</article-title>. <source><italic>Br J Obstet Gynaecol</italic></source>
<year>1992</year>; <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>1021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1022</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1477008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eustatia-Rutten</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Corssmit</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Biermasz</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Survival and death causes in differentiated thyroid carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16263822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The association between occupational characteristics and hysterectomies for treating uterine fibroids in Taiwan</article-title>. <source><italic>Women Health</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawka</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakra</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A systematic review examining the effects of therapeutic radioactive iodine on ovarian function and future pregnancy in female thyroid cancer survivors</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>490</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18284643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceccarelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bencivelli</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Morciano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>131I therapy for differentiated thyroid cancer leads to an earlier onset of menopause: results of a retrospective study</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>3512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11502772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza Rosario</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarenga Fagundes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Villas-Boas Fagundes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Radioiodne therapy and age at menopause in patients with thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Endocrinol</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manuel Garcia-Quiros Munoz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin Hernandez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres Cuadro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>[Age of menopause in patients with differentiated thyroid cancer treated with radioiodine]</article-title>. <source><italic>Endocrinol Nutr</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20304710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sioka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouraklis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zafirakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Menstrual cycle disorders after therapy with iodine-131</article-title>. <source><italic>Fertil Steril</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Saadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prognosis for fertility and ovarian function after treatment with radioiodine for thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Postgrad Med J</italic></source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza Rosario</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarenga Fagundes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Villas-Boas Fagundes</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ovarian function after radioiodine therapy in patients with thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>333</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15977100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esfahani</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Eftekhari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenooz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gonadal function in patients with differentiated thyroid cancer treated with (131)I</article-title>. <source><italic>Hell J Nucl Med</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16868643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sioka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fotopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of I-131 therapy on gonads and pregnancy outcome in patients with thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Fertil Steril</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1559</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<collab>American Thyroid Association Guidelines Taskforce on Thyroid N, Differentiated Thyroid C</collab>. <article-title>Revised American Thyroid Association management guidelines for patients with thyroid nodules and differentiated thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Thyroid</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19860577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pacini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlumberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dralle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>European consensus for the management of patients with differentiated thyroid carcinoma of the follicular epithelium</article-title>. <source><italic>Eur J Endocrinol</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>154</volume>:<fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16728537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garsi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlumberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Therapeutic administration of 131I for differentiated thyroid cancer: radiation dose to ovaries and outcome of pregnancies</article-title>. <source><italic>J Nucl Med</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>852</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18413399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>do Rosario</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Malformations in the offspring of women with thyroid cancer treated with radioiodine for the ablation of thyroid remnants</article-title>. <source><italic>Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>930</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>933</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17160219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balenovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlasic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonicki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pregnancy outcome after treatment with radioiodine for differentiated thyroid carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Coll Antropol</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>743</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17243543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>High-dose radioiodine treatment for differentiated thyroid carcinoma is not associated with change in female fertility or any genetic risk to the offspring</article-title>. <source><italic>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16095849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandao</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Radioiodine therapy and subsequent pregnancy</article-title>. <source><italic>Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fard-Esfahani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadifar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallahi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Radioiodine treatment complications to the mother and child in patients with differentiated thyroid carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Hell J Nucl Med</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19330181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pregnancy outcome after diagnosis of differentiated thyroid carcinoma: no deleterious effect after radioactive iodine treatment</article-title>. <source><italic>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1000</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15234032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Reproductive outcomes and nononcologic complications after radioactive iodine ablation for well-differentiated thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Thyroid</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25289542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Revised American Thyroid Association management guidelines for patients with thyroid nodules and differentiated thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Thyroid</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19860577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>