<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">New Microbes New Infect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">New Microbes New Infect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>New Microbes and New Infections</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2052-2975</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26862435</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4708074</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2052-2975(15)00094-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nmni.2015.10.013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>First Clinical Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Relapsing sepsis episodes of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> with <italic>CTX-M</italic> ESBL or derepressed <italic>ampC</italic> genes in a patient with chronic autoimmune pancreatitis complicated by IgG4 hypergammaglobulinaemia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tuuminen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><email>tamara.tuuminen@islab.fi</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;sterblad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;m&#x000e4;l&#x000e4;inen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sironen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Eastern Finland Laboratory Centre Joint Authority Enterprise (ISLAB), Mikkeli District Laboratory, Mikkeli, Finland</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Department of Bacteriology and Immunology, Haartman Institute, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>Bacterial Infections Unit, Department of Infectious Diseases, National Institute for Health and Welfare, Turku, Finland</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4)</label>Department of Medicine, Kuopio University Hospital, Finland</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5)</label>Imaging Center, Clinical Pathology, Kuopio University Hospital, Finland</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6)</label>Institute of Clinical Medicine, Pathology and Forensic Medicine, University of Eastern Finland, Kuopio, Finland</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7)</label>Biocenter Kuopio and Cancer Center of Easter Finland, University of Eastern Finland, Kuopio, Finland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label><bold>Corresponding author</bold>: T. Tuuminen, Eastern Finland Laboratory Centre Joint Authority Enterprise (ISLAB), Mikkeli District Laboratory, Porrassalmenkatu 35-37, Mikkeli FI-50100, Finland <email>tamara.tuuminen@islab.fi</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Bloodstream recurrent infections have been reported for a variety of opportunistic bacteria. These are often either catheter related or are caused by indwelling devices. A case of relapsing sepsis with two <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains carrying extended-spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamase and derepressed <italic>ampC</italic> genes is reported. The patient had seven episodes of bloodstream infections within 1 year and was diagnosed with chronic autoimmune pancreatitis and IgG4 hypergammaglobulinaemia. Abscesses were found in his spleen and pancreas cauda, which was finally resected. Relapses of bacteraemia with resistant enterobacteria should be considered during perioperative protection. Surgical removal of the infective focus could be curative.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Autoimmune pancreatitis</kwd><kwd>bacteraemia</kwd><kwd>ESBL</kwd><kwd>IgG4 hypergammaglobulinaemia</kwd><kwd>relapsing sepsis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Recurrent bloodstream infections are either reinfections or relapses caused by the same strain. Bloodstream recurrent infections have been reported for a great variety of opportunistic bacteria, with coagulase-negative staphylococci being the most common <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. The majority of the relapsing sepsis infections are either catheter related or are caused by indwelling devices that serve as an excellent solid phase for sticky biofilms, the source for transient bacterial translocation into the vessel lumen. Relapsing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> bacteraemias have also been described <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Molecular fingerprinting <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> as well as biochemical analysis and serotyping <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> have shown that the majority of the sepsis episodes might be caused by the same strain even when adequate antimicrobial therapy is provided. Taking into account the multistrain and multispecies complexity of biofilm, it remains unclear why sepsis episodes are often caused by exactly the same strain and what kind of &#x0201c;leads&#x0201d; this strain may have compared to other &#x0201c;inhabitants&#x0201d; of the biofilm ecosystem.</p><p>Here we report a case of recurrent <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> sepsis. Altogether, the patient experienced seven episodes of <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> bacteraemia in just over a year. All the episodes can be considered as relapses caused by the extended-spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamase (ESBL) strain or by the AmpC hyperproducer. Finally, the focus of these bloodborne infections was found in his spleen and pancreas cauda, which was resected. Of interest, the underlying disease, autoimmune pancreatitis of type 1 with IgG4 hyperglobulinaemia, had probably contributed to the formation of the cyst that harboured infection.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Case Report</title><p>A 47-year-old man came to Finland as a refugee from Southeast Asia. In the immigration health inspection, he was diagnosed with a <italic>Toxocara canis</italic> infection and treated with mebendazole. Soon after arrival, he complained of epigastric pain and fever; he was diagnosed with acute pancreatitis, which was treated conservatively. After this episode, the patient gave up alcohol completely. Pancreatitis episodes, often complicated with septicaemias, recurred several times during the following years. Radiologic findings confirmed chronic pancreatitis with calcifications. Papillotomy, dilatation and stent insertion into the strictured ductus Wirsung were performed. Written informed consent was obtained from the patient.</p><p>Three years after the first pancreatic episode, the patient was hospitalized again for fever and multiple liver abscesses. Abscesses were also found in the spleen and pancreas. Blood cultures revealed <italic>Lactococcus</italic> species. Drainage of abscesses was not feasible because of the small size of the multiple abscesses and the challenging anatomic site. An infection of the pancreatic duct stent was suspected, and the stent was removed. ESBL-producing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> septicaemia complicated the surgical intervention. The condition progressed despite long-term antimicrobial therapy.</p><p>The patient was negative for parasitic infection, HIV, and <italic>Echinococcus</italic> serology. Instead, <italic>Toxocara canis</italic> serology remained positive, compatible with his early infection. During the following months, the patient was hospitalized several times for recurrent pancreatitis and relapsing episodes of sepsis. The laboratory data on the blood culture isolates are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p><p>Abscess formation continued even though the patient received various antimicrobials (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>). Eventually cholecystectomy, splenectomy and a partial pancreatic resection were considered. In addition to resection of the pancreatic cauda, the enlarged spleen was removed, and cholecystectomy was performed. Histopathologic examination of the pancreas revealed extensive fibrosis, multiple cysts (1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;cm in diameter) and inflammatory cells such as neutrophils, macrophages, lymphocytes and plasma cells that were partly immunopositive for IgG4. Histology revealed no microorganisms. The hilum of the spleen revealed purulent inflammation, but the splenic parenchyma and gallbladder were structurally normal. Computed tomographic scan revealed numerous degenerative cystic lesions in the spleen that most probably had formed as a result of prolonged bacterial infection (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). A pseudocyst filled with a grey fluid was found between the pancreatic cauda and the spleen. ESBL <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> was isolated from the fluid. All other tissue cultures were negative in bacteriologic, mycobacteriologic, virologic and parasitologic examinations. These findings finally confirmed suspected end-stage chronic autoimmune pancreatitis associated with the IgG4 syndrome <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. During convalescence, the patient had a relapse of ESBL <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> sepsis but recovered completely.</p><p>The strains were tested for &#x003b2;-lactamase genes as previously described <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. All 3 ESBL isolates harboured a <italic>CTX-M</italic> gene. Three other <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> isolates (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>) had an AmpC phenotype and were negative for <italic>ampC</italic> genes (<italic>CIT, DHA, MOX, FOX, EBC, ACC</italic>), thus apparently overproducing the chromosomal AmpC. In order to investigate the clonality of the strains, we performed molecular typing. The culture isolates were analysed with pulsed-field gel electrophoresis using a protocol based on PulseNet for <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/pulsenet/pathogens/ecoli.html" id="intref0010">http://www.cdc.gov/pulsenet/pathogens/ecoli.html</ext-link>). Briefly, genomic DNA was digested with <italic>Xba</italic>I (New England Biolabs), and separated in a Chef DR III (Bio-Rad). Banding patterns were interpreted using the criteria of Tenover <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. The ESBL isolates were found to be the same strain (one- to two-band differences in the banding patterns). The AmpC overproducers were also similar (a one-band difference in one isolate); however, they were different from the ESBL clone (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>Soon after the surgical intervention, our patient experienced a new episode of ESBL sepsis&#x02014;a complication that might have been avoided if previous bacteriologic data had been taken into account so perioperative carbapenem prophylaxis could have been implemented.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The reported case emphasizes that the primary prevention of bloodstream relapses caused by Gram-negative bacteria is the surgical elimination of the focus of infection. Being encapsulated in a cyst, the bacteria are well protected against the bactericidal action of antimicrobials even in organs with good vascularization such as the pancreas.</p><p>Relapses of bacteraemia with enterobacteria can occur in patients with underlying gastrointestinal or autoimmune disorders, as in our case. These episodes can be caused by resistant bacteria, which should be considered during perioperative protection after the first sepsis episode. Surgical removal of the focus of infection could be curative.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kethireddy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darovic</surname><given-names>G.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catheter-related and infusion-related sepsis</article-title><source>Crit Care Clin</source><volume>29</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>1015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanz-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Cruz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Cr&#x000e9;ixems</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cercenado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> bloodstream infections: epidemiology and risk factors</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><volume>88</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19282697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maslow</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbeit</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> bacteremia</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Clin Microbiol</source><volume>32</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>710</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brauner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaijser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> bacteraemia&#x02014;clinical characteristics and bacterial properties</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Infect</source><volume>28</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8163833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Hasan</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckel-Passow</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baddour</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent Gram-negative bloodstream infection: a 10-year population-based cohort study</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Infect</source><volume>61</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20378069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Reilly</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malde</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filobbos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of the diagnosis, classification and management of autoimmune pancreatitis</article-title><source>World J Gastrointest Pathophysiol</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24891978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;sterblad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakanen</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huovinen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalava</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Resistance</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection and molecular genetics of extended-spectrum beta-lactamases among cefuroxime-resistant <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Klebsiella</italic> spp. isolates from Finland, 2002&#x02013;2004</article-title><source>Scand J Infect Dis</source><volume>39</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17464864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tenover</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbeit</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goering</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mickelsen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Persing</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpreting chromosomal DNA restriction patterns produced by pulsed field gel electrophoresis: criteria for bacterial strain typing</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Clin Microbiol</source><volume>33</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>2233</fpage><lpage>2239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7494007</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Radiologic description of computed tomographic scan of the body (shortened). Liver is diffusely fatty without clear features of cirrhosis. Spleen is enlarged, with craniocaudal dimension of 14&#x000a0;cm. In hilus region there are small fingerlike liquid retentions that could be traits of abscesses or pseudocysts. Prominent lymphatic node is evident between ventricle and spleen, with dimension of 11&#x000a0;mm. Corpus and cauda of pancreas are atrophic; ducts are widened, maximum 7&#x02013;8&#x000a0;mm at corpus region. Abundance of calcified lesions in caput is compatible with chronic pancreatitis. Region of abscesses in spleen is circled. Breathing artifact is evident in abdominal region.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis of strains. Lanes 1, 5 and 10, control strain; lanes 2&#x02013;4, 2 AmpC overproducer; lanes 6&#x02013;9, ESBL strain. ESBL, extended-spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of isolated <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains from blood culture samples and pancreatic cyst</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sepsis episode</th><th>Organism</th><th colspan="11">Antimicrobial susceptibility (mm) (interpretation)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>TZP</th><th>CIP</th><th>TOB</th><th>SXT</th><th>ETP</th><th>MEM</th><th>NET</th><th>ATM</th><th>CRO</th><th>CXM</th><th>CAZ</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>April 2013</td><td>ESBL <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>22 (I)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>20 (S)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>30 (S)</td><td>30 (S)</td><td>20 (S)</td><td>21 (I)</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td></tr><tr><td>May 2013</td><td>ESBL <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>22 (I)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>20 (S)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>30 (S)</td><td>30 (S)</td><td>20 (S)</td><td>21 (I)</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td></tr><tr><td>August 2013</td><td>AmpC <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>24 (S)</td><td>35 (S)</td><td>22 (S)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>28 (S)</td><td>29 (S)</td><td>ND</td><td>23 (I)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>18 (S)</td><td>21 (I)</td></tr><tr><td>November 2013</td><td>AmpC <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>24 (S)</td><td>35 (S)</td><td>22 (S)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>28 (S)</td><td>29 (S)</td><td>ND</td><td>23 (I)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>18 (S)</td><td>21 (I)</td></tr><tr><td>March 2014</td><td>AmpC <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>24 (S)</td><td>35 (S)</td><td>22 (S)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>28 (S)</td><td>29 (S)</td><td>ND</td><td>23 (I)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>18 (S)</td><td>21 (I)</td></tr><tr><td>March 2014</td><td>ESBL <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>25 (I)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>20 (S)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>30 (S)</td><td>ND</td><td>18 (R)</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td></tr><tr><td>May 2014</td><td>ESBL <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></td><td>25 (I)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>20 (S)</td><td>6 (R)</td><td>27 (S)</td><td>30 (S)</td><td>ND</td><td>18 (R)</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CAZ, ceftazidime; CIP, ciprofloxacin; CRO, ceftriaxone; CXM, cefuroxime; ESBL, extended-spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamase; ETP, ertapenem; I, intermediate; MEM, meropenem; ND, not determined; NET, netilmicin; R, resistant; S, susceptible; TOB, tobramycin; TZP, piperacillin&#x02013;tazobactam.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Antibiotic treatment of patient in periods between bacteraemia episodes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Date</th><th colspan="6">Duration of administration (days)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>TZP</th><th>CIP</th><th>ETP</th><th>VAN</th><th>MEM</th><th>CXM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>April 2013</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>7</td></tr><tr><td/><td>3</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>14</td><td>14</td><td/></tr><tr><td>March 2013</td><td/><td/><td>9</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>May 2013</td><td/><td/><td/><td>19</td><td>19</td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>18</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>August 2013</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>2</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>14</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>4</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>December 2013</td><td>4</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>13</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>February 2014</td><td/><td/><td>13</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>March 2014</td><td/><td/><td>3</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>7</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>7</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>April 2014</td><td/><td>5</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>14</td><td/></tr><tr><td>May 2014</td><td>2</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>14</td><td>14</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CIP, ciprofloxacin; CXM, cefuroxime; ETP, ertapenem; MEM, meropenem; TZP, piperacillin&#x02013;tazobactam; VAN, vancomycin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Drug dosages and routes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Drug abbreviation</th><th>Drug name</th><th>Dosages (per day)</th><th>Administration route</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CXM</td><td>Cefuroxime</td><td>1.5 g&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;3</td><td>iv</td></tr><tr><td>TZP</td><td>Piperacillin&#x02013;tazobactam</td><td>4 g&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;3</td><td>iv</td></tr><tr><td>MEM</td><td>Meropenem</td><td>1 g&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;3</td><td>iv</td></tr><tr><td>ETP</td><td>Ertapenem</td><td>1 g&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;1</td><td>iv, po</td></tr><tr><td>VAN</td><td>Vancomycin</td><td>1 g&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;2</td><td>iv</td></tr><tr><td>CIP</td><td>Ciprofloxacin</td><td>500 mg&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;2</td><td>po</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>iv, intravenous; po, by mouth.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>