<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz J Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz. J. Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brazilian Journal of Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1517-8382</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-4405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26691459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4704631</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838246420140466</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Microbiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing the sources of high fecal coliform levels at an urban tropical
beach</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davino</surname><given-names>Aline Mendon&#x000e7;a Cavalcante</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Melo</surname><given-names>Milena Bandeira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Caffaro</surname><given-names>Roberto Augusto</given-names><suffix>Filho</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Centro de Tecnologia, Universidade Federal de Alagoas, Macei&#x000f3;, AL,
Brazil</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Send correspondence to R.A. Caffaro Filho. Centro de Tecnologia,
Universidade Federal de Alagoas, Macei&#x000f3;, AL, Brazil. E-mail:
<email>roberto@ctec.ufal.br</email>, <email>caffaro.filho@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><p>Associate Editor: Lara Dur&#x000e3;es Sette</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Oct-Dec</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015, Sociedade Brasileira de
Microbiologia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>All the content of the journal, except where otherwise noted, is licensed
under a Creative Commons License CC BY-NC.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Recreational water quality is commonly assessed by microbial indicators such as fecal
coliforms. Macei&#x000f3; is the capital of Alagoas state, located in tropical northeastern
Brazil. Its beaches are considered as the most beautiful urban beaches in the
country. Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach in Macei&#x000f3; was found to be unsuitable for bathing continuously
during the year of 2011. The same level of contamination was not observed in
surrounding beaches. The aim of this study was to initiate the search for the sources
of these high coliform levels, so that contamination can be eventually mitigated. We
performed a retrospective analysis of historical results of fecal coliform
concentrations from 2006 to 2012 at five monitoring stations located in the study
region. Results showed that Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach consistently presented the worst quality
among the studied beaches. A field survey was conducted to identify existing point
and non-point sources of pollution in the area. Monitoring in the vicinity of Jati&#x000fa;ca
was spatially intensified. Fecal coliform concentrations were categorized according
to tide range and tide stage. A storm drain located in northern Jati&#x000fa;ca was
identified as the main point source of the contamination. However, fecal coliform
concentrations at Jati&#x000fa;ca were high during high tides and spring tides even when this
point source was inactive (no rainfall). We hypothesize that high fecal coliform
levels in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach may also be caused by aquifer contamination or, more likely,
from tide washing of contaminated sand. Both of these hypotheses will be further
investigated.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>recreational water quality</kwd><kwd>fecal indicators</kwd><kwd>coastal pollution</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="13"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The exposure to microbial pathogens can result in swimming-related illness. Each year,
millions of cases of gastrointestinal diseases are caused by swimming and bathing in
wastewater-polluted coastal waters (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Shuval,
2003</xref>). Pathogens enter the water through point sources such as sewage outfalls.
Water quality at beaches may also be affected by non-point sources, such as storm water
runoff, sand resuspension, animal fecal inputs, and human bather shedding (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abdelzaher <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>).</p><p>Waterborne pathogens often occur at low concentrations and their detection can be
difficult. Fecal Indicator Bacteria (FIB) is a group of microorganisms of the comensal
flora of the gut used to indicate the potential occurrence of pathogens in water. This
group includes <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, enterococci, clostridia, etc. FIB are
generally more abundant and easily measured than fecal pathogens (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Edge and Boehm, 2011</xref>).</p><p>Fecal Coliforms (FC) are a group of FIB used to assess recreational water quality
throughout the world. CONAMA 274/00 Resolution defines the criteria for recreational
water quality in Brazil, including monitoring methodology, microbiological indicators
and reference concentrations that classify water as suitable or unsuitable for bathing
activities. Regarding the concentrations of FC, Brazilian recreational waters are
considered unsuitable when they exceed 2,500 cfu or MPN/100 mL, or exceed 1,000 cfu or
MPN/100 mL in more than 20% of the samples collected in a five-week monitoring
period.</p><p>Tourism accounts for a large part of income generation in the state capitals of the
Brazilian northeast region, which has a tropical climate. Macei&#x000f3; is the capital of
Alagoas state, and its beaches are considered the most beautiful urban beaches in
Brazil. Beach water quality in Macei&#x000f3; is monitored weekly by the state environmental
agency. According to official data, Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach, one of the main tourist hubs of
Alagoas, showed unsuitable condition for bathing continuously throughout the year of
2011. During this period, the same level of contamination was not observed in
surrounding beaches, namely Ponta Verde and Cruz das Almas. The reasons for this
exceptional contamination at Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach are unknown. The aim of this study was to
initiate the search for the sources of high coliform levels in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach, so that
this contamination can be eventually mitigated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Site description</title><p>Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach has a densely urbanized waterfront, with dozens of hotels and hostels,
as well as bars, restaurants and shops. The surrounding beaches of Ponta Verde
(south) and Cruz das Almas (north) have similar characteristics. In this coastal
region, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>, there are five
monitoring stations for recreational water quality, which are sampled weekly by the
state environmental agency.</p><fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study area, located in a densely urbanized coastal region in the city of
Macei&#x000f3;, capital of Alagoas state, northeastern Brazil. In the figure, on the
right side, the location of the five existing monitoring stations is shown: one
at Praia da Ponta Verde (PTV), one at Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach (JTC) and three at Cruz das
Almas Beach (CRA 1, CRA 2 and CRA 3).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-1019-gf01"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Historical monitoring data analysis</title><p>A retrospective analysis of historical data of fecal coliform (FC) concentrations
obtained from 2006 to 2012 at the five monitoring stations located in the study site
was performed. According to the methodology proposed by <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Boehm <italic>et al</italic>. (2002)</xref>, the results of each year
were categorized into wet season (obtained in the months of May, June and July - MJJ)
and dry season (obtained in the months of November, December and January of the
following year - NDJ). Geometric means and confidence intervals (95%) were calculated
for each category (<italic>e.g</italic>., 2006 MJJ; 2006 NDJ; etc.). Concentrations
of FC, date and time of each sampling were obtained from the state environmental
agency. The accumulated rainfall data were obtained from the state agency responsible
for rainfall monitoring.</p></sec><sec><title>Study of the surroundings of JTC monitoring station</title><p>Due to recurrent high levels of FC observed in 2011, the state environmental agency
temporarily increased the monitoring mesh surrounding JTC monitoring station, adding
a station 100 meters south (JTC S) and 100 meters north (JTC N) of station JTC. FC
concentrations at these stations and also at stations on adjacent beaches (PTV and
CRA 1) were evaluated between August and December 2012. For each station, the
geometric mean and confidence intervals (95%) of FC concentrations were calculated.
FC concentrations in each monitoring station were also categorized according to tide
range (spring/neap, based on lunar cycle) and tide stage (&#x02265; 1 m = high and &#x0003c; 1 m =
low) at sampling. Geometric means and confidence intervals (95%) were calculated for
each category at each monitoring station.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Retrospective evaluation of water quality</title><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref> shows the geometric means of FC
concentrations observed between years 2006 and 2012, during wet (MJJ) and dry seasons
(NDJ), at monitoring stations PTV, JTC, CRA 1, CRA 2 and CRA 3 collectively and
individually. Total rainfall in each season can also be seen in the same figure.</p><fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Geometric means of FC concentrations (lines) observed between the years
2006 and 2012, during wet (MJJ) and dry seasons (NDJ), at monitoring stations
PTV, JTC, CRA 1, CRA 2 and CRA 3, collectively (all monitoring stations) and
individually. Total rainfall in each season is represented by bars. This graph
summarizes results from 841 FC analyses.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-1019-gf02"/></fig><p>As expected, geometric means during wet seasons were always higher than geometric
means of dry seasons. The same was observed by <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Boehm
<italic>et al</italic>. (2002)</xref>, when they evaluated, in a similar
manner, the variability of microbial indicator concentrations in a southern
California beach for a period of 43 years. The rainy season of 2009 was an exception
to this rule. We believe that this was due to systematic analytical or sample
processing errors, which were corrected by the agency after this short period.</p><p>Between 2010 and 2012, we note that JTC station (Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach) showed higher
geometric means when compared to the means of all other monitoring stations taken
together (upper left corner). This becomes more evident, if we consider only the dry
season of 2011, when the geometric mean at JTC was greater than 1,000 MPN/100 mL.</p><p>Since the pollution signal is indiscriminately high during wet seasons, we grouped
the geometric means (in logarithmic scale) for the monitoring stations considering
only the dry season of each year, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure
3</xref>.</p><fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Geometric means (lines) in logarithmic scale and confidence intervals (95%)
of FC concentrations observed between 2006 and 2012, during dry seasons (NDJ),
at monitoring stations PTV, JTC, CRA 1, CRA 2 and CRA 3, collectively (all
monitoring stations) and individually. Total rainfall in each season is
represented by bars. This graph summarizes results from 406 FC
analyses.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-1019-gf03"/></fig><p>During dry seasons, the log geometric mean of FC while considering all monitoring
stations collectively (top left) fell between 2 and 2.5, throughout the study period.
However, JTC station showed higher log geometric means of FC, between 2.5 and 3.
Thus, Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach consistently presented the worst quality among all the beaches
considered in this research.</p><p>For year 2012, we can see a significant improvement in overall quality of surveyed
stations. We attribute it to the atypical low rainfall observed in that year, even
during the wet season.</p></sec><sec><title>Spatial intensification of monitoring around Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach</title><p>In order to assess the cause of the high levels of FC in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach a field survey
was conducted to identify existing point and non-point sources of pollution in the
area. Also, monitoring in the vicinity of station JTC was spatially intensified. Two
new stations, Jati&#x000fa;ca north (JTC N) and Jati&#x000fa;ca south (JTC S) were added to the
monitoring grid and sampled weekly for approximately 4 months between August and
December 2012.</p><p>The coastal discharges found in the study region are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>. Altogether, 6 storm drains and a stream that can
directly influence water quality were identified. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>, the geometric means of FC for the monitoring stations sampled
between August and December 2012 are also presented. The pollution signal was greater
north of JTC monitoring station, near station JTC-N.</p><fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Coastal discharges found in the study region and geometric means of FC with
confidence intervals (95%) for monitoring stations PTV, JTC and CRA 1, plus
additional stations 100 meters south (JTC S) and north (JTC N) of JTC station.
This chart summarizes 85 samples collected between August and December
2012.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-1019-gf04"/></fig><p>Northeastern wind prevails during the months of September to December in Macei&#x000f3;,
generating currents in the north-south direction. Considering this characteristic and
on the basis of the field survey, we identified a storm drain slightly north of the
station JTC-N as the main point source of fecal contamination in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach (storm
drain 1 / <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>).</p><p>Contaminated water discharge into the sea through storm drains has been observed in
some studies in other capitals of the northeast region of Brazil. High FC
concentrations (10<sup>6</sup>-10<sup>7</sup>) were found in storm drains of
Fortaleza and Natal and attributed to contamination by sewage (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cardonha <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Vieira <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). This seems to be a common
situation, since in storm drain 1, in an earlier study, <italic>Escherichia
coli</italic> concentrations of the same magnitude were detected (data not shown).
Therefore, we consider that mitigation of the high FC levels in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach should
start by solving the sewage contamination in this storm drain. This would require a
joint effort of the company that manages the sanitary sewer system and municipality
that manages the storm water system.</p><p>However, the high FC levels found in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach between September and December
2012 cannot be explained only by influence of storm drain 1, since this period is
characteristically dry and 2012 was a year drier than normal. To further assess other
potential causes for the observed high levels of FC, the results were categorized
according to tide range and tide stage at the moment of sampling.</p></sec><sec><title>Categorization of results according to tide range and tide stage</title><p>The calculated geometric means and confidence intervals (95%) after categorization of
FC concentrations for tide range (spring/neap) and stage (high/low) at the moment of
sampling are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref> for monitoring
stations PTV, JTC-S, JTC, JTC-N and CRA-1.</p><fig id="f5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Geometric means (log scale) and confidence intervals (95%) after
categorization of FC concentrations for tide range (spring/neap - upper chart)
and stage (high/low - lower chart) at the moment of sampling for monitoring
stations PTV, JTC-S, JTC, JTC-N and CRA-1. Each chart summarizes 85 FC
concentration analyses between August and December 2012.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-1019-gf05"/></fig><p>During spring tides the range between low and high tide is higher than during neap
tides, promoting higher hydraulic dynamics in coastal waters and having greater
potential to dilute contamination from point sources such as sewage-contaminated
storm drains and sewer outfalls (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Boehm <italic>et
al</italic>., 2002</xref>). The three monitoring stations in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach (JTC
S, JTC and JTC N) showed higher FC geometric means in spring tides than in neap
tides. The point JTC N presented a FC geometric mean over 1,000 MPN/100 mL during
spring tides. This same pattern was not observed in the surrounding stations of Ponta
Verde Cruz das Almas. In Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach, where the main source appears to be a point
source (storm drain 1), it was expected that the highest means should be observed
during neap tides, when there is less dilution of contamination from storm drain 1.
Therefore, results indicate that there must be another source of contamination,
probably non-point source, at work in that region.</p><p>It has been shown that tide stage can influence concentrations of fecal indicator
bacteria (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Boehm and Weisberg, 2005</xref>). In this
study, we observed higher FC geometric means during high tides (except for PTV
station). This finding is consistent with other studies conducted in different
localities. <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Wright <italic>et al</italic>.
(2011)</xref> and <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abdelzaher <italic>et
al</italic>. (2010)</xref> also observed higher concentrations of fecal indicators
during high tides, and <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Boehm <italic>et al</italic>.
(2003)</xref> found the highest concentrations during ebb tides (immediately after
high tide).</p><p>Based on the results of tide categorization, we formulated two hypotheses that could
explain the high levels of FC found in Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach. The first hypothesis is the
contamination of the aquifer near the shoreline. At high tides during spring tides,
seawater penetrates deeper into the aquifer and this contamination can be brought
back to the water column. Indeed, studies have shown that fecal indicator organisms
are not significantly filtered by subsurface sand (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Boehm <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>).</p><p>We conducted a field survey to identify if buildings close to monitoring station JTC
N were connected to the sewer system. Many buildings in the area precede the
establishment of a sewer system, having individual septic systems that should be
discontinued when sewer trunks were available. However, in the two closest blocks
from JTC N monitoring station, we observed two buildings (34 apartments in total), a
hostel (40 apartments), two shops and a mall (24 shops, two restaurants and a bar)
that still do not have connection to the sewer system. <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Cahoon <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref> determined malfunctioning septic
systems as the primary source of water contamination in an estuarine zone in North
Carolina. In the same manner, aquifer contamination at Jati&#x000fa;ca could result from
malfunctioning septic systems. Aquifer contamination could also be caused by leaks in
a sewer trunk line. This hypothesis was proposed by <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Boehm <italic>et al</italic>. (2003)</xref> to explain high concentrations of
fecal indicators in groundwater found at a beach in California. We recommend
conducting a detailed investigation of groundwater quality at Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach, as well
as inspections on the sewer trunk line and septic systems in the region to confirm or
refute this hypothesis.</p><p>The second hypothesis, proposed to explain the high FC levels at Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach
observed even during dry periods, is the presence of high concentrations of FC in its
beach sand. There is evidence showing that fecal microorganisms are able to survive
and multiply in soils and sediments of tropical beaches (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Byappanahalli and Fujioka, 1998</xref>). <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Phillips <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref> observed a correlation between the
concentrations of microorganisms in sand and water, in a study conducted in eight
different beaches in Florida, USA, and suggested that the sand is the predominant
reservoir of fecal microorganisms that impact water quality. To assess this
hypothesis, a detailed investigation of the quality of the sand of Jati&#x000fa;ca Beach is
needed.</p><p>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Wright <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>
conducted a study to assess the sources of high levels of enterococci in a
subtropical beach. They monitored storm drain water quality and also beach sand
quality along a transect perpendicular to shoreline. In addition to high levels of
enterococci found in coastal discharges, the authors observed that the concentration
of enterococci decreases as it moves away from the inter-tidal zone, both in sea and
continent direction, concluding that the source of enterococci in the studied beach
was within the intertidal-zone. Thus, coastal discharges and tide washing of the sand
can play a major role in controlling the levels of fecal indicators in the water
column.</p><p>We believe that the best explanation for the causes of high FC levels in Jati&#x000fa;ca
Beach is very similar to the findings of <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Wright
<italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>. Our results indicate that the influence
of storm drain 1 is the primary source of FC to the water column. When this point
source is inactive (when there's no rainfall) high FC levels can arise from tide
washing of contaminated sand, which explains the higher FC geometric means observed
during high tides and spring tides.</p><p>The systematic assessment of quality of coastal waters is used to classify them in
relation to bathing conditions. However, to ensure public health protection, it is
necessary to find and mitigate the causes of the high levels of contamination often
found in urban coastal areas. In this study, we initiated an assessment of the causes
of high FC levels in an urban coastal environment in a tropical region, and proposed
two hypotheses which will be further investigated in future research.</p><p>This study, similar to others (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cardonha <italic>et
al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Vieira <italic>et
al</italic>., 2002</xref>), exposes the deficiencies in sanitation of an
important city in northeastern Brazil. All these cities have tourism as a major
contributor in their economies. Those who manage to assure good water quality to
their beaches will be at a privileged position, bringing benefits to the health of
its citizens and to the performance of the local economy.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>Acknowledgments</p><p>The authors thank Regina Lucia Pinheiro de Carvalho and Ricardo C&#x000e9;sar de Oliveira from
the environmental state agency (Instituto do Meio Ambiente do Estado de Alagoas - IMA)
for their help in obtaining information and extremely important data for this work, and
Carlos Davino for assistance in the statistical treatment of the data.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelzaher</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Presence of pathogens and indicator microbes at a non-point source
subtropical recreational marine beach</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19966020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisberg</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Tidal forcing of enterococci at marine recreational beaches at
fortnightly and semidiurnal frequencies</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>5575</fpage><lpage>5583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16124289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mrse</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Tiered approach for identification of a human fecal pollution source
at a recreational beach: Case study at Avalon Bay, Catalina Island,
California</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12636264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Decadal and shorter period variability of surf zone water quality at
Huntington Beach, California</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>3885</fpage><lpage>3892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12269739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shellenbarger</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Paytan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Groundwater discharge: Potential association with fecal indicator
bacteria in the surf zone</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>3558</fpage><lpage>3566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15296305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byappanahalli</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Evidence that tropical soil environment can support the growth of
<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>174</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Shellfishing closures in southwest Brunswick County, North Carolina:
Septic tanks <italic>vs</italic>. storm-water runoff as fecal coliform
sources</article-title><source>J Coastal Res</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>327</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardonha</surname><given-names>AMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Fecal pollution in water from storm sewers and adjacent seashores in
Natal, Rio Grande do Norte, Brazil</article-title><source>Int Microbiol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15492936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edge</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><chapter-title>Classical and molecular methods to measure fecal
bacteria</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sadowsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Fecal Bacteria</source><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington D.C</publisher-loc><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>273</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Solo-Gabriele</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Piggot</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Relationships between sand and water quality at recreational
beaches</article-title><source>Water Res</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>6763</fpage><lpage>6769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22071324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuval</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Estimating the global burden of thalassogenic diseases: Human
infectious diseases caused by wastewater pollution of the marine
environment</article-title><source>J Water Health</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15382734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Catter</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saker-Sampaio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The stormwater drain system as a pollution vector of the seashore in
Fortaleza (Cear&#x000e1; State, Brazil)</article-title><source>Braz J Microbiol</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>298</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdelzaher</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Solo-Gabriele</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>The inter-tidal zone is the pathway of input of enterococci to a
subtropical recreational marine beach</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278478</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>