<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Rheum Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann. Rheum. Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">annrheumdis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ard</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0003-4967</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-2060</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27381034</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5264211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">annrheumdis-2015-208913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2015-208913</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Basic and Translational Research</subject></subj-group><series-title>Extended report</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nerve growth factor inhibition with tanezumab influences weight-bearing and subsequent cartilage damage in the rat medial meniscal tear model</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LaBranche</surname><given-names>Timothy P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bendele</surname><given-names>Alison M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>Brian C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gropp</surname><given-names>Kathryn E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>Susan I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bagi</surname><given-names>Cedo M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>Thomas R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grantham</surname><given-names>Lonnie E</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>David L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zorbas</surname><given-names>Mark A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af7">7</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Pfizer Inc</institution>, <addr-line>Cambridge, Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>Blueprint Medicines</institution>, <addr-line>Cambridge, Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><institution>Bolder BioPATH, Inc.</institution>, <addr-line>Boulder, Colorado</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><institution>Pfizer Inc</institution>, <addr-line>Groton, Connecticut</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="af5"><label>5</label><institution>Arbor Analytics, LLC</institution>, <addr-line>Ann Arbor, Michigan</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="af6"><label>6</label><institution>Pfizer Inc</institution>, <addr-line>South San Francisco, California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="af7"><label>7</label><institution>Pfizer Inc</institution>, <addr-line>San Diego, California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><author-notes><fn><p><bold>Handling editor</bold> Tore K Kvien</p></fn><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Timothy P LaBranche, Blueprint Medicines, 38 Sidney Street, Suite 200, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA; <email>tlabranche@blueprintmedicines.com</email></corresp><fn><p>Mr Omura died on 10 July 2015.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>76</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by the BMJ Publishing Group Limited. For permission to use (where not already granted under a licence) please go to http://www.bmj.com/company/products-services/rights-and-licensing/</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p>To investigate whether the effects of nerve growth factor (NGF) inhibition with tanezumab on rats with medial meniscal tear (MMT) effectively model rapidly progressive osteoarthritis (RPOA) observed in clinical trials.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Male Lewis rats underwent MMT surgery and were treated weekly with tanezumab (0.1, 1 or 10&#x02005;mg/kg), isotype control or vehicle for 7, 14 or 28&#x02005;days. Gait deficiency was measured to assess weight-bearing on the operated limb. Joint damage was assessed via histopathology. A second arm, delayed onset of treatment (starting 3&#x02013;8&#x02005;weeks after MMT surgery) was used to control for analgesia early in the disease process. A third arm, mid-tibial amputation, evaluated the dependency of the model on weight-bearing.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Gait deficiency in untreated rats was present 3&#x02013;7&#x02005;days after MMT surgery, with a return to normal weight-bearing by days 14&#x02013;28. Prophylactic treatment with tanezumab prevented gait deficiency and resulted in more severe cartilage damage. When onset of treatment with tanezumab was delayed to 3&#x02013;8&#x02005;weeks after MMT surgery, there was no increase in cartilage damage. Mid-tibial amputation completely prevented cartilage damage in untreated MMT rats.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These data suggest that analgesia due to NGF inhibition during the acute injury phase is responsible for increased voluntary weight-bearing and subsequent cartilage damage in the rat MMT model. This model failed to replicate the hypotrophic bone response observed in tanezumab-treated patients with RPOA.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Knee Osteoarthritis</kwd><kwd>Osteoarthritis</kwd><kwd>Arthritis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Pfizer</institution><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004319</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Knee osteoarthritis (OA) is a condition characterised by pain, inflammation and functional disability.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> OA pain is complex and involves both inflammatory and neuropathic components mediated through persistent tissue injury and release of inflammatory mediators.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Pain treatment for OA is problematic because many standard therapies provide minimal pain relief and do not address underlying mechanisms driving disease pathophysiology.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></p><p>The neurotrophin, nerve growth factor (NGF), is considered a key modulator of pain perception in several chronic pain conditions, including OA.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;7</xref> Tanezumab, a humanised monoclonal antibody, binds NGF and prevents interaction with its receptors (high-affinity transmembrane tyrosine kinase receptor (TrkA) and the low-affinity NGF receptor [p75]).<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Tanezumab provided significant improvement in pain, physical function and patients' global assessments in a number of chronic pain conditions.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9&#x02013;16</xref></p><p>Investigator reports of adverse events initially described as osteonecrosis leading to total joint replacement during the conduct of phase III clinical OA studies led the US Food and Drug Administration to put trials of all NGF inhibitors on partial clinical hold.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17&#x02013;19</xref> Blinded adjudication of the results showed that there was no increase in osteonecrosis, nor frequency of total joint replacement with tanezumab monotherapy. Tanezumab treatment was however associated with increased incidence of rapidly progressive osteoarthritis (RPOA). A retrospective analysis of the data suggested ways to mitigate this risk, and based on these data the clinical hold was lifted to allow further trials to test these risk mitigation approaches.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17&#x02013;20</xref></p><p>The increased frequency of RPOA was unexpected, as no issues with bone or joints were seen in non-clinical studies of anti-NGF therapy using large multiples of the clinical dose.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Also, no evidence of abnormal bone or joint phenotypes exists in humans with TrkA or p75 null mutations other than that observed in congenital pain insensitivity mutations.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Last, in an experimental fracture model, anti-NGF therapy was shown to ameliorate fracture pain without impacting bone healing.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p><p>Meniscal injury and acute meniscectomy are known to increase the risk of knee OA.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Up to 80% of patients with knee OA, as well as a high percentage of age-matched controls, have evidence of meniscal injury at the time of diagnosis yet abnormal load-bearing and joint instability stemming from meniscal injury resulting in substantial OA lesions may take years.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Attempts to model this in animals have produced varied results.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The medial meniscal tear (MMT)-induced joint damage model in rats has many features attractive for an animal model. These animals show joint instability and tibial cartilage damage in as little as 7&#x02013;14&#x02005;days after surgery.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> MMT-induced joint damage lesions are highly reproducible and include articular cartilage proteoglycan loss, chondrocyte degeneration and loss of matrix. Although erosion of cartilage is a feature of this model, rarely does it progress to ulceration within 14 or 28 days. Subchondral bone sclerosis and osteophyte formation, which are compensatory responses to altered mechanical loading and joint instability are present in this model.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26&#x02013;28</xref></p><p>The objective of this study was to characterise the impact of NGF inhibition with tanezumab on voluntary weight-bearing and subsequent articular cartilage damage in MMT rats to see if this model would be useful for investigating potential mechanisms underlying the clinical findings of increased RPOA in patients treated with tanezumab.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Animals and tanezumab administration</title><p>For animal care and use, see online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">supplementary text</xref> S1.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2015-208913.supp1</object-id><label>Supplementary text</label><p><inline-supplementary-material id="ss1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913supp_text.pdf" content-type="local-data"/></p></supplementary-material><p>All animals underwent MMT or sham surgery on study day 0. In MMT surgery rats, the medial meniscus in the right hind limb was cut through the full thickness to simulate a complete tear.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> In sham surgery animals, the knee was opened and the medial meniscus was touched only (not cut). Sham surgery rats received vehicle, and animals that underwent MMT surgery were treated with either isotype control (a non-specific antibody of the same type (immunoglobulin G) and class (2a) as tanezumab), vehicle (10&#x02005;mM trehalose buffer) or tanezumab (0.1, 1 or 10&#x02005;mg/kg) subcutaneously once a week for 7, 14 or 28&#x02005;days.</p><p>In the first arm of the study, treatment began on the day of surgery (day 0, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F1">figure 1</xref>A).<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> To examine the impact of analgesia on weight-bearing and lesion severity, a second arm evaluated delaying the onset of tanezumab treatment (0.1&#x02005;mg/kg weekly) until gait deficiency was no longer evident (day 23); half the animals started receiving treatment on day 23, while the other half were delayed another month (day 57) before treatment was initiated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F1">figure 1</xref>B). In both arms of this study, anti-drug antibodies in plasma were measured, as well as concentration of parent compound in serum to evaluate the potential for clearance of tanezumab via immunologic response.</p><fig id="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Study designs for (A) the initial arm (28-day study), (B) the second arm (delayed-treatment onset study) and (C) the weight-bearing (amputation) study. GA, gait analysis; HA, histopathology analysis; MMT, medial meniscal tear; SC, subcutaneous.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913f01"/></fig><p>To understand the role of weight-bearing in the progression of knee joint damage in the rat MMT model, a third arm of the study evaluated the impact of mid-tibial amputation on MMT lesion progression, eliminating weight-bearing as a variable. The knees were collected 14&#x02005;days after MMT for micro-CT (&#x000b5;CT) imaging, followed by histopathology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F1">figure 1</xref>C). In the first two study arms, the impact of NGF inhibition on subchondral bone, osteophyte size and growth plate thickness was evaluated in MMT rats to assess secondary effects on the overall joint.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Gait deficiency</title><p>Difference in dynamic weight-bearing between the ipsilateral (MMT operated; right side) limb and contralateral (control; left side) limb is an established approach to measuring gait in rat and mouse models of OA.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Voluntary weight-bearing by non-amputated MMT rats was assessed on days &#x02212;3, 3, 7, 14 and 28 in the first arm of the study and additional days 37, 42, 56, 63 and 71 in the delayed-treatment study to confirm that there was no pain relapse in any animals (see online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">supplementary text</xref> S2).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Histopathology and quantitative image analysis</title><p>Microscopy-based semiquantitative scoring of cartilage and bone changes is an established endpoint for describing response to compounds in MMT rats. Cohorts of animals were sacrificed 7, 14 or 28&#x02005;days after surgery or 14&#x02005;days after treatment onset (day 23 or 57). Knees were collected at necropsy and evaluated via light microscopy by a veterinary pathologist as described (see online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">supplementary text</xref> S3).<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Radiography and &#x000b5;CT imaging</title><p>Knees were X-rayed with a MX20 specimen scanner (Faxitron Bioptics, Tucson, Arizona, USA) using recommended settings; exposure 12&#x02013;18&#x02005;s at 31&#x02212;35&#x02005;kV. Radiographs were used to assess gross anatomy of the region of interest (ROI) evaluated by &#x000b5;CT and to inspect bone samples for presence of abnormalities.</p><p>&#x000b5;CT was conducted on the right tibial epiphysis and metaphysis using a MicroCT 100 system (Scanco Medical, Bassersdorf, Switzerland) with the following parameters: 800 slices, 10&#x02005;&#x000b5;m resolution, total scanned area of 8.0&#x02005;mm<sup>2</sup> and source energy of 70&#x02005;kVp, 115&#x02005;&#x000b5;A at 8&#x02005;W to capture the entire proximal tibia section. Cortical and cancellous bone of the entire epiphysis were scanned and analysed in an ROI on 100 consecutive slices with 1.0&#x02005;mm thickness that best represented the central segment of the epiphysis. Parameters included tissue volume (TV), bone volume (BV), BV/TV ratio and bone mineral density (BMD). Cortical and cancellous bone of the proximal metaphysis were scanned and analysed in an ROI on 100 consecutive slices 1&#x02005;mm below the growth plate with a thickness of 1.0&#x02005;mm that best represented the central metaphysis segment. Parameters included TV, BV, BV/TV and BMD. Cancellous bone compartment of the metaphysis was analysed 1&#x02005;mm below the growth plate and extending 3&#x02005;mm distally to include only the secondary spongiosa. Cancellous bone was evaluated in an ROI drawn on 100 consecutive slices with a thickness of 1.0&#x02005;mm that best represented the central segment of the tibia.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Cancellous bone parameters included TV, BV, BV/TV, trabecular number, trabecular thickness, trabecular separation and BMD.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Pharmacokinetics and anti-drug antibody</title><p>To evaluate the potential for clearance of compound via immunologic response, we measured anti-drug antibodies in plasma as well as concentration of tanezumab in serum pharmacokinetic (PK) samples. Blood samples were collected on days 3, 7, 14 and 21. An additional PK sample was taken 4&#x02005;days prior to termination. In the delayed-treatment study, blood samples for PK and anti-drug antibodies were collected on days 16, 30, 57 and 64. PK plasma concentrations of tanezumab were measured using a validated ELISA at ICON Development Solutions (Whitesboro, New York, USA). The lower limit of quantitation in Lewis rat plasma was 50&#x02005;ng/mL. Concentrations below the limit of quantitation were treated as 0&#x02005;ng/mL in the PK calculations. Anti-drug antibodies concentrations in serum were measured using a validated ELISA at ICON Development Solutions. Final assessment of induction of an anti-drug antibodies response was based on comparison of predose and postdose results for each animal.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Body weight change, weight-bearing (gait) deficiency at each time point and histopathology outcomes were analysed. Vehicle and sham surgery groups were compared with the isotype group using a two-sided t test (with a Welch correction for unequal variances if necessary) or Mann-Whitney U test. Each tanezumab-treated group was compared with the isotype group using a two-sided Dunnett or Dunn multiple comparisons test. Significance for all tests was set at p&#x02264;0.05. Gait deficiency was assessed by Dunnett and t-tests.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Tanezumab treatment influences weight-bearing and subsequent cartilage damage in the rat MMT model</title><p>Although MMT rats with intact hind limbs appeared to ambulate normally after surgery, they experienced a measurable weight-bearing (gait) deficiency on the operated limb. Gait deficiency in MMT rats administered vehicle or isotype control peaked 3&#x02005;days after surgery (11.8% and 12.2% decrease, respectively), continued through day 7 and resolved by days 14&#x02013;28 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F2">figure 2</xref>A). In contrast, tanezumab-treated MMT rats exhibited no gait deficiency at any point, indicating that tanezumab-treated MMT rats were bearing full weight on the operated limbs throughout the study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F2">figure 2</xref>). Tanezumab-treated rats exhibited more severe total tibial cartilage substantial degeneration width than either vehicle or isotype controls on days 7, 14 and 28 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F2">figure 2</xref>B). No significant differences in body weight gain were observed over the course of the study. Focal areas of alopecia along the mouth/muzzle began developing on day 14 and were seen in most animals in the 1&#x02005;mg/kg tanezumab group by day 28. Gait analysis was also performed as part of the delayed-treatment study (see online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">supplementary table</xref> S1).</p><fig id="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Weight-bearing corresponds with severity of cartilage damage in MMT rats. (A) Gait deficiency in tanezumab-treated MMT rats compared with control treatment and sham surgery rats. Data expressed as per cent decrease from mean of right and left (SE). Starting on day 7, 10 animals per treatment group were removed for microscopic evaluation. (B) Substantial tibial cartilage degeneration width, as determined by histopathology on days 7, 14 and 28 (n=10 rats/group). (C) Representative photomicrographs (50&#x000d7; magnification) from the isotype and sham surgery controls and tanezumab treatment groups on day 28. Days reflect days after MMT surgery. *p&#x0003c;0.05 versus isotype control; **p&#x0003c;0.01 versus isotype control; ***p&#x0003c;0.001 versus isotype control. CD, cartilage degeneration; MMT, medial meniscal tear.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913f02"/></fig><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2015-208913.supp2</object-id><label>supplementary tables</label><p><inline-supplementary-material id="ss2" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913supp_tables.pdf" content-type="local-data"/></p></supplementary-material><p>There was evidence of a robust, compensatory (hypertrophic) response to the partially destabilised joint. Namely, a time-dependent increase in subchondral bone sclerosis was observed in untreated MMT rats (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913TB1">table 1</xref>), which was exacerbated by tanezumab (statistically significant greater subchondral sclerosis compared with isotype controls on days 7, 14 and 28). Larger osteophyte size was also observed in tanezumab-treated MMT rats compared with isotype controls on days 7 (tanezumab 10&#x02005;mg/kg, p&#x0003c;0.05), 14 (tanezumab 1&#x02005;mg/kg, p&#x0003c;0.01) and 28 (tanezumab 0.1, 1 and 10&#x02005;mg/kg, p&#x0003c;0.001 for all; <xref ref-type="table" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913TB1">table 1</xref>), indicating a time&#x02013;dose relationship with increasing effect. No osteophytes were observed in sham surgery animals. Last, a significant focal increase in growth plate thickness was also observed in tanezumab-treated MMT rats compared with isotype control-treated rats (1 and 10&#x02005;mg/kg on days 14 and 28, p&#x02264;0.05, <xref ref-type="table" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913TB1">table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Histopathology summary, n=10/group; mean (SE)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter/day</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isotype control</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vehicle control</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham surgery</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanezumab<break/>0.1&#x02005;mg/kg/week</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanezumab<break/>1&#x02005;mg/kg/week</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanezumab<break/>10&#x02005;mg/kg/week</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic>Growth plate difference (medial-lateral), &#x000b5;m</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.33 (5.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33 (2.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.33 (2.95)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.67 (10.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.00 (8.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.67 (11.60)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.00 (15.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.67 (7.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.67 (5.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.67 (8.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.00 (26.15)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.33 (22.59)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33 (4.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.00 (4.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00 (5.55)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.33 (10.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185.33 (50.73)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.33 (76.24)**</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic>Medial collateral ligament, &#x000b5;m</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">865.33 (26.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">893.33 (13.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">870.67 (35.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1068.00 (33.46)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1041.33 (48.42)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1128.00 (60.65)***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">637.33 (26.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">633.33 (31.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">641.33 (28.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">664.00 (24.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">689.33 (31.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">688.00 (29.02)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">476.00 (16.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">466.67 (15.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">472.00 (20.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">530.67 (17.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">570.67 (22.82)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">545.33 (15.71)*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic>Bone damage score</italic>&#x02020;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (0.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (0.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40 (0.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (0.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (0.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80 (0.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 (0.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 (0.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 (0.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70 (0.30)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (0.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40 (0.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 (0.16)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40 (0.34)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20 (0.29)*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic>Bone sclerosis score</italic>&#x02021;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (0.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (0.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (0.13)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30 (0.15)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 (0.10)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70 (0.26)***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (0.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 (0.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.10)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50 (0.17)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70 (0.15)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80 (0.13)***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80 (0.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70 (0.26)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (0.13)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 (0.16)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80 (0.13)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70 (0.15)***</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic>Tibial osteophyte size, &#x000b5;m</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.33 (26.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.33 (26.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167.33 (21.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150.33 (29.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223.67 (14.59)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">309.67 (10.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">299.67 (16.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">382.67 (27.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">476.67 (43.62)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">417.67 (41.30)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">581.67 (34.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601.67 (27.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1106.67 (49.20)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1068.33 (75.30)***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1093.33 (50.63)***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*p&#x0003c;0.05 versus isotype control; **p&#x0003c;0.01 versus isotype control; ***p&#x0003c;0.001 versus isotype control.</p></fn><fn><p>&#x02020;Damage to calcified cartilage and subchondral bone was scored on a 6-point numerical scale (0=no changes to 5=increased basophilia; marked to severe fragmentation of calcified cartilage, mesenchymal change in marrow involves up to three-fourths of the total area and articular cartilage has collapsed into the epiphysis to a depth of &#x0003e;250&#x02005;&#x000b5;m from tidemark).</p></fn><fn><p>&#x02021;Medial tibial subchondral/epiphysial bone sclerosis was scored on a 6-point numerical scale (0=no changes to 5=76%&#x02013;100% increase in subchondral or epiphysial trabecular bone thickness in medial versus lateral; very little marrow space remains in medial tibia).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Delaying onset of tanezumab treatment protects against cartilage damage in MMT rats</title><p>Gait deficiency began shortly after MMT surgery and appeared to resolve by days 14&#x02013;28. To confirm whether changes in weight-bearing during this early postoperative period was the principal driver of increased joint damage in the tanezumab-treated MMT rats, we delayed the onset of treatment from day 0 to day 23 (cohort 1) or day 57 (cohort 2). The second cohort in particular initiated treatment well past the time that gait abnormalities normalised. Tanezumab-treated MMT rats had significantly greater cartilage degeneration width than MMT controls when treatment began on day 23 (p=0.035, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F3">figure 3</xref>). However, delaying treatment until weight-bearing fully returned to normal (ie, day 57 but not day 23) resulted in complete protection from worsening of joint damage when compared with control treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F3">figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Delaying onset of treatment from day 0 until after gait deficiency returns to normal (day 57 but not day 23) resulted in no difference in cartilage damage between treated and untreated MMT rats sacrificed 14&#x02005;days after treatment. Data points include mean substantial tibial cartilage degeneration width measurements (tanezumab 0.1&#x02005;mg/kg/week for 14&#x02005;days; n=10 rats/group). Days reflect days after MMT surgery. CD, cartilage degeneration; MMT, medial meniscal tear.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913f03"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Limb amputation protects against joint damage in untreated MMT rats</title><p>As reported,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> as well as in this study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F4">figure 4</xref>) signs of tibial articular cartilage damage appear in normal weight-bearing MMT rats in as early as 7&#x02005;days after surgery. In this study, those changes were prevented by tibial amputation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F4">figure 4</xref>). MMT rats with tibial amputations are not placing weight on their operated limbs, as evidenced by less cortical and cancellous bone in amputated rats than unamputated rats, regardless of whether they had MMT surgery performed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913TB2">table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F4">figure 4</xref>C).</p><table-wrap id="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Bone parameters evaluated ex vivo by &#x000b5;-CT at proximal tibial epiphysis and metaphysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal rats</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMT surgery</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMT plus amputation</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham plus amputation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><italic>Proximal tibial epiphysis (cortical and cancellous bone)</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TV, mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65&#x000b1;0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87&#x000b1;0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83&#x000b1;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67&#x000b1;0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BV, mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76&#x000b1;0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74&#x000b1;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67&#x000b1;0.04<sup>&#x02020;,&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#x000b1;0.05<sup>&#x02020;,&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BV/TV, ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46&#x000b1;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#x000b1;0.03<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#x000b1;0.02<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMD, g/cm<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">985.14&#x000b1;16.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">990.85&#x000b1;14.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">983.37&#x000b1;14.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1005.05&#x000b1;11.05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><italic>Proximal tibial metaphysis (cortical and cancellous bone)</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TV, mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81&#x000b1;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88&#x000b1;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87&#x000b1;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80&#x000b1;0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BV, mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73&#x000b1;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#x000b1;0.06<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#x000b1;0.07<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#x000b1;0.05<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BV/TV, ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20&#x000b1;0.02<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x000b1;0.02<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09&#x000b1;0.02<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMD, g/cm<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">929.74&#x000b1;32.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">922.53&#x000b1;57.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">848.15&#x000b1;40.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">943.72&#x000b1;68.42</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><italic>Proximal tibial metaphysis (cancellous bone only)</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TV, mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96&#x000b1;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BV, mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#x000b1;0.01<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x000b1;0.01<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03&#x000b1;0.02<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BV/TV, ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x000b1;0.01<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x000b1;0.01<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03&#x000b1;0.02<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TbN, 1/mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82&#x000b1;0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65&#x000b1;0.26<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#x000b1;0.19<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#x000b1;0.32<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TbT, &#x000ec;m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056&#x000b1;0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048&#x000b1;0.005<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039&#x000b1;0.007<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041&#x000b1;0.010<sup>&#x02020;,&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TbS, &#x000ec;m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#x000b1;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#x000b1;0.09<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94&#x000b1;4.64<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01&#x000b1;1.23<sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;,&#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMD, g/cm<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">918.43&#x000b1;19.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">923.92&#x000b1;37.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">864.96&#x000b1;41.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">921.60&#x000b1;45.66</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>&#x02020;p&#x0003c;0.05 versus normal; &#x02021;p&#x0003c;0.05 versus MMT; &#x02020;&#x02020;p&#x0003c;0.01 versus normal; &#x02021;&#x02021;p&#x0003c;0.01 versus MMT; &#x02020;&#x02020;&#x02020;p&#x0003c;0.001 versus normal and &#x02021;&#x02021;&#x02021;p&#x0003c;0.001 versus MMT.</p></fn><fn><p>BMD, bone mineral density; BV, bone volume; MMT, medial meniscal tear; TbN, trabecular number; TbS, trabecular separation; TbT, trabecular thickness; TV, tissue volume; &#x003bc;CT, micro-CT.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="ANNRHEUMDIS2015208913F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>The rat MMT model is dependent on dynamic weight-bearing for cartilage damage. Rats underwent either MMT or sham surgery&#x000b1;amputation of the lower tibia. (A) Tibial cartilage substantial degeneration width (SE), as determined by histopathology at day 14 after MMT surgery was observed in MMT rats (no amputation). (B) Representative photomicrographs from each group (16&#x000d7; magnification). (C) Top row depicts X-ray images of the right knee. Second row shows representative two-dimensional &#x003bc;CT images of the proximal tibia (arrows indicate less cancellous bone at metaphysis). Third row shows the image of tibial epiphysis (arrow indicates thicker subchondral bone at medial tibial plateau and arrowhead points at osteophyte). Bottom row shows proximal tibial metaphysis (square indicates areas of secondary spongiosa where cancellous bone has been evaluated). MMT, medial meniscal tear; &#x003bc;CT, micro-CT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="annrheumdis-2015-208913f04"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>PK and anti-drug antibody levels</title><p>For PK and anti-drug antibodies results, see online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">supplementary text</xref> S4.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The serious joint adverse events observed in placebo-controlled clinical trials of anti-NGF antibodies have been adjudicated as either normal or RPOA, the latter characterised by atrophic bone with subchondral insufficiency and/or occasional foci of secondary osteonecrosis.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> This clinical finding was unexpected, since extensive non-clinical safety studies failed to find adverse events of bone or joint. The current study was undertaken to see if a commonly used and relevant arthritis model, the rat MMT, would be useful for further understanding the finding.</p><p>Treating MMT rats with tanezumab did not recapitulate the atrophic bone destruction associated with RPOA in clinical trials. Although anti-NGF treatment early in the MMT disease process influenced weight-bearing and drove additional cartilage damage, secondary changes in subchondral bone were instead hypertrophic (subchondral bone thickening, with osteophytes present). There were however notable findings related to weight-bearing and its impact on joint damage, highlighting that this model is ideal for evaluating the relationship between joint instability, changes in weight/load-bearing and health of articular cartilage damage.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Cartilage damage and subsequent effects on bony tissues (ie, subchondral bone sclerosis and osteophyte formation) appear to be exquisitely sensitive to weight-bearing early in the rat MMT disease process (ie, 0&#x02013;14&#x02005;days after meniscal tear). In contrast, treatment in the chronic phase after gait deficiency had already normalised, similar to the clinical trial experience, had no adverse effects on the joint.</p><p>Mid-tibial amputation protected against MMT-induced joint damage, further suggesting that dynamic weight-bearing is the key driver for joint damage in this model. For instance, there was more severe decreased bone volume in the proximal tibial metaphysis of amputated rats versus normal rats. The idea that weight-bearing drives joint damage in the MMT rat is also supported by observations that MMT rats given intra-articular injections of irritating substances leading to joint swelling and pain actually result in decreased cartilage damage and bone sclerosis scores, largely because the rats are unwilling to bear weight on the joint (A. Bendele, unpublished observations).<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p><p>In this study, MMT rats exhibited gait deficiency on the operated limb shortly after surgery, which returned to baseline by days 14&#x02013;28. Transection of the meniscus leads to this gait abnormality, not general surgery trauma, as animals undergoing sham surgery exhibited no change in weight-bearing at any point. Treatment with tanezumab at &#x02265;0.1&#x02005;mg/kg resulted in MMT rats behaving similarly to sham surgery rats, since they did not exhibit altered weight-bearing. These results, combined with other work investigating the role of NGF in a meniscal transection rat model of OA, suggest that analgesia can significantly influence voluntary weight-bearing.</p><p>Results suggest that at least two separable phases of pain behaviours occur in the rat MMT model: (1) an early phase, in which gait abnormality is present and dynamic weight-bearing significantly alters the future trajectory of joint damage, and (2) a later phase, in which there is no detectable gait abnormality and tissue destruction is no longer sensitive to NGF inhibition. From this, we propose that increased joint damage seen in tanezumab-treated MMT rats was due to an increase in voluntary weight-bearing early in the disease process and not due to direct toxic effect of tanezumab on cartilage or bone. To support this, an additional arm of the study was conducted delaying onset of tanezumab treatment from day 0 to day 23 or 57 after MMT surgery when gait deficiency was no longer present. Overall, the results presented here support the conclusion that analgesia may exacerbate joint damage when it is present during the early phase. This is likely due to mechanical overloading shortly after meniscal injury. The relevance of this model to RPOA reported in human clinical trials should be considered. Specifically, results from this study may help guide future clinical trial design by suggesting exclusion criteria (ie, patients deemed sensitive to mechanical overloading/radiographic evidence of bone or joint insufficiency).</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors acknowledge the excellent technical assistance of Phil Bendele at Bolder BioPATH for the tibial amputation model, as well as ICON laboratories for the determination of PK and anti-drug antibodies parameters. The authors also acknowledge Drs Larry Whiteley, Nasir Khan and Lloyd Dethloff (Pfizer) for their guidance and critical review of this work. Medical writing support was provided by Joseph Oleynek at Engage Scientific Solutions and was funded by Eli Lilly &#x00026; Co. and Pfizer.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> TPL, KEG, TRC, DLS and MAZ designed the study. BCO, AMB, SIH and CMB generated data for the study. LEG performed the statistical analyses. All authors were involved in data interpretation and writing and reviewing the manuscript.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was funded by Pfizer, Inc. and Eli Lilly &#x00026; Co.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> KEG, SIH, CMB, TRC and MAZ are employees of Pfizer and own stock and/or stock options in Pfizer. TPL and DLS were employees of Pfizer at the time of these studies and own stock and/or stock options in Pfizer. LEG is a contracted resource of and owns stock in Pfizer.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> Oversight by local institutional animal care and use committees.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rasch</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of knee osteoarthritis in the United States: arthritis data from the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 1991&#x02013;94</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>2271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17013996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langford</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wodehouse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Arthritis and pain. Current approaches in the treatment of arthritic pain</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17572915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>French</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bermingham</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The nerve of osteoarthritis pain</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>1019</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/acr.20142">doi:10.1002/acr.20142</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20589688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hefti</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walicke</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Novel class of pain drugs based on antagonism of NGF</article-title>. <source>Trends Pharmacol Sci</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2005.12.001">doi:10.1016/j.tips.2005.12.001</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16376998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantyh</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koltzenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Antagonism of nerve growth factor-TrkA signaling and the relief of pain</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/ALN.0b013e31821b1ac5">doi:10.1097/ALN.0b013e31821b1ac5</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21602663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Angiogenesis and nerve growth factor at the osteochondral junction in rheumatoid arthritis and osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1852</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/rheumatology/keq188">doi:10.1093/rheumatology/keq188</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20581375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dawbarn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Targeting nerve growth factor in pain: what is the therapeutic potential?</article-title>
<source>BioDrugs</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2165/0063030-200822060-00002">doi:10.2165/0063030-200822060-00002</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18998753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdiche</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Malashock</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Probing the binding mechanism and affinity of tanezumab, a recombinant humanized anti-NGF monoclonal antibody, using a repertoire of biosensors</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1326</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1110/ps.035402.108">doi:10.1110/ps.035402.108</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18505735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Radin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Tanezumab reduces osteoarthritic knee pain: results of a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III trial</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>790</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpain.2012.05.006">doi:10.1016/j.jpain.2012.05.006</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22784777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Radin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Tanezumab reduces osteoarthritic hip pain: results of a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III trial</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/art.37950">doi:10.1002/art.37950</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23553790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gimbel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and Safety of Intravenous Tanezumab in Osteoarthritis Hip and Knee Pain: comparison to Placebo and Naproxen in Two Phase III Studies (NCT00830063 &#x00026; NCT00863304)</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>
<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ampainsoc.org/abstract/view/4761/">http://www.ampainsoc.org/abstract/view/4761/</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moldwin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cossons</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Proof of concept trial of tanezumab for the treatment of symptoms associated with interstitial cystitis</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>1716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.juro.2010.12.088">doi:10.1016/j.juro.2010.12.088</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21420111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borenstein</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Birbara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of tanezumab in the treatment of chronic low back pain</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>2248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pain.2011.05.003">doi:10.1016/j.pain.2011.05.003</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21696889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kivitz</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gimbel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bramson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of tanezumab versus naproxen in the treatment of chronic low back pain</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>1009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pain.2013.03.006">doi:10.1016/j.pain.2013.03.006</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23628600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schnitzer</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Birbara</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Tanezumab for the treatment of pain from osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>363</volume>:<fpage>1521</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa0901510">doi:10.1056/NEJMoa0901510</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20942668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spierings</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fidelholtz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolfram</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A phase III placebo- and oxycodone-controlled study of tanezumab in adults with osteoarthritis pain of the hip or knee</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>1603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pain.2013.04.035">doi:10.1016/j.pain.2013.04.035</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23707270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Food and Drug Administration Center for Drug Evaluation and Research</collab>. <comment>Background Materials. Meeting of the Arthritis Advisory Committee (AAC)</comment><source>.</source>
<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommittees/CommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/ArthritisDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM295202.pdf">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommittees/CommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/ArthritisDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM295202.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 10 Apr 2012</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Food and Drug Administration Center for Drug Evaluation and Research. Background Materials Addendum. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommittees/CommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/ArthritisDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM295203.pdf">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommittees/CommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/ArthritisDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM295203.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 10 Apr 2012</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Pfizer Inc</collab>. <article-title>Arthritis Advisory Committee Briefing Document</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommittees/CommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/ArthritisDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM295205.pdf">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommittees/CommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/ArthritisDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM295205.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 10 Apr 2012</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnitzer</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spierings</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of tanezumab monotherapy or combined with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs in the treatment of knee or hip osteoarthritis pain</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-204905">doi:10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-204905</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24625625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorbas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A multiple-dose toxicity study of tanezumab in cynomolgus monkeys</article-title>. <source>Regul Toxicol Pharmacol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.yrtph.2010.11.005">doi:10.1016/j.yrtph.2010.11.005</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21130822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koewler</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buus</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of a monoclonal antibody raised against nerve growth factor on skeletal pain and bone healing after fracture of the C57BL/6J mouse femur</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1732</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1359/jbmr.070711">doi:10.1359/jbmr.070711</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17638576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dewire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The clinical importance of meniscal tears demonstrated by magnetic resonance imaging in osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>85-A</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12533565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendele</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Animal models of osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15758487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerwin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bendele</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glasson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The OARSI histopathology initiative&#x02014;recommendations for histological assessments of osteoarthritis in the rat</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>18</volume>(Suppl <issue>3</issue>):<fpage>S24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2010.05.030">doi:10.1016/j.joca.2010.05.030</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendele</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Animal models of osteoarthritis in an era of molecular biology</article-title>. <source>J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15758375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laemont</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Surgically induced osteoarthritis in the rat results in the development of both osteoarthritis-like joint pain and secondary hyperalgesia</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1041</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2006.05.001">doi:10.1016/j.joca.2006.05.001</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16769229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janusz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bendele</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Induction of osteoarthritis in the rat by surgical tear of the meniscus: inhibition of joint damage by a matrix metalloproteinase inhibitor</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>10</volume>:
<fpage>785</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053/joca.2002.0823">doi:10.1053/joca.2002.0823</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Nerve growth factor mediates hyperalgesia and cachexia in auto-immune arthritis</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pain.2005.03.039">doi:10.1016/j.pain.2005.03.039</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15927377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mapp</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Augmented pain behavioural responses to intra-articular injection of nerve growth factor in two animal models of osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1710</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-203416">doi:10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-203416</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23852764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knights</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Modifications of gait as predictors of natural osteoarthritis progression in STR/Ort mice</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1832</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/art.38616">doi:10.1002/art.38616</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bagi</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Alternative approach to assessment of bone quality using micro-computed tomography</article-title>. <source>Bone</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>326</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bone.2004.02.019">doi:10.1016/j.bone.2004.02.019</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15207774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Serious joint-related adverse events in randomized controlled trials of anti-nerve growth factor monoclonal antibodies</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>23</volume>(Suppl <issue>1</issue>):<fpage>S18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2014.10.005">doi:10.1016/j.joca.2014.10.005</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25527216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>