<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med (Wars)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Med (Wars)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2391-5463</issn><publisher><publisher-name>De Gruyter Open</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28352754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5368881</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/med-2015-0094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">med-2015-0094</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Retinal tear: an unusual complication of ocular toxoplasmosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Celebi</surname><given-names>Ali Riza Cenk</given-names></name><xref rid="c1-med-2015-0094" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="af1-med-2015-0094">Acibadem University School of Medicine Department of Ophthalmology Turgut Ozal Boulevard, No:16 Pbx: 34303 Kucukcekmece, Istanbul, 
<country>Turkey</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kilavuzoglu</surname><given-names>Ayse Ebru</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="af2-med-2015-0094">Acibadem University School of Medicine Department of Ophthalmology Istanbul/
<country>Turkey</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Altiparmak</surname><given-names>Ugur Emrah</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="af3-med-2015-0094">Acibadem University School of Medicine Department of Ophthalmology Istanbul/
<country>Turkey</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cosar</surname><given-names>Cemile Banu</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="af4-med-2015-0094">Acibadem University School of Medicine Department of Ophthalmology Istanbul/
<country>Turkey</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ozkiris</surname><given-names>Abdullah</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="af5-med-2015-0094">Acibadem University School of Medicine Department of Ophthalmology Istanbul/
<country>Turkey</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-med-2015-0094"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Tel: 90 212 404 40 84 Fax: 90 212 404 48 39, E-mail:<email>cenk.celebi@acibadem.edu.tr</email>, <email>arcenkcelebi@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Ali Riza Cenk Celebi et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0"><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>It is aimed to report on a 16-year-old patient with acquired ocular toxoplasmosis complicated by a retinal tear.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Retrospective medical chart review</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A 16-year-old Caucasian female presented with vision loss in her right eye. In addition to a white active lesion between the fovea and the optic nerve head, marked vitreous opacification was noted. She was diagnosed with ocular toxoplasmosis. The patient was treated with oral azithromycin, clindamycin, and trimethoprimsulfamethoxazole. One month later, retinochoroiditis resolved and vitreous cleared. Three months after onset, patient presented with floaters in the right eye and a retinal tear was located at the temporal region of the retina. Prophylactic argon laser treatment that encircled the retinal tear was performed. No other abnormalities were noted during 6 months of follow-up.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Retinal tear associated with ocular toxoplasmosis is rare; however, a retinal tear can occur due to vitreoretinal traction following post-inflammatory structural alteration of the vitreous. Retinal tears may be seen during the healing phase, when the inflammation turns into tightening of vitreous substance. Careful retinal examination in cases of ocular toxoplasmosis is warranted, especially in patients with severe vitreous inflammation.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ocular toxoplasmosis</kwd><kwd>retinal tear</kwd><kwd>argon laser photocoagulation</kwd><kwd>vitreoretinal traction</kwd><kwd>vitreous inflammation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1 Introduction</title><p><italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection is well known and occurs worldwide; toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis is the most common form of posterior uveitis caused by <italic>T. gondii</italic> in otherwise healthy individuals [<xref rid="b1-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis accounted for 7.2% of all cases of uveitis in a referral center in Turkey [<xref rid="b2-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Classically, toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis appears as a focus of inner retinitis adjacent to an old chorioretinal scar, and is accompanied by vitritis. Active ocular toxoplasmosis, also caused by <italic>T. gondii</italic>, is characterized by focal necrotizing retinochoroiditis, which in 90 percent of cases is unilateral [<xref rid="b2-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. During the healing process the acute lesions resolves, leaving a chorioretinal scar with well-defined hyperpigmented borders and central chorioretinal atrophy [<xref rid="b3-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Nonetheless, considerable variation in the clinical features of ocular toxoplasmosis led some to consider if atypical cases represent different forms of the disease [<xref rid="b4-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Vitreoretinal complications of toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis include retinal tear, exudative and/or rhegmatogenous retinal detachment, vitreous hemorrhage, epiretinal membrane, and choroidal neovascularization [<xref rid="b5-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Herein we report on a patient with acquired ocular toxoplasmosis complicated by a retinal tear. To the best of our knowledge, the presented case is the youngest with acquired ocular toxoplasmosis complicated by a retinal tear.</p></sec><sec><title>2 Case presentation</title><p>A 16-year-old Caucasian female presented to our department with sudden vision loss in her right eye. Systemic evaluation was negative for any systemic illnesses. She was not on any systemic medications nor had a family history of eye illnesses. Visual acuity was count-fingers at 50 cm in the right eye and 20/20 with &#x02013;1.75 diopter spherical correction in the left eye. There was +2 aqueous cells in the anterior chamber and +2 anterior vitreous cells in the right eye. Corneal endothelial mutton-fat keratic precipitates were also noted in the right eye. Slit-lamp examination of the left eye was unremarkable. Intraocular pressure was 14 mmHg in both eyes.</p><p>Dilated funduscopic examination revealed a diffuse, elevated white-yellow lesion in the right retina with 1.5 times the diameter of the optic disc in size that was located half a disc diameter temporal to the optic nerve head. Focal condensation of inflammatory cells in the vitreous was observed overlying an area of active chorioretinitis (<xref rid="f1-med-2015-0094" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Chest x-ray, complete blood count, and serum biochemistry, including angiotensin-converting enzyme, were within normal limits. Purified protein derivative of tuberculin was negative. Titers for <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> -specific IgM (3.1 IU/mL) and IgG (4.3 IU/mL) were elevated. The patient was consulted to the pulmonology department due to suspicion of tuberculosis and sarcoidosis, both of which were ruled out. Based on the serological findings and clinical presentation, the ocular toxoplasmosis was diagnosed.</p><p>The patient was put on oral clindamycin 300 mg q.i.d, azithromycin 500 mg q.d, and trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole 800/160 mg q.d, and for the right eye only topical anti-inflammatory treatment with prednisolone acetate ophthalmic every two hours and tropicamide ophthalmic t.i.d. After 1 week of treatment, the patient&#x02019;s visual acuity in the right eye increased to 20/160. Dilated funduscopic examination of the right eye showed a decrease in vitreous haze (<xref rid="f2-med-2015-0094" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). After 1 month of treatment visual acuity in the right eye was 20/60 and dilated funduscopic examination of the right eye showed a decrease in the size of the macular infiltrate (<xref rid="f3-med-2015-0094" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>After 3 months of treatment, the patient presented with complaints of flashing lights and floaters in her right eye. Dilated funduscopic examination showed a horseshoe retinal tear at the 9 o&#x02019;clock position. The retinal tear was treated with Argon laser photocoagulation immediately (<xref rid="f4-med-2015-0094" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). At the 6-month follow-up visual acuity in the right eye was 20/40 and slit-lamp examination findings were within normal limits. Additionally, dilated funduscopic examination of the right eye showed fibrotic tissue at the toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis spot, and active vitreous inflammation was not noted. Furthermore, the horseshoe retinal tear was well circumscribed with laser scars (<xref rid="f5-med-2015-0094" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>The research related to human use has been complied with all the relevant national regulations, institutional policies and in accordance the tenets of the Helsinki Declaration.</p><p>Patient&#x02019;s written consent was obtained regarding the fundus images that were used in this manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>3 Discussion</title><p>The hallmark of the ocular toxoplasmosis includes focal necrotizing retinochoroiditis that results in a characteristic adjacent or nearby retinochoroidal atrophic scar. However, a variety of less common, &#x0201c;atypical&#x0201d; presentations may occur; punctate outer retinal toxoplasmosis, retinal vasculitis, retinal vascular occlusions, rhegmatogenous and serous retinal detachments, unilateral pigmentary retinopathy mimicking retinitis pigmentosa, neuroretinitis and other forms of optic neuropathy, and scleritis [<xref rid="b6-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The presented case had ocular toxoplasmosis complicated by a retinal tear. The precise frequency of retinal tears in patients with ocular toxoplasmosis is unknown, though toxoplasmic retinochoroidits cases with retinal tear have been reported. A study that included 150 consecutive patients with toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis reported that 5% of patients had retinal tears [<xref rid="b7-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The same study showed that attacks of active ocular toxoplasmosis preceded retinal tears were characterized by severe intraocular inflammation. The occurrence of retinal tears in patients with uveitis may be related to early posterior vitreous detachment caused by the intraocular inflammatory process [<xref rid="b8-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Bodanowitz et al. [<xref rid="b9-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] reported that retinal tear in patients with retinitis is associated with toxoplasmosis and that retinal tear is a rare complication of toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis. It was proposed that a retinal tear could occur due to vitreoretinal traction following structural alteration of the vitreous.</p><p>It is noteworthy that in over 90 percent of acquired cases, attacks of active ocular toxoplasmosis characterized by severe intraocular inflammation preceded retinal tear. Vitritis in patients with ocular toxoplasmosis, varying in severity, is quite common and can even be an initial finding before the development of retinitis. As the area of retinochoroiditis increases there is a tendency for the severity of vitritis to increase [<xref rid="b10-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Dense vitreous inflammation in cases of ocular toxoplasmosis and retinal tear was observed, and profuse inflammation of the vitreous tissue was reported to be the cause of retinal tears [<xref rid="b9-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Lafaut et al. [<xref rid="b11-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] reported that proliferative protrusion of the sensory retinal layer and a secondary scar caused by ocular toxoplasmosis cause retinal tear in patients with active ocular toxoplasmosis due to severe intraocular inflammation.</p><p>The use of corticosteroids for ocular toxoplasmosis remains controversial; these drugs are primarily used to alleviate severe inflammation and, as such, might play a role in the development of vitreoretinal traction and preretinal membranes [<xref rid="b12-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. An earlier study reported that 4 patients with ocular toxoplasmosis and retinal tear used systemic corticosteroids together with anti-parasitic agents before the onset of ocular toxoplasmosis. The researchers posited that corticosteroid monotherapy might induce extremely severe inflammation resulting in fulminant ocular disease; therefore it is not recommended [<xref rid="b13-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Visual prognosis of retinal detachment due to retinal tear as a complication of ocular toxoplasmosis was reported to be very poor, as legal blindness occurs in 56% of cases [<xref rid="b14-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. It was also reported that patients with an attached retinal tear retained their visual potential, which might be because the retinal tears were diagnosed during ophthalmological examinations performed for an active attack of ocular toxoplasmosis, resulting in early treatment [<xref rid="b15-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It was posited that laser treatment of asymptomatic attached retinal tears in an eye with recurrent intraocular inflammation is justified. First, there is the additional risk of vitreous traction and secondly the visual prognosis after surgical repair for retinal detachment in ocular toxoplasmosis was poor [<xref rid="b12-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Extra-macular and macular localization of retinitis were not associated with an increase in the risk of retinal detachment, although extra-macular lesions were associated with more severe vitreous inflammation [<xref rid="b10-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Tugal-Tutkun et al. [<xref rid="b16-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] reported that there was not a gender predilection and that 86.2% of patients diagnosed as ocular toxoplasmosis were aged &#x0003c;35 years. Numerous studies have shown that the severity of ocular toxoplasmosis increases with age [<xref rid="b17-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="b18-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The presented case was aged 16 years at the time of diagnosis and to the best of our knowledge is the youngest case of ocular toxoplasmosis complicated by retinal tear. The presented patient had a macular lesion. Macular or juxtapapillary involvement with active lesions was reported to be significantly more common in previously uninvolved eyes than in eyes with preexisting scars. The rich blood supply of the macular region of the choroid may explain the predilection for this area if dissemination to the eye from other sites is presumed to occur in patients with primary ocular toxoplasmosis [<xref rid="b16-med-2015-0094" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>4 Conclusion</title><p>Retinal tear associated with ocular toxoplasmosis is rare; however, a retinal tear can occur due to vitreoretinal traction following post-inflammatory structural alteration of the vitreous. Retinal tears may be seen during the healing phase, when the inflammation turns into tightening of vitreous substance. As such, we recommend careful retinal examination in patients with ocular toxoplasmosis, especially patients with severe intraocular vitreous inflammation. In cases of toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis diagnostic attention should not be limited to evaluation of the optical transparency of the vitreous; the vitreous structure should also be assessed and, if changes are noted, funduscopy should be repeated in order to find any retinal tears in a timely fashion.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1-med-2015-0094"><p><bold>Conflict of interest statement:</bold> Authors state no conflict of interest</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-med-2015-0094"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCannel</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Helm</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornell</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmer</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causes of uveitis in the general practice of ophthalmology UCLA Community-Based Uveitis Study Group</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1996</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8554079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-med-2015-0094"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karada&#x0011f;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakurt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saricao&#x0011f;lu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasiripi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causes of uveitis in a referral hospital in Ankara, Turkey</article-title><source>Ocul Immunol Inflamm</source><year>2005</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15804769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-med-2015-0094"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Belfort</surname><given-names>R</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Remington</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasmosis</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pepose</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelmus</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ocular Infection &#x00026; immunity</source><edition>1st edn</edition><publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name><publisher-loc>St Louis, MO</publisher-loc><fpage>1183</fpage><lpage>1223</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-med-2015-0094"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klaren</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kijlstra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasmosis, an overview with emphasis on ocular involvement</article-title><source>Ocul Immmunol Inflamm</source><year>2002</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-med-2015-0094"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giralt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alforja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bur&#x000e9;s-Jesltrup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaroli-Marano</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Corcostegui</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pars plana vitrectomy for vitreoretinal complications of ocular toxoplasmosis</article-title><source>Eur J Ophhalmol</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-med-2015-0094"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perrotta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobili</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grassia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebastiani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmeggiani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Costagliola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bilateral neuroretinitis in a 6-year-old boy with acquired toxoplasmosis</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14557195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-med-2015-0094"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch-Driessen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stilma</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinal detachment in ocular toxoplasmosis</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10647716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-med-2015-0094"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucena Dda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena Dda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lucena</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><trans-title xml:lang="en">Retinal tears in toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis: case series</trans-title><source>Arq Bras Oftalmol</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-med-2015-0094"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bodanowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><trans-title xml:lang="en">Retinal tear in retinochoroiditis toxoplasmotica</trans-title><source>Klin Monbl Augenheilkd</source><year>1996</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8648989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-med-2015-0094"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Dam-van Loon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Muccioli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovakimyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barisani-Asenbauer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><collab>International Ocular Toxoplasmosis Research Group</collab><article-title>Intraocular inflammation associated with ocular toxoplasmosis: relationships at initial examination</article-title><source>Am J Ophthamol</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>865</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-med-2015-0094"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lafaut</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leys</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dralands</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Laey</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vasoproliferative retinal tumors associated with peripheral chorioretinal scars in presumed congenital toxoplasmosis</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>237</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10654174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-med-2015-0094"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kianersi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Naderi Beni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghanbari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ocular toxoplasmosis and retinal detachment: five case reports</article-title><source>Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23090818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-med-2015-0094"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch-Driessen</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sense and nonsense of corticosteroid administration in the treatment of ocular toxoplasmosis</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>1998</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>858</fpage><lpage>860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9828766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-med-2015-0094"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch-Driessen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Berendschot</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ongkosuwito</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ocular toxoplasmosis: cinical features and prognosis of 154 patients</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2002</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11986090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15-med-2015-0094"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desmettre</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Labalette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantinides</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laser photocoagulation around the foci of toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis: a descriptive statistical analysis of 35 patients with long-term follow-up</article-title><source>Ophthalmologica</source><year>1996</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9148260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16-med-2015-0094"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tugal-Tutkun</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Corum</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ot&#x000fc;k</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Urgancioglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active ocular toxoplasmosis in Turkish patients: a report on 109 cases</article-title><source>Int Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17318320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17-med-2015-0094"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fardeau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Romand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassoux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettembourg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Thulliez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehoang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis with atypical clinical features</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2002</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18-med-2015-0094"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Greven</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudhalkar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vine</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atypical, severe toxoplasmic retinochoroiditis in elderly patients</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1997</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9022104</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1-med-2015-0094" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The patient&#x02019;s funduscopic examination at initial presentation showed dense vitreous inflammation with yellow-white macular infiltrate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="med-2015-0094f1"/></fig><fig id="f2-med-2015-0094" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>After 1 week of treatment, funduscopy showed a decrease in vitreous inflammation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="med-2015-0094f2"/></fig><fig id="f3-med-2015-0094" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>After 1 month of treatment funduscopic examination showed a marked decrease in vitreous inflammation and a decrease in the size of the macular infiltrate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="med-2015-0094f3"/></fig><fig id="f4-med-2015-0094" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Dilated funduscopic examination showed a new horseshoe retinal tear that was circumscribed with Argon laser photocoagulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="med-2015-0094f4"/></fig><fig id="f5-med-2015-0094" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>At the 6-month follow-up dilated funduscopic examination showed no vitreous inflammation and that the horseshoe retinal tear was circumscribed by old pigmented Argon laser photocoagulation scars<bold>.</bold></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="med-2015-0094f5"/></fig></floats-group></article>